<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6303865</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-018-4014-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Note</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RNA sequencing of kidney and liver transcriptome obtained from wild cynomolgus macaque <italic>(Macaca fascicularis</italic>) originating from Peninsular Malaysia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ee Uli</surname><given-names>Joey</given-names></name><address><email>joeyeeuli@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1399-971X</contrib-id><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>Christina Seok-Yien</given-names></name><address><email>chrisyong@upm.edu.my</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>Swee Keong</given-names></name><address><email>skyeap2005@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alitheen</surname><given-names>Noorjahan Banu</given-names></name><address><email>noorjahan@upm.edu.my</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rovie-Ryan</surname><given-names>Jeffrine J.</given-names></name><address><email>jeffrine@wildlife.gov.my</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mat Isa</surname><given-names>Nurulfiza</given-names></name><address><email>nurulfiza@upm.edu.my</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Soon Guan</given-names></name><address><email>sgtan_98@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2231 800X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11142.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, Faculty of Biotechnology and Biomolecular Sciences, </institution><institution>Universiti Putra Malaysia, </institution></institution-wrap>Serdang, Selangor Malaysia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2231 800X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11142.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Universiti Putra Malaysia, </institution></institution-wrap>43400 Serdang, Selangor Malaysia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>China-ASEAN College of Marine Sciences, Xiamen University, Sepang, Selangor Malaysia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>National Wildlife Forensic Laboratory, Ex-Situ Conservation Division, Department of Wildlife and National Parks, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>923</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par1">Using high-throughput RNA sequencing technology, this study aimed to sequence the transcriptome of kidney and liver tissues harvested from Peninsular Malaysia cynomolgus macaque (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>). <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> are significant nonhuman primate models in the biomedical field, owing to the macaque&#x02019;s biological similarities with humans. The additional transcriptomic dataset will supplement the previously described Peninsular Malaysia <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> transcriptomes obtained in a past endeavour.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">A total of 75,350,240 sequence reads were obtained via Hi-seq 2500 sequencing technology. A total of 5473 significant differentially expressed genes were called. Gene ontology functional categorisation showed that cellular process, catalytic activity, and cell part categories had the highest number of expressed genes, while the metabolic pathways category possessed the highest number of expressed genes in the KEGG pathway analysis. The additional sequence dataset will further enrich existing <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> transcriptome assemblies, and provide a dataset for further downstream studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13104-018-4014-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic></kwd><kwd>Cynomolgus macaque</kwd><kwd>RNA sequencing</kwd><kwd>Transcriptome</kwd><kwd>Biomedical science</kwd><kwd>Kidney</kwd><kwd>Liver</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Research University Grant Scheme</institution></funding-source><award-id>GPIPB/2013/9413602</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par13">Cynomolgus macaques (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>) are nonhuman primate (NHP) models significant to biomedicine due to their close evolutionary relationship with humans. The cynomolgus macaque&#x02019;s recapitulation of human physiology, genetics, and behaviour is advantageous as translational models for various studies in the biomedical field, including drug development and safety testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Cynomolgus macaque individuals from different geographical locations have been shown to exhibit genetic characteristics that varies between geographical origins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Therefore, it is vital that the genomes and transcriptomes of cynomolgus macaque NHP models originating from different geographical locations are sequenced as a reference for future biomedical research design and implementation.</p><p id="Par14">This study describes the RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) of two tissues&#x02014;kidney and liver&#x02014;harvested from wild Peninsular Malaysian cynomolgus macaques, and is an extension of a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] whereby the lymph node, spleen, and thymus transcriptomes of wild Peninsular Malaysian <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> were also sequenced with RNA-seq technology. An additional 75,350,240 sequence reads were obtained from this study, supplementing the previous wild Peninsular Malaysian <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> dataset for downstream applications. Furthermore, additional Malaysian cynomolgus macaque RNA-seq datasets will further furnish the cynomolgus macaque genome and transcriptome annotations and also provide a valuable asset for biomedical studies involving cynomolgus macaques.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Main text</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Samples</title><p id="Par15">Two male conflict macaques that appeared to belong in the same family group were captured by the Department of Wildlife and National Parks (DWNP) from the state of Selangor. Visual examination showed that the macaques were free of disease. Euthanisation and harvesting of organs were also performed by authorised and qualified veterinarians of DWNP. In brief, the macaques were sedated intramuscularly using general anaesthesia (combination of ketamine, 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;mg/kg and xylazine, 0.2&#x02013;0.4&#x000a0;mg/kg) before a lethal dosage of Dolethal<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> were given intravenously. Harvested kidney and liver tissues were stored in RNAlater RNA Stabilization Agent (Qiagen). Total RNA extraction was carried out with RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). A modified protocol was employed to remove genomic DNA contamination by incorporating Epicentre&#x02019;s DNase I solution. RNA extract integrity was determined using 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Inc., United States of America) via RNA Pico chip. Samples with RIN&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;7.0 were selected for library construction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>High-throughput sequencing, data analysis, and validation</title><p id="Par16">Preparation of <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> kidney and liver RNA-seq libraries followed methods previously described in Ee Uli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Raw sequencing reads were submitted to NCBI Short Read Archive under accessions SRX2499144-SRX2499147. For data analyses, we used the same bioinformatic workflow and tools as depicted in our earlier publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Briefly, the assembly of raw sequence reads, normalisation, empirical analysis of differentially expressed genes (EDGE test), and gene ontology (GO) and KEGG pathway annotations were performed in CLC Genomics Workbench (CLCGW) version 7.5.1 (Qiagen Denmark), while functional classification of expressed genes in the kidney and liver transcriptomes was performed using Panther Database version 11.1 released on 2016-10-24 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pantherdb.org/">http://pantherdb.org/</ext-link>) and DAVID Bioinformatics Resources version 6.8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://david-d.ncifcrf.gov/home.jsp">https://david-d.ncifcrf.gov/home.jsp</ext-link>). To better present the tissue-specific genes, we combined gene expression data from this study and our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] to create a Venn diagram representation of tissue-specific genes using the web tool Venn Diagrams (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/Venn">http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/Venn</ext-link>). Validation of the RNA-seq dataset was performed with NanoString nCounter Elements XT (NanoString Technologies Inc., Seattle, WA, USA) gene expression assay. The methodology was the same as previously described in Ee Uli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> lists the genes utilised for the RNA-seq validation and their respective probe pair sequences.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Sequence reads trimming and RNA-seq mapping</title><p id="Par17">The number of raw kidney and liver sequence reads obtained were 44,452,083 and 30,898,157 respectively, each read possessing a sequence length of 70&#x000a0;bp. After trimming, the number of kidney and liver sequence reads were 41,854,334 and 28,943,585 singly. Summing up to a total of 70,788,919 good quality reads retained for assembly, with the average lengths of the reads ranging from 58.8 to 60.1&#x000a0;bp. Post-trimming, 93.94% of the reads were retained and were considered suitable for RNA-seq mapping. The overall mapping percentage of the sequence reads for each RNA-seq library ranged from 65.00 to 68.59%. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref> summarises the statistics of the sequence reads trimming and mapping.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Normalisation and differential gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par18">A total of 5473 significant differentially expressed genes were called. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref> lists the differentially expressed genes identified from the EDGE test with their respective annotated gene names and descriptions. Within the Kidney vs. Liver tissue comparison, the top three most upregulated genes in liver were <italic>PLA2G2A</italic>, <italic>SAA1</italic>, and <italic>ORM1</italic>, while the three most downregulated genes include <italic>UMOD</italic>, <italic>TINAG</italic>, and <italic>DHDH</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Tissue-specific genes</title><p id="Par19">Using gene expression data obtained from our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and this study, a Venn diagram representation of tissue-specific genes in kidney, liver, lymph node, spleen, and thymus tissues was generated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Lymph node showed the highest number of tissue-specific genes (2156 genes) among the five tissues compared; while kidney and liver had 310 and 154 tissue-specific genes respectively. The three most highly expressed tissue-specific genes in the kidney include <italic>MIOX</italic>, <italic>AQP2</italic>, and <italic>CDH16</italic>, while the top three tissue-specific genes expressed in the liver include <italic>APCS</italic>, <italic>APOA2</italic>, and LOC102121341. A complete list of tissue-specific genes can be found in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Venn diagram of the number of expressed genes (normalised expression value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1) in their respective tissues</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Functional annotation and classification</title><p id="Par20">In the kidney, 14,001, 7046, and 5635 expressed genes were categorised to biological process, molecular function, and cellular component domains respectively, while 12,004, 6059, and 4935 expressed genes in the liver were categorised to BP, MF, and CC domains respectively. The distribution of the expressed genes into different level 2 GO categories are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The BP category with the highest number of expressed genes for both tissues is cellular process (kidney, 4039; liver, 3496). For the MF domain, the catalytic activity category contains the highest number of expressed genes for both tissues (kidney, 2709; liver, 2419). As for CC, both tissues show the highest number of expressed genes in the cell part category (kidney, 2185; liver, 1954).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Categorisation of expressed genes to gene ontology categories in kidney and liver tissues</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Gene ontology</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Number of genes</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Kidney</th><th align="left">Liver</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Biological process</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cellular process</td><td char="." align="char">4039</td><td char="." align="char">3496</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Metabolic process</td><td char="." align="char">3493</td><td char="." align="char">3114</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Localization</td><td char="." align="char">1060</td><td char="." align="char">926</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Response to stimulus</td><td char="." align="char">1031</td><td char="." align="char">878</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Developmental process</td><td char="." align="char">939</td><td char="." align="char">745</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cellular component organization or biogenesis</td><td char="." align="char">842</td><td char="." align="char">753</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Biological regulation</td><td char="." align="char">923</td><td char="." align="char">740</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Multicellular organismal process</td><td char="." align="char">668</td><td char="." align="char">499</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Immune system process</td><td char="." align="char">499</td><td char="." align="char">443</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Biological adhesion</td><td char="." align="char">247</td><td char="." align="char">211</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Reproduction</td><td char="." align="char">165</td><td char="." align="char">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Locomotion</td><td char="." align="char">81</td><td char="." align="char">71</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Rhythmic process</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Growth</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cell killing</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Molecular function</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Catalytic activity</td><td char="." align="char">2709</td><td char="." align="char">2419</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Binding</td><td char="." align="char">2660</td><td char="." align="char">2310</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Transporter activity</td><td char="." align="char">572</td><td char="." align="char">435</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Receptor activity</td><td char="." align="char">446</td><td char="." align="char">348</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Structural molecule activity</td><td char="." align="char">450</td><td char="." align="char">384</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Signal transducer activity</td><td char="." align="char">147</td><td char="." align="char">110</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Translation regulator activity</td><td char="." align="char">32</td><td char="." align="char">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Antioxidant activity</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td char="." align="char">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Channel regulator activity</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Cellular component</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cell part</td><td char="." align="char">2185</td><td char="." align="char">1954</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Organelle</td><td char="." align="char">1359</td><td char="." align="char">1220</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Membrane</td><td char="." align="char">851</td><td char="." align="char">676</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Macromolecular complex</td><td char="." align="char">744</td><td char="." align="char">681</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Extracellular region</td><td char="." align="char">318</td><td char="." align="char">264</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Extracellular matrix</td><td char="." align="char">96</td><td char="." align="char">75</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cell junction</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="." align="char">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Synapse</td><td char="." align="char">32</td><td char="." align="char">26</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par21">In the kidney and liver, a total of 4406 and 3960 genes were assigned to KEGG pathway categories respectively. The metabolic pathways category contains the highest number of expressed genes for both kidney and liver tissues&#x02014;903 and 839 genes respectively. The distribution of the expressed genes into different KEGG pathway categories are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Categorisation of expressed genes to KEGG pathway categories in kidney and liver tissues</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">KEGG pathway</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Number of genes</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Kidney</th><th align="left">Liver</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Metabolism</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Global overview and maps</td><td char="." align="char">903</td><td char="." align="char">1046</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf01100: metabolic pathways</td><td char="." align="char">903</td><td char="." align="char">839</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf01230: biosynthesis of amino acids</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">58</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf00520: amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;mcf00562: inositol phosphate metabolism</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Energy metabolism</td><td char="." align="char">139</td><td char="." align="char">135</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf00190: oxidative phosphorylation</td><td char="." align="char">139</td><td char="." align="char">135</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Glycan biosynthesis and metabolism</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf00510: <italic>N</italic>-glycan biosynthesis</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Genetic information processing</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Folding, sorting and degradation</td><td char="." align="char">124</td><td char="." align="char">119</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04141: protein processing in endoplasmic reticulum</td><td char="." align="char">124</td><td char="." align="char">119</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Environmental information processing</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Membrane transport</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf02010: ABC transporters</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Signal transduction</td><td char="." align="char">600</td><td char="." align="char">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04010: MAPK signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">180</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04012: ErbB signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">69</td><td char="." align="char">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04015: Rap1 signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">154</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04022: cGMP-PKG signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">119</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04064: NF-kappa B signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04668: TNF signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">78</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Signalling molecules and interaction</td><td char="." align="char">177</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04512: ECM-receptor interaction</td><td char="." align="char">71</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04514: cell adhesion molecules (CAMs)</td><td char="." align="char">106</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Organismal system</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Development</td><td char="." align="char">101</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04360: axon guidance</td><td char="." align="char">101</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Immune system</td><td char="." align="char">154</td><td char="." align="char">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04610: complement and coagulation cascades</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">56</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04611: platelet activation</td><td char="." align="char">101</td><td char="." align="char">89</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04662: B cell receptor signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">53</td><td char="." align="char">54</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Nervous system</td><td char="." align="char">172</td><td char="." align="char">88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04722: neurotrophin signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">93</td><td char="." align="char">88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04725: cholinergic synapse</td><td char="." align="char">79</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Endocrine system</td><td char="." align="char">302</td><td char="." align="char">221</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04910: insulin signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">106</td><td char="." align="char">98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04915: estrogen signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">80</td><td char="." align="char">73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04917: prolactin signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04921: oxytocin signalling pathway</td><td char="." align="char">116</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Cellular processes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Transport and catabolism</td><td char="." align="char">250</td><td char="." align="char">325</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04142: lysosome</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04144: endocytosis</td><td char="." align="char">182</td><td char="." align="char">174</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04146: peroxisome</td><td char="." align="char">68</td><td char="." align="char">65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cellular community&#x02014;eukaryotes</td><td char="." align="char">168</td><td char="." align="char">152</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;mcf04510: focal adhesion</td><td char="." align="char">168</td><td char="." align="char">152</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Validation of RNA-seq differential gene expression</title><p id="Par22">Thirteen genes were selected to validate the RNA-seq differential gene expression dataset via NanoString gene expression assay. Normalised fold change values between the RNA-seq and NanoString platforms show concordance in magnitude directionality (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Our previous study also employed the NanoString gene expression assay to validate the RNA-seq dataset, and has shown similar concordance between the two platforms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par23">In our previous endeavour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], the lymph node, spleen, and thymus transcriptomes of the Malaysian cynomolgus macaque were sequenced via Illumina Hi-seq 2500 technology. The dataset presented in this study provides additional transcriptomic sequences from the kidney and liver of the Malaysian cynomolgus macaque, with a sum of 75,350,240 sequence reads obtained from four tissue libraries. In Ee Uli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], the transcriptome sequences were derived from immune-related tissues, whereas the kidney and liver transcriptomes generated in this study were obtained from metabolism-related tissues, and to a certain extent, these tissues also pertain to immune functions as well. Cynomolgus macaques are utilised as NHP models for liver-expressed drug metabolising enzyme studies, for example, the pharmacokinetics of the cytochrome P450 family of enzymes have been extensively studied in cynomolgus macaques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">It was observed that the percentages of the processed sequence reads that mapped back to the reference genome for all four libraries were below 70%. To rule out sequence contamination, we performed a BLAST alignment of the unmapped reads to NCBI&#x02019;s nucleotide (nt) database and classified the hits into their specific taxonomic classification. The majority of the unmapped reads were assigned to Cercopithecidae and other primate family taxa, while the remaining reads were unassigned or did not have any BLASTN hits (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). This suggests the absence of contaminating sequences, and also suggests the presence of novel transcripts in the kidney and liver dataset of the Malaysian cynomolgus macaque, which are yet to be described and curated in the <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> reference genome.</p><p id="Par25">Comparisons were made between the kidney and liver tissues due to the similarities in metabolic function between the two tissues. However, the specific metabolic functions of both kidney and liver tissues are ultimately different. For instance, the KEGG pathway enrichment analysis highlights 58 liver genes that were specifically enriched in the biosynthesis of amino acids pathway, while 55 kidney genes were involved in the Inositol phosphate metabolism pathway.</p><p id="Par26">Based on the differential gene expression analysis of kidney and liver tissues, the top three most upregulated genes in liver were <italic>PLA2G2A</italic>, <italic>SAA1</italic>, and <italic>ORM1</italic>, while the three most downregulated genes in kidney include <italic>UMOD</italic>, <italic>TINAG</italic>, and <italic>DHDH</italic>. The <italic>PLA2G2A</italic> gene codes for phospholipase A2 group IIA, and is suggested to be involved in the metabolism of phospholipids, inflammatory responses, and antimicrobial defence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. <italic>SAA1</italic> codes for the acute-phase serum amyloid A1 protein, and is involved in inflammation response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. <italic>ORM1</italic> codes for orosomucoid 1, which is suggested to induce the conversion of monocytes to M2b macrophages in response to type 2 cytokines in cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic>UMOD</italic> codes for uromodulin, a urinary protein which inhibits the crystallisation of renal fluids that causes renal stone formation, and also expedites transepithelial migration of neutrophils in inflammation responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Tubulointerstitial nephritis antigen is a glycoprotein coded by <italic>TINAG</italic>, which is a nephritogenic antigen implicated in tubular homeostasis and cell survival in the kidney [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. <italic>DHDH</italic> codes for the enzyme dihydrodiol dehydrogenase, and is suggested to be involved in detoxification processes in the kidney and liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">In the GO analysis, both kidney and liver transcriptomes were observed to have the majority of genes represented by the same categories in their respective GO domains. In the BP domain, the highly represented category was cellular process, while the category with the highest gene representation in the MF domain was catalytic activity. As for CC domain, the highest number of expressed genes was represented in the cell part category. The representation of functional GO categories in the <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> transcriptome were observed to be similar to that of other chordates, including that of the silver carp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], pig [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], black grouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and pufferfish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and suggest a fair representation of the <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> transcriptome with that of other chordates.</p><p id="Par28">The Malaysian cynomolgus macaque, <italic>M. f. fascicularis</italic>, is a unique subspecies that is suggested to have high nucleotide diversity and is genetically unique compared to other South East Asian <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Genetic heterogeneity is suggested to contribute to varied responses in cynomolgus macaques towards drugs and pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], making research into the Malaysian population of cynomolgus macaque invaluable to the biomedicine field. The transcriptome dataset of the Peninsular Malaysian cynomolgus macaque obtained from this study can be compared with cynomolgus macaques originating from other geographical locations including Mauritius, the Philippines, Indochina, Indonesia, and China. Such comparisons can be utilised for the detection of single nucleotide polymorphisms in the macaque transcriptome, to infer phylogeny utilising a larger set of genic sequences, and also to determine the nucleotide diversity of the Peninsular Malaysian cynomolgus macaque. Furthermore, the transcriptomic data obtained from this study may be utilised to design genic molecular markers for rapid assessment of wild populations of cynomolgus macaques in Peninsular Malaysia in a relatively shorter period of time and at a lower cost.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par29">Via the Illumina Hi-seq 2500 platform, 75,350,240 sequence reads in total were obtained from kidney and liver transcriptomes of the wild Peninsular Malaysian cynomolgus macaque. Additional sequence reads from the Malaysian cynomolgus macaque individuals will potentially further supplement the present genomic and transcriptomic data of this significant NHP primate model.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Limitations</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par30">Only two biological replicates were available for library construction and data analyses.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par31">RNA sequencing of additional tissues will provide more robust transcriptomic dataset of wild Peninsular Malaysia <italic>M. fascicularis</italic>.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Selected genes for NanoString nCounter XT Gene Expression assay validation of RNA-Seq gene expression profiles. Table lists selected genes utilised for the validation of RNA-Seq gene expression profiles via NanoString nCounter XT Gene Expression assay and their respective probes nucleotide sequences.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2.</bold>
<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic> kidney and liver sequence reads trimming and reference guided assembly summary statistics. Summary of <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic> kidney and liver sequence reads quality trimming and reference guided assembly.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3.</bold> List of differentially expressed genes from kidney vs. liver comparison. Differentially expressed genes in kidney and liver tissues called from the empirical differential gene expression analysis in CLC Genomics Workbench. Listed are the genes with their corresponding fold change values, together with their gene ontology and pathway annotations.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4.</bold> Tissue-specific genes (sorted from highest to lowest Normalised mean expression value). A list of tissue-specific genes generated from a Venn diagram comparison of expressed genes (normalised expression value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1) in kidney, liver, lymph node, spleen, and thymus tissues.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 5.</bold> Validation of RNA-seq differential gene expression results. Log<sub>2</sub> transformed fold change values were obtained from RNA-seq and NanoString nCounter XT platforms. Black bar represents fold change values obtained from RNA-Seq platform, while white bar represents fold change value obtained from NanoString nCounter XT platform.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4014_MOESM6_ESM.jpg"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 6.</bold> BLAST alignment of unmapped <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic> reads to NCBI nucleotide database. Graphical representation of unmapped <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> sequence reads assigned to taxonomic ranks based on BLAST alignment with NCBI nucleotide (nt) database. Intensity of the colour green represents the number of unmapped reads mapped to a respective taxonomic rank&#x02014;the more intense the green, the higher the number of reads assigned to a particular taxon.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>NHP</term><def><p id="Par3">nonhuman primate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DWNP</term><def><p id="Par4">Department of Wildlife and National Parks</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNA-seq</term><def><p id="Par5">RNA sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CLCGW</term><def><p id="Par6">CLC Genomics Workbench</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPM</term><def><p id="Par7">transcripts per million</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDGE</term><def><p id="Par8">empirical analysis of differentially expressed genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par9">gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p id="Par10">biological process</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MF</term><def><p id="Par11">molecular function</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC</term><def><p id="Par12">cellular component</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JEU, CS-YY, SKY, NBA, and SGT conceptualised and designed the study. JJR-R provided cynomolgus macaque samples. JEU performed the lab work. JEU, CS-YY, SKY, and NMI analysed the dataset. Manuscript was prepared by JEU. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par32">The authors would like to thank the Department of Wildlife and National Parks, Malaysia, for their permission to conduct this study. Additional thanks goes out to Dr. Ng Wei Lun (School of Life Sciences, Sun Yat-sen University), Nancy Liew Woan Charn (Laboratory of Vaccines and Immunotherapeutics, Institute of Bioscience, Universiti Putra Malaysia), and Mok Shao Feng for their invaluable guidance and assistance throughout the preparation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par33">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par34">Raw sequencing reads were submitted to NCBI Short Read Archive database under accessions SRX2499144-SRX2499147.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par36">Permission to obtain kidney and liver tissue samples of macaque individuals for research purposes by the Genetics Lab at the Department of Biology was granted by the Department of Wildlife and National Parks [Reference Number: JPHL&#x00026;TN(IP): 80-4/2]. Sampling and euthanasia of conflict <italic>M. fascicularis</italic> were performed by the Department of Wildlife and National Parks according to the guidelines set by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC), University of California, Davis, United States of America as adopted by the PREDICT Project in Malaysia.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par37">This research was supported by Research University Grant Scheme (Project No. GPIPB/2013/9413602) provided by Universiti Putra Malaysia, Malaysia. The funder had no role in study design, conducting the study, decision to publish, and preparation of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par38">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balimane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cynomolgus monkey as a potential model to assess drug interactions involving hepatic organic anion transporting polypeptides: in vitro, in vivo, and in vitro-to-in vivo extrapolation</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.112.200691</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23335392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukuya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CYP2C19 polymorphisms account for inter-individual variability of drug metabolism in cynomolgus macaques</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2014.07.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25036290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25036290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzetta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Towers</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of TRIM5&#x003b1; and TRIMCyp sequences in cynomolgus macaques from different geographical origins</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-011-0585-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22322672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22322672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ee Uli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>CSY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovie-Ryan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Isa</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) of lymph node, spleen, and thymus transcriptome from wild Peninsular Malaysian cynomolgus macaque (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>)</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3566</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28828235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28828235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cynomolgus monkey CYPs: a comparison with human CYPs</article-title><source>Xenobiotica</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00498250903003135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Uno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashiyama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of p450 enzymes between cynomolgus monkeys and humans: p450 identities, protein contents, kinetic parameters, and potential for inhibitory profiles</article-title><source>Curr Drug Metab</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22963393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22963393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajasegaran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of gastric cancer invasion and metastasis by PLA2G2A, a novel &#x003b2;-catenin/TCF target gene</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>4277</fpage><lpage>4286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-6517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18519687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum amyloid A1: structure, function and gene polymorphism</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2016</year><volume>583</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2016.02.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26945629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orosomucoid 1 drives opportunistic infections through the polarization of monocytes to the M2b phenotype</article-title><source>Cytokine</source><year>2015</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cyto.2015.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25689617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajczer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertocchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uromodulin facilitates neutrophil migration across renal epithelial monolayers</article-title><source>Cell Physiol Biochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000320554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondeti</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haruna</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Raparia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwar</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of extracellular matrix renal tubulo-interstitial nephritis antigen (TINag) in cell survival utilizing integrin &#x003b1;v&#x003b2;3/focal adhesion kinase (FAK)/phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3&#x000a0;K)/protein kinase Bserine/threonine kinase (AKT) signaling pathway</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>34131</fpage><lpage>34146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.241778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Kabbani</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional features of dimeric dihydrodiol dehydrogenase</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1464</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-008-7508-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18264804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of silver carp (<italic>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</italic>) by paired-end RNA sequencing</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsr046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22279088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of muscle and ovary transcriptome of <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>: assembly, annotation and marker discovery</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsr021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21729922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekblom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Castoe</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongcam-Rudloff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome sequencing of black grouse (<italic>Tetrao tetrix</italic>) for immune gene discovery and microsatellite development</article-title><source>Open Biol</source><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsob.120054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23155487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23155487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of the gill and swimbladder of <italic>Takifugu rubripes</italic> by RNA-Seq</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085505</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25546424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25546424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdul-Latiff</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruslin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Faiq</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hairul</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovie-Ryan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul-Patah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Continental monophyly and molecular divergence of Peninsular Malaysia&#x02019;s <italic>Macaca fascicularis fascicularis</italic></article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/897682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettiarachchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Babarinde</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing of six Mauritian cynomolgus macaques (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>) reveals a genome-wide pattern of polymorphisms under extreme population bottleneck</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evv033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25805843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liedigk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolleck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ker</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijaard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Md-Zain</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul-Latiff</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitogenomic phylogeny of the common long-tailed macaque (<italic>Macaca fascicularis fascicularis</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1437-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25887664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menninger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieczorek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Riesen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunkler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Audet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The origin of cynomolgus monkey affects the outcome of kidney allografts under Neoral immunosuppression</article-title><source>Transplant Proc</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2887</fpage><lpage>2888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(02)03547-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12431645</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>