<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Omega</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Omega</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ao</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">acsodf</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Omega</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2470-1343</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10620895</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.3c06074</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Utilizing Heteroatom
Types and Numbers from Extensive
Ligand Libraries to Develop Novel hERG Blocker QSAR Models Using Machine
Learning-Based Classifiers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>Safa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Oktay</surname><given-names>Lalehan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Erol</surname><given-names>Ismail</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9056-9000</contrib-id><name><surname>&#x0015e;ahin</surname><given-names>Kader</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath5"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0426-0905</contrib-id><name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>Serdar</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Computational
Biology and Molecular Simulations Laboratory, Department of Biophysics,
School of Medicine, <institution>Bah&#x000e7;e&#x0015f;ehir
University</institution>, Istanbul 34353, <country>Turkey</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Computational
Drug Design Center (HITMER), <institution>Bah&#x000e7;e&#x0015f;ehir
University</institution>, Istanbul 34353, <country>Turkey</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Department
of Analytical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, <institution>Bah&#x000e7;e&#x0015f;ehir University</institution>, Istanbul 34734, <country>Turkey</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label>Molecular
Therapy Lab, Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, <institution>Bah&#x000e7;e&#x0015f;ehir University</institution>, Istanbul 34353, <country>Turkey</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>serdar.durdagi@bau.edu.tr</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>43</issue><fpage>40864</fpage><lpage>40877</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Permits the broadest form of re-use including for commercial purposes, provided that author attribution and integrity are maintained (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0011" id="ab-tgrw1"/></p><p>The human ether-&#x000e0;-go-go-related gene (hERG) channel
plays
a crucial role in membrane repolarization. Any disruptions in its
function can lead to severe cardiovascular disorders such as long
QT syndrome (LQTS), which increases the risk of serious cardiovascular
problems such as tachyarrhythmia and sudden cardiac death. Drug-induced
LQTS is a significant concern and has resulted in drug withdrawals
from the market in the past. The main objective of this study is to
pinpoint crucial heteroatoms present in ligands that initiate interactions
leading to the effective blocking of the hERG channel. To achieve
this aim, ligand-based quantitative structure&#x02013;activity relationships
(QSAR) models were constructed using extensive ligand libraries, considering
the heteroatom types and numbers, and their associated hERG channel
blockage pIC<sub>50</sub> values. Machine learning-assisted QSAR models
were developed to analyze the key structural components influencing
compound activity. Among the various methods, the KPLS method proved
to be the most efficient, allowing the construction of models based
on eight distinct fingerprints. The study delved into investigating
the influence of heteroatoms on the activity of hERG blockers, revealing
their significant role. Furthermore, by quantifying the effect of
heteroatom types and numbers on ligand activity at the hERG channel,
six compound pairs were selected for molecular docking. Subsequent
molecular dynamics simulations and per residue MM/GBSA calculations
were performed to comprehensively analyze the interactions of the
selected pair compounds.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Istanbul Kalkinma Ajansi</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100008968</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>TR10/21/YEP/0133</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Bah&#x000c3;&#x000a7;esehir &#x000c3;&#x0009c;niversitesi</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100015732</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BAP.2022-01.12 EFD-1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>ao3c06074</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>ao3c06074</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite advancements in
diagnosis and treatment, cardiovascular
diseases (CVD) continue to be the leading cause of death worldwide,
as highlighted by the World Health Organization (WHO). The mortality
rate related to CVD is a significant concern, as seen in countries
like Russia, where the annual rate is 614 deaths per 100,000 individuals,
placing it among the highest worldwide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> The human ether-&#x000e0;-go-go-related gene (hERG), which encodes
voltage-gated potassium ion channels, plays a critical role in the
repolarization of cardiac action potential in human cardiomyocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> These potassium channels (K<sub>V</sub>) are
integral membrane proteins that serve vital functions in various physiological
processes. They are involved in generating nerve impulses, regulating
neuronal excitability, cardiac pacemaking, and modulating muscular
contractility. The channels are composed of homotetramers, each with
six transmembrane segments (S1&#x02013;S6). The voltage sensing domain
(VSD) comprises segments S1 to S4, while the pore domain (PD) consists
of S5, S6, the P-loop, and the selectivity filter (SF) that facilitates
the permeation of K<sup>+</sup> ions (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>K<sub>v</sub>11.1 (hERG) channel. While S1&#x02013;S4
helices form
the voltage sensing domain, S5&#x02013;S6 helices form the pore domain
region of the channel.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Prolonged ventricular repolarization caused by
hERG channel blockade
can increase the risk of cardiac damage, as evident by an extended
QT interval on electrocardiography (ECG). Paradoxically, the use of
antiarrhythmic medications to prolong QT intervals poses one of the
highest risk of potentials. This risk has been also observed across
various drug classes, including antihistamines, antipsychotics, antibiotics,
and gastrointestinal stimulants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Notably,
medications such as cisapride (a serotonin receptor agonist), quinidine
(an antiarrhythmic), astemizole, and terfenadine (both antihistamines)
have either been withdrawn from the market or highly restricted due
to their potential cardiotoxicity associated with hERG channel blockage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> These regulatory actions emphasize the significance
of hERG-related risks and underscore the need to monitor and control
the use of medications that may interfere with cardiac repolarization.
Consequently, the hERG potassium ion channel has become a crucial
therapeutic target, leading to the prioritization of screening drugs
for their interaction with the hERG channel during the early stages
of drug design. International Conference on Harmonization (ICH) regulations
now require the evaluation of drug candidates for their ability to
block the hERG channel during preclinical testing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> This evaluation has become a pivotal aspect in the initial
phases of drug research to ensure the safety and efficacy of new drugs,
particularly concerning their potential to cause adverse effects on
cardiac repolarization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> By conducting
a rigorous screening of hERG channel function, researchers can identify
and eliminate drug candidates with unfavorable interactions, ultimately
reducing the risk of cardiotoxicity and enhancing patient safety.
In recent years, multiple mechanisms associated with QT prolongation
have been discovered, highlighting the complexity beyond hERG channel
blockade.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup> Despite the long-standing recommendation
by international regulatory agencies since 2005 to assess the inhibitory
effect of new drugs on the hERG channel in preclinical settings,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> research continues to uncover additional factors
influencing QT prolongation.</p><p>The comprehensive evaluation of
QT prolongation risk, utilizing
the multiple ion channel effect model that considers sodium and calcium
channel blocking alongside the hERG channel assay, proves to be more
robust than relying solely on the hERG assay for assessing drug safety.
However, a significant number of currently available drugs undergo
evaluation using only the hERG assay during the preclinical stage.
As a result, efforts have been made to assess the risk of drug-induced
QT prolongation at the preclinical and clinical level. Despite initiatives
like <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://crediblemeds.org">crediblemeds.org</uri>, which
aims to provide an updated list of QT-prolonging drugs, there are
still instances where drugs with unknown risks of QT prolongation
continue to be prescribed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup></p><p>Presently,
the assessment of hERG-associated cardiac toxicity involves
employing <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> techniques
to study the impact of potential hERG channel blockers and to understand
their effects on channel permeability. While <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments offer comprehensive drug evaluations, their high cost,
inefficiency, and conflict with the 3R principle (i.e., reduction,
and refinement in animal studies) highlight the need to minimize their
use. In recent years, <italic>in vitro</italic> assays have made progress
in terms of duration and cost-effectiveness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> However, these methods also have limitations in investigating the
underlying structural mechanisms responsible for observed outcomes.
To address this challenge, computational techniques have emerged as
a promising approach in drug design and development for evaluating
the hERG-blocking potential of small compounds before conducting experiments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> Computational methods provide insights into
the structural basis of the hERG channel blockade and can complement
experimental approaches, contributing to a more efficient and informed
drug discovery process. By utilizing computational modeling and simulations,
researchers can prioritize and optimize potential drug candidates,
reducing reliance on resource-intensive <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments and ultimately accelerating the development
of safer and more effective medications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup></p><p><italic>In silico</italic> strategies, such as machine learning
(ML)-based classifiers and structure-based modeling, offer valuable
and reliable complements to experimental approaches in addressing
the issue of hERG-associated cardiac toxicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> These computational methods leverage large data sets and advanced
algorithms to analyze the structural and functional properties of
hERG channels and their interactions with potential blockers. By training
machine learning models on experimental data, researchers can accurately
predict the hERG-blocking potential of novel compounds. Additionally,
structure-based modeling techniques enable detailed exploration of
the binding interactions between compounds and hERG channels, providing
insights into the mechanisms of channel blockade. Integrating <italic>in silico</italic> approaches with experimental studies not only
enhances the understanding of hERG-associated cardiac toxicity but
also facilitates the identification of safer and more effective drug
candidates in a more efficient and cost-effective manner.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> While ligand-based models can offer effective
predictive performance, their utility in screening diverse compound
classes could be constrained due to limitations in their applicability
domain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> This restriction arises from
their reliance on training sets with a limited number of closely related
analogs. In this scenario, the utilization of target-driven based
methods, which are known for enhanced interpretability, becomes a
valuable strategy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> These approaches can
be effectively integrated into consensus strategies alongside ligand-based
classifiers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> Notably, over recent years, target-driven
approaches such as molecular docking have gained prominence as an
effective technique for developing classification models within the
realm of predictive toxicology. This computational approach has found
extensive usage in elucidating interactions between small-molecule
ligands and the hERG channel. It is frequently employed in conjunction
with additional computational techniques such as molecular dynamics
(MD) simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> and experimental methods
like mutagenesis studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> These combined efforts
enable the pinpointing of specific residues responsible for drug binding
within the hERG central cavity. Notably, residues such as Thr623,
Ser624, Val625, Gly648, Tyr652, Phe656, and Phe557 have been identified
as important amino acids for ligand interactions at the central cavity
of the hERG channel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup></p><p>In the current study, ligand-based
QSAR models were constructed
using data on heteroatom types and numbers derived from extensive
ligand libraries, incorporating information about chemical constitution
and hERG channel blockage (i.e., pIC<sub>50</sub> values). The QSAR
models, developed using various methods, proved effective in identifying
essential structural components influencing the compound activity.
The investigation of heteroatoms highlighted their role in the hERG
activity of blockers. By quantifying the impact of heteroatom types
and number in a compound on the pIC<sub>50</sub> value, six compound
pairs were selected for docking followed by molecular dynamics (MD)
simulations and MM/GBSA calculations for a comprehensive analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p>The overall methodology of
this study is summarized in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>, which gives an
overview of the employed approaches and techniques during the study.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Overview
of the employed methodology in this study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Construction of Ligand Databases from ChEMBL</title><p>The ChEMBL database (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/chembl/">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/chembl/</uri>) was employed to gather structural
and biological activity data of known hERG blockers. As of November
2022, the database contained 14,364 available compounds with their
corresponding IC<sub>50</sub> values at the hERG channel. To standardize
the activity values, the IC<sub>50</sub> values were transformed into
pIC<sub>50</sub> by taking the negative logarithm (base 10) of each
IC<sub>50</sub> value. pIC<sub>50</sub> is a widely used pharmacological
indicator that quantifies the potency of a substance by measuring
the concentration of a ligand required to inhibit a specific biological
activity. To manage the extensive database, a subset of 508 compounds
was selected among 14,364 compounds. In order to construct a subset
database, a normal distribution curve was generated, encompassing
a range of pIC<sub>50</sub> values spanning from 2.07 to 9.85 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). This subset included compounds with
varying levels of activity, providing a balanced representation of
low, moderate, and high activity within the smaller database (508
compounds).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Building QSAR Models</title><p>Schrodinger&#x02019;s
AutoQSAR module was employed to develop QSAR models, initially using
DeepChem.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> ML methods were used to create
predictive models for the target data. To compare its efficiency with
that of DeepChem, a similar process was repeated using the traditional
QSAR method. Additionally, the CANVAS cheminformatics package was
utilized to build QSAR models. Physicochemical descriptors were calculated
from the molecular properties of the 508 structures to enhance model
generation. For model generation, multiple linear regression (MLR),
partial least-squares (PLS) regression, and kernel-based PLS regression
(KPLS) were employed. The statistical results of the constructed models,
such as <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup>, were assessed to determine the most effective method. KPLS
models were developed by using various types of fingerprints. The
models that exhibited high scores for each fingerprint were selected,
and scatter plots were used for visualization and atomic contribution
analysis to identify influential substructures affecting activity
of the compound.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Investigating the Heteroatom Types and Numbers</title><p>To identify heteroatom types and numbers that significantly influence
hERG blockage, the CANVAS chemoinformatics package was utilized on
each of the chemical structure of the ligand. To ensure statistical
reliability, the compound clusters that contain at least 5 compounds
were only considered for subsequent analyses. Median pIC<sub>50</sub> values were calculated for each data set, and a Python script in
the Spyder IDE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> was executed to perform
correlation analysis. The script examines how changes in specific
heteroatom types and numbers, in the presence of other heteroatoms,
correlate with changes in the pIC<sub>50</sub> value. The resulting
graphs illustrate the correlation between the pIC<sub>50</sub> value
and the number and types of heteroatoms. Comparisons and calculations
were conducted between clusters (sets) with the same number of other
heteroatoms while observing the variations in the specific heteroatom&#x02019;s
count within the structure. To determine significant effects, the
number of other heteroatoms was kept constant, and the impact of a
particular heteroatom count was examined. If a substantial effect
of at least around one log unit was detected between the median pIC<sub>50</sub> values of the compared sets, the compound with the highest
pIC<sub>50</sub> value was selected from the set with the higher median
pIC<sub>50</sub> value, while the compound with the lowest pIC<sub>50</sub> value was chosen from the set with the lowest median pIC<sub>50</sub> value.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Ligand Preparation</title><p>The LigPrep module
of the Maestro molecular modeling package was employed to prepare
the 508 ligands.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> During the ligand preparation
process, the protonation states of the compounds were calculated within
a pH range of 7.0 &#x000b1; 2.0 using the Epik module.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> Compounds with chiral centers generated up to four distinct stereoisomers,
and ionization states were considered for each molecule. To ensure
accurate representation of molecular characteristics, the OPLS3e<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> force field was applied.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Protein Preparation</title><p>The cryo-EM structure
of the hERG K<sup>+</sup> channel (PDB ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="PDB" xlink:href="5VA1">5VA1</ext-link>) was obtained from the RCSB Protein Data
Bank.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> In this structure, the ion channel
is in an open-like state (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="PDB" xlink:href="5VA1">5VA1</ext-link>), and the voltage sensors exhibit a depolarized shape.
Despite its relatively small size, the central cavity contains four
deep hydrophobic pockets, which may explain the heightened sensitivity
of the hERG channel to diverse ligand structures. To enable molecular
docking and MD simulations, the channel was prepared using the Protein
Preparation tool in the Maestro molecular modeling suite.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> Before the MD simulations, three potassium ions
and two water molecules were added to the SF of the channel. Additionally,
missing side chains and loops were filled. The Maestro&#x02019;s Prime
module,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> was employed to incorporate the missing
loops and side chains into the residues. PROPKA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref></sup> was used to add hydrogen atoms to the protein at physiological pH,
ensuring accurate ionization states of amino acid residues. Structural
optimization was then performed by using the OPLS3 force field with
a convergence criterion of 0.3 &#x000c5; RMSD for heavy atoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Receptor Grid Generation</title><p>The generation
of a receptor grid is a crucial step in grid-based docking studies.
It involves creating a 3D grid that represents the binding site of
the receptor, which is necessary to evaluate the binding energy of
ligands during docking simulations. The Receptor Grid Generation tool
was utilized to identify the binding pocket (active site) in the structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> The grid was generated by specifying key residues
(i.e., Thr623, Ser624, Tyr652, Ala653, and Phe656) located at the
centroid of selected residues (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>A). The coordinates for the center of the grid were
determined as (2.86, &#x02212;5.97, &#x02212;1.27) in the (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic>) coordinate system, respectively.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(A) Docking
pose of CHEMBL1782574 in the central cavity of the
hERG channel. (B) hERG channel (PDB ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="PDB" xlink:href="5VA1">5VA1</ext-link>) merged with the POPC membrane bilayer.
The figure represents water molecules as the surface.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Molecular Docking</title><p>The docking simulations
were conducted using the grid-base Glide docking algorithm,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> which systematically explores the lowest energy conformation of
the docked compound at the binding site of the receptor. The ligands
underwent hierarchical filtration to assess the complementarity of
the ligand&#x02013;receptor system. Ligands that passed this phase
underwent energy minimization and were assigned scores. Two docking
protocols, Glide/SP and Glide/XP, were employed in this study. Standard
parameters, including ligand sampling with nitrogen inversions and
ring conformations, bias sampling of torsion for amides, and postdocking
minimization of 5 poses for each ligand, were considered. On the other
hand, Glide/XP performed deeper sampling, beginning with SP sampling
before utilizing its own anchor-and-grow technique. It utilizes a
more complex scoring algorithm, demanding a higher ligand&#x02013;receptor
shape complementarity. The Glide/XP docking is employed with standard
settings using flexible ligand sampling, Epik state penalties incorporated
into the docking score, and postdocking minimization of 10 poses.
The docked poses were ranked based on docking scores, and only the
top-scoring poses were selected for further analysis using MD simulations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Molecular Dynamics (MD) Simulations</title><p>The molecules with the highest docking scores were subjected to MD
simulations using Desmond.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> The membrane-embedded
structure (PDB ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="PDB" xlink:href="5VA1">5VA1</ext-link>) was obtained from the OPM database.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> The system builder placed the hERG channel protein in an orthorhombic
solvation box using the TIP3P solvent model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> and a POPC membrane model at 310 K, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>B. The simulations were conducted in the
NPT ensemble at 310 K with a pressure of 1.01325 bar, maintained using
a Nose&#x02013;Hoover thermostat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup> and Martyina&#x02013;Tobias&#x02013;Klein
barostat.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> The system was balanced by
adding Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> ions and 0.15 M NaCl solution to achieve
a pH of 7.4 and neutralize the simulation medium. Prior to the simulations,
energy minimization and relaxation of the structure were employed
in Desmond. Each MD simulation was conducted for 200 ns production
run which generates 1000 trajectory frames. The relevant MD simulations
data were collected individually and saved in trajectory files.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Molecular Mechanics Generalized Born Surface
Area (MM/GBSA) Calculations</title><p>To calculate average binding
free energy of each compound at the hERG channel used in MD simulations
and to better understand the main differences between weak and strong
inhibitors, MM/GBSA analysis was performed using Maestro&#x02019;s
Prime module.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> A systematic approach was employed,
wherein MM/GBSA calculations were performed using one frame out of
every ten frames. The dielectric constant was defined using the VSGB
2.0 implicit solvation model,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup>. After
the calculations for each complex, the average MM/GBSA value and standard
deviations for each compound were computed. Furthermore, to gain insight
into the contribution of individual residues in the four chains of
the hERG channel to the inhibitory activity and frequency of ligand&#x02013;protein
contacts, per-residue MM/GBSA analysis was conducted to calculate
binding free energies on a residue level. This analysis provides more
detailed information about the role of specific residues in the interaction
between the ligands and the protein.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and Discussion</title><p>The main objective
of this study is to create ligand-based QSAR
models by utilizing heteroatom types and numbers from extensive ligand
libraries, which encompass information about the chemical structure
of ligands and their respective hERG channel blockage IC<sub>50</sub> values. Furthermore, the study seeks to explore atomic-level features
that enhance the affinity with the hERG channel and influence the
inhibitory activity of compounds. A data set consisting of 14,364
hERG blocker compounds was collected from the ChEMBL database. In
order to manage easily the constructed models, a smaller subset database
was considered among 14,364 hERG blockers. For this aim, an evenly
distributed biological activity of compounds was selected, which involved
508 compounds (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). To ensure the
reliability of the collected IC<sub>50</sub>/pIC<sub>50</sub> values,
they were also cross-checked from scientific literature. These 508
compounds were selected to generate a normal distribution curve, which
provides insights into the distribution of hERG-blocking potential
within the data set. The pIC<sub>50</sub> values for these compounds
ranged from 2.07 to 9.85. QSAR models were constructed to investigate
the relationship between the structure and activity of the hERG blocker
compounds, providing valuable insights into the crucial structural
elements that influence their activity. Various QSAR modeling techniques
were employed to assess their effectiveness on the given data set.
The results revealed that the models developed using traditional methods
exhibited elevated <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> values, indicating superior precision and predictability,
albeit with lower or moderate ranking score values (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>). Similarly, models developed using the DeepChem
method also performed well in terms of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> values but with lower ranking
score values (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>). When constructing
the QSAR models, having a reliable objective function, or &#x0201c;score&#x02033;,
becomes essential to distinguish between effective (i.e., stable)
and ineffective QSAR models. In AutoQSAR, the quality of the models
is evaluated based on their performance on specific training and test
sets. The accuracy of a model is represented by a value between 0
and 1, where 1 indicates perfect predictions and 0 signifies entirely
incorrect predictions. The model M is then scored accordingly:<disp-formula id="ueq1"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_m001" position="anchor"/></disp-formula></p><p>This formula is designed to provide
favorable scores to models
that demonstrate high accuracy on both the training and test sets.
Conversely, it penalizes models that exhibit low accuracy on either
or both sets, as well as models that show substantial discrepancies
in accuracy between the two sets.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup></p><p>Consistency in the effectiveness of the models was observed across
various descriptor sets and molecular fingerprints. Among the different
methods compared, the KPLS approach outperformed PLS and MLR (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link>). Consequently, QSAR models utilizing
machine learning-based classifiers were developed using the KPLS method
along with eight different fingerprints (atom pairs, atom triplets,
dendritic, linear, MACCS, mol_print, radial, and topological). To
assess the impact of each fingerprint type on the statistical scores
of the constructed QSAR models, we employed the CANVAS tool. The same
data set containing 508 hERG blocker compounds with their corresponding
pIC<sub>50</sub> values was used in CANVAS. The results showed that
the KPLS approach, when using atom_triplets, MACCS, radial, and dendritic
fingerprints, yielded low <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> values (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>). However, other
fingerprints like topological, mol_print, linear, and atom_pairs produced
both high <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> values. The models with superior statistical results for
each fingerprint type are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Performance Evaluation of Top KPLS-Based
Fingerprint Models Generated by CANVAS</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="&#x02212;"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">fingerprint
type</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x02212;">training set/test set ratio</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">atom_pairs</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">85%&#x02013;15%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.94</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.60</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">linear</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">85%&#x02013;15%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.90</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.54</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">topological</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">85%&#x02013;15%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.65</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.53</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">mol_print</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">75%&#x02013;25%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.56</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.50</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">dendritic</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">75%&#x02013;25%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.98</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.49</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">radial</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">75%&#x02013;25%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.49</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">MACCS</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">85%&#x02013;15%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.27</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">atom_triplets</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x02212;">80%&#x02013;20%</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.99</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.17</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Overall, these findings underscore the significance
of successful
QSAR modeling techniques, particularly the KPLS approach, in elucidating
the structure&#x02013;activity relationships of hERG blocker compounds.
These models offer valuable insights into designing potent and precise
molecules. The use of different fingerprints and modeling methods
allows for a comprehensive analysis, leading to a better understanding
of the data set&#x02019;s characteristics. The QSAR models displayed
a strong correlation between predicted and observed pIC<sub>50</sub> values (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>).
These models effectively predicted the activity of both the training
and test sets, demonstrating their efficacy in predicting the potency
of hERG blocker compounds.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Scatter plots of observed and predicted pIC<sub>50</sub> values
of the hERG blockers based on the KPLS model with (A) atom_pairs,
(B) linear, (C) topological, and (D) mol_print fingerprints.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>Additionally, an investigation into the influence
of heteroatoms
on the functionality of hERG inhibitors was undertaken, focusing on
the quantity and variety of heteroatoms present in the compounds.
Heteroatoms give rise to structures known as functional groups. These
functional groups serve as points where molecules interact and where
chemical reactivity occurs between distinct compounds. Thus, heteroatoms
have the potential to bring about noteworthy changes in both the properties
and reactivity of a molecule.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> The LigFilter
descriptors were computed using the CANVAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> excluding carbon and hydrogen atoms (i.e., considering only heteroatoms).
This allowed for the determination of the number of heteroatoms in
a data set comprising 508 compounds (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Tables S4&#x02013;S7</ext-link>), providing valuable insights into the heteroatom composition within
the compounds under study. The analysis revealed that oxygen, nitrogen,
chlorine, and sulfur atoms were particularly important heteroatoms
in the 508 selected compounds, modulating the inhibition activity
of the hERG blockers. Oxygen atoms exhibited an inverse relationship
with activity, as an increase in their number within the compounds
led to decreased inhibition (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>). <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref> depicts pIC<sub>50</sub> values of selected compounds at
the hERG channel versus the number of oxygen atoms within each compound.
Compounds are selected based on the compound that their pIC<sub>50</sub> values fit to the mean value in each set. Similarly, an increase
in the chlorine atom number resulted in a slight decrease in activity
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>). On the other hand, the presence
of sulfur atoms displayed a positive correlation with activity, indicating
that as the sulfur atom content increased within a compound, the pIC<sub>50</sub> value also tended to increase (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link>). However, the presence of nitrogen atoms did not show a
discernible impact on the biological activity, with no clear correlation
between the pIC<sub>50</sub> value and the number of nitrogen atoms
in the compound. Nevertheless, a closer examination revealed that
an increase in the number of nitrogen atoms from 1 to 3 within a compound
resulted in a decrease in pIC<sub>50</sub> values, but when the number
of nitrogen atoms exceeded 3, the trend in pIC<sub>50</sub> values
showed an increase. Furthermore, when there were more than 5 nitrogen
atoms in a compound, the pIC<sub>50</sub> trend was not stable (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figure S4</ext-link>). These findings provide valuable insights
into the structure&#x02013;activity relationships of hERG blockers,
particularly concerning the influence of heteroatom types and numbers.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Influence
of heteroatoms on the activity of the hERG blockers.
(A) Effect of the number of oxygen atoms on the hERG blockage activity
(pIC<sub>50</sub>). (B) Detailed analyses on the influence of the
oxygen atoms on the pIC<sub>50</sub> values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Illustrative example demonstrating an activity decrease
with elevated
oxygen levels within the structures.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><p>To further investigate the correlation between
heteroatoms and
the pIC<sub>50</sub> value, additional analyses were conducted by
grouping compounds with the same number of a specific heteroatom type.
This approach allowed for a more targeted analysis of how biological
activity (pIC<sub>50</sub>) evolves with changes in the quantity of
a particular heteroatom type while keeping the total count of heteroatoms
in the molecular structure constant. <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figures S2B, S3B, and S4B</ext-link> depict these grouped analyses, offering a clearer understanding
of the relationship between heteroatoms and activity. Further statistical
analysis was performed to examine the quantitative impact of heteroatoms
on pIC<sub>50</sub> activity, focusing on changes of approximately
1 log unit or more for the effect of a specific atom on the activity.
To ensure reliable sampling, a threshold of five members in a cluster
was set, and clusters containing fewer than five compounds were excluded
from the analysis. By evaluating the increase or decrease in the number
of a specific heteroatom while keeping the number of other heteroatoms
constant, significant effects on the activity were observed. To gain
a deeper understanding of these effects, compounds with the highest
and lowest pIC<sub>50</sub> values were selected from each cluster,
encompassing both strong and weak inhibitors, providing a comprehensive
view of the differences influencing the activity. As a result, six
pairs of molecules were identified, each pair consisting of a strong
and weak inhibitor (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref>). This approach enabled a comprehensive investigation of
the discrepancies among these molecules and facilitated subsequent
analyses.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Quantitative Analysis of the Influence
of Heteroatoms on the pIC<sub>50</sub> Values</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">Molecular formula of the compound representing
the <bold>weakest</bold> inhibition within the set and its CHEMBL
ID</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">pIC<sub>50</sub> value of the compound
representing
the <bold>weakest</bold> inhibition within the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Heteroatom type and number representing the <bold>weakest</bold> inhibition within the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Total number
of heteroatoms representing the <bold>weakest</bold> inhibition within
the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">Mean pIC<sub>50</sub> value for
the <bold>weak</bold> inhibition set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Molecular formula of the compound representing
the <bold>strongest</bold> inhibition within the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">pIC<sub>50</sub> value of the compound representing
the <bold>strongest</bold> inhibition within the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Heteroatom type and number representing the <bold>strongest</bold> inhibition within the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Total number
of heteroatoms representing the <bold>strong</bold> inhibition within
the set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">Mean pIC<sub>50</sub> value for
the strong inhibition
set</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">log unit difference between median
values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>19</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> (70)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.89</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>22</sub>H<sub>26</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1257821)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.85</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.92</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">1.03</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>23</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1097)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.175</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>31</sub>NO<sub>4</sub> (572163)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.42</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.93</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>23</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1097)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.175</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>24</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>S (1257578)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.59</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.17</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.99</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>23</sub>H<sub>35</sub>F<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>3</sub>S (1782574)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.41</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">11</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.81</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>26</sub>F<sub>3</sub>N<sub>5</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (3422978)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.41</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5 N</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">11</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.95</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>26</sub>FN<sub>5</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (2424928)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.51</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0
S</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">10</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.96</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>28</sub>H<sub>31</sub>F<sub>3</sub>N<sub>6</sub>S (390649)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1 S</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">10</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.9</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.94</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>23</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1097)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0 Cl</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.22</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>27</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>OS (195180)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.52</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1 Cl</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.72</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">1.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To gain deeper insights into the impact of the type
and number
of heteroatom in these selected representative compound pairs, molecular
docking analyses were carried out by using the Glide/SP and Glide/XP
algorithms. These chosen molecules were docked to the pore domain
region of the hERG channel. The outcomes of these simulations, comprising
the ligand&#x02013;protein interactions (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>) and docking scores obtained from Glide/SP
and Glide/XP, are presented in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref></xref>.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Investigating ligand&#x02013;protein interactions within
the intracavitary
pore domain of the channel: Examination of the docking pose of the
CHEMBL1782574 compound with 2D and 3D insights.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0007" id="gr7" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Docking Scores from Glide/SP and XP
of the Top Selected Ligands in the hERG Binding Site (Central Cavity)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center" char=".">Glide (kcal/mol)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">pair number</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">CHEMBL
ID</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">pIC<sub>50</sub></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">SP</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">XP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.00</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.33</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.14</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1257821</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.85</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.84</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL572163</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.42</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.34</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;4.12</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;3.95</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1257578</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.59</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.79</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.87</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;3.95</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1782574</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.41</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.34</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;4.42</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL3422978</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.41</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;7.08</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL2424928</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.51</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.69</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.21</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL390649</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;4.92</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;3.95</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.21</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL195180</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.52</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;6.84</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;5.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Following the selection of the top docking scores,
the compounds
were subjected to further analysis by using MD simulations. A total
of 6 pairs, representing both strong and weak inhibitors, were utilized
in 200 ns all-atom MD simulations. The resulting trajectories from
each simulation were collected and subjected to analysis. To assess
the structural stabilities of each ligand pair at the binding pocket,
the root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) of the ligands was measured
in comparison to their initial positions (i.e., Glide/XP). A higher
ligand RMSD value generally indicates a deviation from the initial
binding pose, while a lower RMSD value suggests that the molecule
maintains its initial conformation throughout the simulations. As
expected, the results from <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref> validate these assumptions, as the RMSD values consistently
remain lower for the strong inhibitors and higher for the weak inhibitors.
However, it is worth noting that only one pair of molecules CHEMBL70
(pIC<sub>50</sub>, 3) and CHEMBL1257821 (pIC<sub>50</sub>, 9.85) deviates
from this trend.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Ligand RMSD analyses. (A) Normal distribution of ligand
RMSDs.
(B) Change of RMSD values of heavy atoms of ligands based on their
initial positions at the binding pocket of the channel (LigFitProt).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0008" id="gr8" position="float"/></fig><p>These findings provide valuable insights into the
structural dynamics
and binding characteristics of the inhibitors, emphasizing the significance
of heteroatom types and numbers in achieving a strong or weak inhibitory
profile. The ligand&#x02013;protein interactions were analyzed through
the generation of a simulation interaction diagram. Throughout the
200 ns all-atom MD simulations, various contacts between the ligand
and the protein were observed and recorded. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figures S5 to S10</ext-link> present detailed interactions between the ligand
atoms and the protein, focusing on interactions that occurred for
more than 15% of the simulation time. These analyses shed light on
the complex interactions between the ligands and the protein, further
contributing to our understanding of the structure&#x02013;activity
relationships and binding mechanisms of the inhibitors.</p><p>The
MM/GBSA results were thoroughly examined alongside the experimental
pIC<sub>50</sub> data for each pair of molecules. <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">4</xref></xref> presents the average MM/GBSA
binding free energy values between the selected ligand pairs and the
hERG channel.</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Average MM/GBSA Values for the Selected
Compounds</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>Pair number</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">CHEMBL ID</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">Average MM/GBSA (kcal/mol)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">Std. Dev. (kcal/mol)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">pIC<sub>50</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;53.20</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.63</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.00</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1257821</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;53.09</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.80</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL572163</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;64.71</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.42</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;44.65</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.46</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1257578</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;70.80</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">8.00</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.59</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;44.65</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.46</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1782574</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;58.90</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.23</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.41</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL3422978</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;70.99</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5.84</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL2424928</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;62.32</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.16</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.51</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL390649</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;63.61</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">10.96</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" style="border:none;" align="left">pair 6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL1097</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;44.65</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.47</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4.00</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">CHEMBL195180</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x02013;70.07</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6.29</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7.52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>As anticipated, the average MM/GBSA outcomes revealed
a clear correlation
between the binding energy and activity. Molecules with higher pIC<sub>50</sub> values exhibited more negative binding energy values, indicating
stronger interactions and a better fit with the pore domain of the
ion channel. Conversely, molecules with lower pIC<sub>50</sub> values
showed less negative binding energy values, suggesting weaker binding
and less favorable interactions, categorizing them as weak inhibitors.
The overall agreement between the MM/GBSA results and experimental
data substantiated the predictive capability of the MM/GBSA method.
However, it is crucial to acknowledge that the MM/GBSA results for
the pair of molecules CHEMBL70 and CHEMBL1257821 did not align well
with the experimental data. This discrepancy signals the necessity
for further investigation to comprehend the underlying factors contributing
to the observed deviation in this specific pair of molecules. While
CHEMBL70, a kappa opioid receptor antagonist, was anticipated to have
a smaller RMSD and a more negative average MM/GBSA score compared
to CHEMBL1257821, the latter displayed a strong inhibitory effect
at the hERG channel with a pIC<sub>50</sub> value of 9.85. However,
the mismatched results observed for this pair may be attributed to
the state of the hERG channel. The hERG channel can exist in either
an open state or an open-inactivated state for hosting the blockers,
and different drugs may have varying affinities depending on the specific
state. It is plausible that CHEMBL1257821 and CHEMBL70 interact differently
with the hERG channel due to variations in the conformational state
of the channel. To explore this hypothesis, an open-inactivated state
model of the hERG channel that we have reported previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> was utilized for docking the two compounds (i.e.,
CHEMBL1257821 and CHEMBL70), employing the consistent Glide/SP and
Glide/XP docking protocols. Although the weak inhibitor CHEMBL70 demonstrates
docking scores of &#x02212;6.44 and &#x02212;6.77 kcal/mol when employed
with the Glide/SP and Glide/XP modules in the open-inactivated state,
the corresponding outcomes for the strong inhibitor CHEMBL1257821
are &#x02212;8.84 and &#x02212;8.27 kcal/mol, as determined by the Glide/SP
and Glide/XP approaches, respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Table S8</ext-link>). Further investigations and studies are warranted to explore the
specific binding mechanisms and interactions of these compounds with
the hERG channel in different states. Understanding these nuances
can provide crucial insights into the design and development of more
effective hERG inhibitors.</p><p>In this study, a comprehensive MM/GBSA
analysis was also conducted
to identify the crucial residues within the hERG channel that significantly
impact the inhibition activity. The goal of this analysis was to pinpoint
the residues that establish strong interactions with the ligands compared
to others. The results of the MM/GBSA per-residue study, depicted
in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">Figures S11&#x02013;S19</ext-link>. The findings of the per-residue
analysis shed light on the essential residues responsible for governing
the inhibitory function of the hERG channel. Notably, the hERG channel
contains two sets of aryl residues, Tyr652 and Phe656, at the central
cavity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref></sup> These residues collectively exert control
over the dynamic processes of potassium channel gating and subsequent
potassium ion conduction. As expected, residues (Tyr652 and Phe656)
were also identified as key contributors in the per-residue interaction
analysis, forming strong contacts with the ligands (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>). The intricate modulation
of these essential functions underscores their critical role in the
overall channel activity. Notably, these specific residues offer potential
interaction sites for various chemical compounds, carrying the capacity
to influence hERG blockage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref></sup> Comparing
with existing literature, our results align well with previous studies
highlighting the importance of Tyr652 and Phe656 in hERG channel function.
These residues consistently emerge as vital players. The robust residue&#x02013;ligand
interactions reinforce their relevance. This coherence validates our
findings and underscores their crucial role in the hERG modulation.
Interestingly, each ligand at the pore domain also exhibited additional
interactions with specific residues that played a role in binding
to the hERG channel. For example, compound CHEMBL1257578 showed that
Val625 from Chain-A, Leu650 from Chain-B, Thr623, Val625, Met645,
and Val659 from Chain-C, and Met645 from Chain-D were significant
contributors to the binding energy, in addition to Tyr652 and Phe656
(<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>). The findings
align consistently with established literature, for the residues Thr623
and Val625, situated in proximity to the pore helix, which were found
to be implicated in hERG binding for many tested drugs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref></sup> These polar amino acids might have the capability
to engage with the polar tails found in numerous potent hERG blockers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref></sup> followed by Met645, which was determined in another study as one
of the vital binding elements contributing to the stabilization of
vesnarinone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref></sup> An investigation that used
a combination of alanine-scanning and site-directed mutagenesis, alongside
protein modeling, potential energy mapping, and docking studies, discovered
that among the residues implicated in drug binding, Thr623, Val625,
and Val659 play a significant role.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Per-residue
MM/GBSA analyses for the CHEMBL1257578 compound.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_0009" id="gr9" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, this study
provides valuable insights into the structure&#x02013;activity
relationships of hERG blockers and the substructures that influence
their inhibition activity. The development of ligand-based QSAR models
based on heteroatom numbers from extensive ligand libraries proved
to be effective, with CANVAS-created QSAR models showing high <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> values.
Among the various QSAR modeling techniques employed, the KPLS method
demonstrated superior performance, enabling the development of QSAR
models using multiple fingerprints. The investigation of heteroatoms
revealed significant correlations among the number of oxygen, nitrogen,
chlorine, and sulfur atoms in the chemical structure of the inhibitors
and their pIC<sub>50</sub> values. The increase in the quantity of
oxygen and chlorine atom numbers demonstrated an inverse correlation
with inhibitory activity, whereas the increased number of sulfur atoms
displayed a parallel relationship. However, the impact of nitrogen
atoms on the hERG channel blocking activity proved to be more complex.
It was observed that when the number of nitrogen atoms increased from
1 to 3 within a compound, the pIC<sub>50</sub> values showed a decreasing
trend. However, when the number of nitrogen atoms exceeded 3, a reverse
trend emerged, with pIC<sub>50</sub> values increasing. Furthermore,
having more than 5 nitrogen atoms in a compound did not show a stable
pIC<sub>50</sub> trend. These findings underscore the importance of
heteroatoms in influencing the activity of hERG blockers. The study
highlights the significant role that specific heteroatom types and
their respective quantities play in modulating the inhibitory effects
on the hERG channel. Understanding these relationships can contribute
to the design and optimization of potent and selective hERG inhibitors.</p><p>The utilization of MD simulations and MM/GBSA calculations enabled
comprehensive analysis of compound pairs, facilitating a comparison
between strong and weak inhibitors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref></sup> The results aligned
perfectly with expectations as strong inhibitors displayed lower ligand
RMSD values and more negative average MM/GBSA binding energy values,
indicating stronger binding to the hERG channel. On the other hand,
weak inhibitors exhibited higher ligand RMSD values and less negative
average MM/GBSA values, indicating a weaker binding affinity. Moreover,
the MM/GBSA per-residue analysis identified critical residues in the
four chains of the hERG channel that play a significant role in the
blockage activity. Notably, Tyr652 and Phe656 emerged as key residues,
demonstrating consistent and diverse interactions with all of the
studied inhibitor ligands. Specifically, Tyr652 engaged in the highest
number of interactions, accounting for over 50% of the simulation
time, primarily driven by hydrophobic forces. Additionally, other
crucial residues such as Thr623, Ser624, and Ser660 were found to
actively participate in ligand interactions throughout the simulation
period. These findings highlight the pivotal role of Tyr652 and Phe656
and other residues in establishing and modulating inhibitor&#x02013;ligand
interactions, providing valuable insights into the design and optimization
of targeted therapeutics.</p><p>In summary, this study enhances our
comprehension of hERG channel
blockage and offers valuable insights that can aid in the design of
more effective hERG blockers. The presented findings play a crucial
role in advancing drug discovery and provide significant considerations
for the development of targeted therapeutics.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information
is
available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Statistical results of the top AutoQSAR traditional
and DeepChem method models; results of the MLR and PLS method models
from CANVAS; influence of chlorine, oxygen, nitrogen, and sulfur atoms
on the pIC<sub>50</sub> activity values; docking results for mismatched
compound pairs between the open and open-inactivated states of the
hERG channel; normal distribution analysis of hERG blockers in a subset
of 508 compounds; influence of heteroatoms on the activity of the
hERG blockers; protein&#x02013;ligand interaction for pairs; per-residue
interaction analyses (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.3c06074/suppl_file/ao3c06074_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao3c06074_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>ao3c06074_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="NOTES-d14e1343-autogenerated"><p>The
authors declare no
competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was funded by the Scientific Research
Projects Commission of Bah&#x000e7;e&#x0015f;ehir University (BAU),
project number BAP.2022-01.12 EFD-1. This study was also funded by
the T.C. Istanbul Development Agency, project no. TR10/21/YEP/0133.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Subbotina</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lees-Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noskov</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Insights into the Molecular Mechanism of HERG1 Channel
Activation and Blockade by Drugs</article-title>. <source>Curr. Med.
Chem.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>30</issue>), <fpage>3514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3532</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986710792927886</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20738248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baukrowitz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yellen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Inward Rectification Mechanism
of the HERG Cardiac Potassium Channel</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1996</year>, <volume>379</volume> (<issue>6568</issue>), <fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>836</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/379833a0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8587608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Creanza</surname><given-names>T.
M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Delre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ancona</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lentini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saviano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangiatordi</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structure-Based
Prediction of HERG-Related Cardiotoxicity:
A Benchmark Study</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>61</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>4758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4770</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.1c00744</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34506150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L.-P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Predicting
HERG Channel Blockers with Directed Message Passing Neural
Networks</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>3423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3430</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D1RA07956E</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35425351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Darpo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nebout</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sager</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Clinical
Evaluation of QT/QTc Prolongation
and Proarrhythmic Potential for Nonantiarrhythmic Drugs: The International
Conference on Harmonization of Technical Requirements for Registration
of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use E14 Guideline</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Pharmacol.</source>
<year>2006</year>, <volume>46</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0091270006286436</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16638733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>BayeshERG: A Robust,
Reliable and Interpretable Deep Learning Model for Predicting HERG
Channel Blockers</article-title>. <source>Brief. Bioinf.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>23</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>bbac211</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbac211</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Recanatini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poluzzi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Masetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>De Ponti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>QT Prolongation
through HERG K(+) Channel Blockade: Current Knowledge and Strategies
for the Early Prediction during Drug Development</article-title>. <source>Med. Res. Rev.</source>
<year>2005</year>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/med.20019</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15389727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Erol</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Salmas</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noskov</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>First Universal Pharmacophore Model for HERG1 K+ Channel
Activators: ActhER</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Graphics Model.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmgm.2017.03.020</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Woosley</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CredibleMeds.Org: What
Does It Offer?</article-title>. <source>Trends Cardiovasc. Med.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>28</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcm.2017.07.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28801207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Role of HERG Potassium Channel Assays
in Drug Development</article-title>. <source>Channels</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/chan.2.2.6004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18849661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ebneth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bothmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trube</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Apfel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Evaluation of a High-Throughput Fluorescence
Assay Method for HERG Potassium Channel Inhibition</article-title>. <source>J. Biomol. Screening</source>
<year>2005</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1087057104272045</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noskov</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Modeling of Open,
Closed, and Open-Inactivated States of the HERG1 Channel: Structural
Mechanisms of the State-Dependent Drug Binding</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Modell.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>2760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2774</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci300353u</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Bannigan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aldeghi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>H&#x000e4;se</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Machine Learning Directed Drug Formulation
Development</article-title>. <source>Adv. Drug Delivery Rev.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>175</volume>, <elocation-id>113806</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2021.05.016</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit14"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Wolf P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>A.-M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vendruscolo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sormanni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment
of Therapeutic Antibody Developability by Combinations of In Vitro
and In Silico Methods</article-title>. In <source>Therapeutic Antibodies:
Methods and Protocols</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Houen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed.; Methods in Molecular Biology; <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>, <year>2022</year>;
pp <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-1450-1_4</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Carracedo-Reboredo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li&#x000f1;ares-Blanco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cedr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Novoa</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carballal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maojo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pazos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fernandez-Lozano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Review on
Machine Learning Approaches and Trends in Drug Discovery</article-title>. <source>Comput. Struct. Biotechnol. J.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>4538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4558</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2021.08.011</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34471498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>AlRawashdeh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structural Analysis of HERG Channel
Blockers and the Implications for Drug Design</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Graphics Model.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>120</volume>, <elocation-id>108405</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmgm.2023.108405</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J. Z. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>HergSPred: Accurate
Classification of HERG Blockers/Nonblockers with Machine-Learning
Models</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>62</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>1830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1839</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.2c00256</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35404051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Gadaleta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangiatordi</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Catto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carotti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicolotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Applicability
Domain for QSAR Models: Where Theory Meets Reality</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Quant. Struct.-Prop. Relat.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>1</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/IJQSPR.2016010102</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Cavalluzzi</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Imbrici</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gualdani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stefanachi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangiatordi</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lentini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicolotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Human Ether-&#x000e0;-Go-Go-Related
Potassium Channel: Exploring SAR to Improve Drug Design</article-title>. <source>Drug Discovery Today</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2019.11.005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31756511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rybacka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roncaglioni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tropsha</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Varnek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zakharov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grulke</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trisciuzzi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fourches</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Benfenati</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muratov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wedebye</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grisoni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangiatordi</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Incisivo</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tetko</surname><given-names>I. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Balabin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kancherla</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cassotti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nikolov</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicolotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Beger</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Todeschini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CERAPP: Collaborative
Estrogen Receptor Activity Prediction Project</article-title>. <source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>124</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1033</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1510267</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alberga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Balabin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ballabio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Benfenati</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bhhatarai</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fourches</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Sosa</surname><given-names>A.
T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gramatica</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grisoni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grulke</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jeliazkova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Manganelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangiatordi</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maran</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marcou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muratov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D.-T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicolotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nikolov</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Norinder</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Piir</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pogodin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poroikov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roncaglioni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rupakheti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sakkiah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sangion</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>K.-W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sild</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taboureau</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tetko</surname><given-names>I. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Todeschini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trisciuzzi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tropsha</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Den
Driessche</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Varnek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wedebye</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zakharov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CoMPARA: Collaborative Modeling Project for Androgen
Receptor Activity</article-title>. <source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>128</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>27002</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP5580</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32074470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular Docking and Molecular Dynamics
Studies on the Structure&#x02013;Activity Relationship of Fluoroquinolone
for the HERG Channel</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biosyst.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2869</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4MB00396A</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25100024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fukunishi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsujimae</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Inanobe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kurachi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mutational Analysis
of Block and Facilitation of HERG Current by a Class III Anti-Arrhythmic
AgentNifekalant</article-title>. <source>Channels</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>1</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/chan.4691</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18690032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Melgari</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>El Harchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hancox</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular
Basis of HERG Potassium Channel Blockade by the Class Ic Antiarrhythmic
Flecainide</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2015.06.021</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26159617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Vandenberg</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perozo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Towards
a Structural View of Drug
Binding to HERG K+ Channels</article-title>. <source>Trends Pharmacol.
Sci.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>38</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>899</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>907</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2017.06.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Von Bargen</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Repasky</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>AutoQSAR: An Automated Machine Learning
Tool for Best-Practice Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship
Modeling</article-title>. <source>Future Med. Chem.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>15</issue>), <fpage>1825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1839</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4155/fmc-2016-0093</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27643715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit27"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Raybaut</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Spyder-Documentation</source>. Available online at: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pythonhosted.org">pythonhosted.org</uri>. <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit28"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>LigPrep</surname><given-names>Schr&#x000f6;dinger</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calkins</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Towards the Comprehensive,
Rapid, and Accurate Prediction of the Favorable Tautomeric States
of Drug-like Molecules in Aqueous Solution</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Aided Mol. Des.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-010-9349-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cholleti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Timlin</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Uchimaya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Epik: A Software Program
for PKaprediction
and Protonation State Generation for Drug-like Molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Aided Mol. Des.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>691</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-007-9133-z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17899391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Damm</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Reboul</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>OPLS3e: Extending
Force Field Coverage for Drug-Like Small Molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1874</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jctc.8b01026</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30768902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cryo-EM Structure
of the Open Human Ether-&#x000e0;-Go-Go-Related
K+ Channel HERG</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>169</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430.e10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.03.048</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28431243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Madhavi
Sastry</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Adzhigirey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Annabhimoju</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Protein and Ligand Preparation: Parameters, Protocols,
and Influence on Virtual Screening Enrichments</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Aided Mol. Des.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>27</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-013-9644-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>On the Role of the
Crystal Environment in Determining Protein Side-Chain Conformations</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<year>2002</year>, <volume>320</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>608</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(02)00470-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12096912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T. J. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Hierarchical
Approach to All-Atom
Protein Loop Prediction</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>55</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>367</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.10613</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15048827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>S&#x000f8;ndergaard</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>PROPKA3: Consistent Treatment of
Internal and Surface
Residues in Empirical PKa Predictions</article-title>. <source>J. Chem.
Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>537</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct100578z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>S&#x000f8;ndergaard</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Improved Treatment
of Ligands and Coupling Effects in Empirical Calculation and Rationalization
of PKa Values</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>2284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2295</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct200133y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26606496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Halgren</surname><given-names>T.
A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Glide: A New Approach for Rapid,
Accurate Docking and Scoring. 2. Enrichment Factors in Database Screening</article-title>. <source>J. Med. Chem.</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1750</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1759</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm030644s</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15027866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Halgren</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klicic</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mainz</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Repasky</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shenkin</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Glide:
A New Approach for Rapid, Accurate Docking and Scoring. 1. Method
and Assessment of Docking Accuracy</article-title>. <source>J. Med.
Chem.</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm0306430</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15027865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Repasky</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Halgren</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sanchagrin</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mainz</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Extra Precision
Glide: Docking and Scoring Incorporating a Model of Hydrophobic Enclosure
for Protein&#x02013;Ligand Complexes</article-title>. <source>J. Med.
Chem.</source>
<year>2006</year>, <volume>49</volume> (<issue>21</issue>), <fpage>6177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm051256o</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17034125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Farid</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pearlstein</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>New Insights about HERG Blockade
Obtained from Protein Modeling, Potential Energy Mapping, and Docking
Studies</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source>
<year>2006</year>, <volume>14</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>3160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2005.12.032</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16413785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit42"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kurzweil</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Keynote Speech:
Raymond Kurzweil</article-title>. In <source>Proceedings of the 2006
ACM/IEEE conference on Supercomputing</source>; SC&#x02019;06;<publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>, <year>2006</year>; pp <fpage>0-es</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/1188455.1198315</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>Lomize</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pogozheva</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mosberg</surname><given-names>H. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lomize</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>OPM Database
and PPM Web Server: Resources for Positioning of Proteins in Membranes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>D370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr703</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structure and Dynamics of Liquid Water with Different
Long-Range Interaction Truncation and Temperature Control Methods
in Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>J. Comput.
Chem.</source>
<year>2002</year>, <volume>23</volume> (<issue>13</issue>), <fpage>1211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.10117</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12210146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Holian</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Nose&#x02013;Hoover Thermostat</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<year>1985</year>, <volume>83</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>4069</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4074</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.449071</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Martyna</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Constant
Pressure Molecular Dynamics
Algorithms</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<year>1994</year>, <volume>101</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>4177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.467468</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friesner</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The VSGB 2.0 Model: A next Generation
Energy Model
for High Resolution Protein Structure Modeling</article-title>. <source>Proteins: Struct. Funct. Bioinf.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>79</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>2794</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2812</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.23106</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit48"><source>Chemical compound - Functional Groups | Britannica</source>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.britannica.com/science/chemical-compound/Functional-groups">https://www.britannica.com/science/chemical-compound/Functional-groups</uri> (accessed 2023&#x02013;08&#x02013;10).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit49"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lowrie</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Analysis and Comparison
of 2D Fingerprints: Insights into Database Screening Performance Using
Eight Fingerprint Methods</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Graphics
Model.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>29</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmgm.2010.05.008</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit50"><name><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lowrie</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Large-Scale
Systematic
Analysis of 2D Fingerprint Methods and Parameters to Improve Virtual
Screening Enrichments</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>784</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci100062n</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20450209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit51"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Leishman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rankovic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug Discovery
vs HERG</article-title>. In <source>Tactics in Contemporary Drug Design</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Meanwell</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed.; Topics in
Medicinal Chemistry; <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc>, <year>2015</year>; pp <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/7355_2014_38</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit52"><name><surname>Villoutreix</surname><given-names>B. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taboureau</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Computational
Investigations of HERG Channel Blockers:
New Insights and Current Predictive Models</article-title>. <source>Adv. Drug Delivery Rev.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2015.03.003</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit53"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>In Silico Prediction of HERG Potassium
Channel Blockage by Chemical
Category Approaches</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Res.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>582</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5TX00294J</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit54"><name><surname>Aronov</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Predictive
in Silico Modeling for HERG Channel Blockers</article-title>. <source>Drug Discovery Today</source>
<year>2005</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1359-6446(04)03278-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15718164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit55"><name><surname>Pearlstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vaz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rampe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Understanding
the Structure&#x02013;Activity Relationship
of the Human Ether-a-Go-Go-Related Gene Cardiac K+ Channel. A Model
for Bad Behavior</article-title>. <source>J. Med. Chem.</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>46</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2017</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2022</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm0205651</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12747773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit56"><name><surname>Mitcheson</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular
Determinants of High-Affinity Drug Binding
to HERG Channels</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Drug Discovery
Devel.</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>6</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit57"><name><surname>Pearlstein</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vaz</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.-L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Preobrazhenskaya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shchekotikhin</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Korolev</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lysenkova</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Miroshnikova</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hendrix</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rampe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Characterization of
HERG Potassium Channel Inhibition Using CoMSiA 3D QSAR and Homology
Modeling Approaches</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1835</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-894X(03)00196-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12729675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit58"><name><surname>Kay&#x00131;k</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>T&#x000fc;z&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>N. &#x0015e;.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structural Investigation
of Vesnarinone at the Pore Domains of Open and Open-Inactivated States
of HERG1 K+ Channel</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Graphics Model.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmgm.2017.08.017</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit59"><name><surname>Thai</surname><given-names>K.-M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Binary QSAR Model
for Classification of HERG Potassium
Channel Blockers</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>4107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2008.01.017</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18243713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit60"><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mitcheson</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sanguinetti</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular
Determinants of HERG Channel Block</article-title>. <source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source>
<year>2006</year>, <volume>69</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1716</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.105.020990</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16474003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit61"><name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Orhan</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aksoydan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shahraki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Iyison</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Avsar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Screening
of Clinically Approved and Investigation Drugs as Potential Inhibitors
of SARS-CoV-2: A Combined in silico and in vitro Study</article-title>. <source>Mol. Inform.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>41</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <elocation-id>e2100062</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/minf.202100062</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34529322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit62"><name><surname>Aksoydan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular simulations
reveal the impact of RAMP1 on
ligand binding and dynamics of calcitonin gene-related peptide receptor
(CGRPR) heterodimer</article-title>. <source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>141</volume>, <elocation-id>105130</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2021.105130</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34923287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit63"><name><surname>Is</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Durdagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aksoydan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yurtsever</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Proposing
Novel MAO-B Hit Inhibitors Using Multidimensional Molecular Modeling
Approaches and Application of Binary QSAR Models for Prediction of
Their Therapeutic Activity, Pharmacokinetic and Toxicity Properties</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem. Neurosci.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1782</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acschemneuro.8b00095</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29671581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>