<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6376669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3766</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-3766-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Taxonomy, virulence genes and antimicrobial resistance of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolated from extra-intestinal and intestinal infections</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8853-8363</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yanyan</given-names></name><address><email>zhouyanyan1216@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><address><email>wersdu@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>Zheng</given-names></name><address><email>nanzheng0127@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Pingping</given-names></name><address><email>applezhang890804@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>Biao</given-names></name><address><email>kanbiao@icdc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Donghui</given-names></name><address><email>n66ydh@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Jianrong</given-names></name><address><email>youyilab@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 153X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24696.3f</institution-id><institution>Center of Clinical Laboratory, </institution><institution>Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100050 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution>Beijing Center for Disease Prevention and Control, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100013 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory for Infectious Disease Prevention and Control; Department of Diarrheal Diseases, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution><institution>National Institute for Communicable Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 102206 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>158</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Clinical characteristics (taxonomy, virulence genes and antimicrobial resistance ) of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> in isolated from extra-intestinal and intestinal infections were investigated to describe epidemiology, associated virulence factors and optimal therapy options.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Clinical samples (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;115) of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were collected from a general hospital in Beijing between the period 2015 and 2017. Taxonomy was investigate by Multilocus phylogenetic analysis (MLPA), 10 putative virulence factors by use of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and antimicrobial resistance to 15 antibiotics by use of the microbroth dilution method.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The most common species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> detected in samples of intestinal tract included; <italic>A. caviae</italic> (43.9%), <italic>A. veronii</italic> (35.7%), and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (12.2%). Prevalent species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> collected from extra-intestinal infections included; <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> (29.4%), <italic>A. caviae</italic> (29.4%), and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (23.5%). <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> were detected in 1% of stool samples and 29.4% (5/17) of extra-intestinal infections. <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> strains in extra-intestinal infections were related to malignancy. The most common medical conditions among patients with <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infections included malignancy and liver-transplant related cholecystitis. Multiple drug resistance (MDR) was prevalent in extra-intestinal isolates (82.3%, 14/17) and was greater than the prevalence in intestinal isolates (30.6%, 30/98) (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Resistant rates of extra-intestinal isolates were 70.6, 35.3, 23.5 and 5.9% for ceftriaxone, ciprofloxacin, gentamicin and imipenem, respectively, and were higher than found in previous studies. Despite differences in the number and type of virulence genes among samples of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>, no significant correlation was found between invasion and virulent genes in intestinal or extra-intestinal infections.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Overall results of this study support a role for <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> as a potential causative infectious agent of gastroenteritis, and malignancy, liver cirrhosis, post liver transplantation in immunocompromised patients. <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> was more prevalent in samples of extra-intestinal infections when compared to samples of intestinal infections, and was especially prominent in samples of patients presenting with malignancy. <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates from extra-intestinal samples had high rates of drug resistance but 3rd generation cephalosporins, fluoroquinolones and aminoglycosides remain as options to treat severe diarrhea. However, increasing MDR of extra-intestinal infection samples warrants monitoring.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12879-019-3766-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Aeromonas</italic></kwd><kwd>Multilocus phylogenetic analysis (MLPA)</kwd><kwd>Virulence genes </kwd><kwd>Multi-drug resistance</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100005089</institution-id><institution>Beijing Municipal Natural Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>No.7164249</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Capital&#x02019;s Funds for Health Improvement and Research</institution></funding-source><award-id>No.2016-4-1101</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par34">The genus <italic>Aeromonas</italic> is a common, gram-negative, facultative anaerobe, coccobacillary-to-bacillary bacteria that belongs to <italic>Aeromonadaceae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]<italic>.</italic>The genus <italic>Aeromonas</italic> is comprised of mesophiles and psychrophiles which can cause a number of diseases to warm and cold-blooded animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Recently, mesophilic <italic>Aeromonas</italic> have received increased attention as an emergent agent of foodborne illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In humans, <italic>Aeromonas</italic> can cause extra-intestinal diseases, especially in immunocompromised individuals, including septicemia, wound infections, urinary tract infections, hepatobiliary tract infections and necrotizing fasciitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par35"><italic>Aeromonas</italic> have a complex taxonomy and the genus is comprised of over 30 species, however their identification has been limited by use of conventional biochemical identification methods such as matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time of flight masss spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS), and 16S ribosomal ribonucleic acid (rRNA) sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To this end, the use of 5 or more housekeeping genes has been demonstrated as an effective approach for multilocus phylogenetic analysis (MLPA) and species identification of <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, MLPA has been recommended for the verification of taxonomic affiliation by genome sequencing before being submitted to the NCBI database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Current literature indicates that <italic>A. hydrophila</italic>, <italic>A. veronii bv sobria</italic>, and <italic>A. caviae</italic> are responsible for the majority of human infections and clinical isolations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, caution must be exercised as <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> can be misidentified as <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> by use of some phenotypic methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and MLPA is suggeted for molecular subtyping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par36"><italic>A. dhakensis</italic> was initially described as a <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> subspecies in 2002, and <italic>A. aquariorum</italic> described later, and was recommended to be reclassified as a separate species in 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">The pathogenesis of <italic>Aeromonas spp</italic>. involves a series of virulence factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Haemolytic toxins include: aerolysin-related cytotoxic enterotoxin (Act) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], heat-labile cytotonic enterotoxin (Alt), heat-stable cytotonic toxins (Ast) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], hemolysin (HlyA) and aerolysin (AerA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In addition, the type III secretion system (TTSS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], polar flagellum (fla), lateral flagella (laf) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], elastase (Ela) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] and lipase (Lip) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] contribute to the pathogenicity of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>.</p><p id="Par38">Most cases of diarrheal due to <italic>Aeromonads</italic> are self-limiting and treatment with oral or intravenous fluids is effective. However, patients with serious diarrhea or extra-intestinal infection should receive an antimicrobial treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Previously, <italic>Aeromonas</italic> has been observed as resistant to ampicillin, while 3rd generation cephalosporin, fluoroquinolone and aminoglycosides demonstrated excellent antimicrobial activity to <italic>Aeromonas</italic> species isolated from clinical sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. However, extensive use of antibiotics in aquaculture and human treatment has led to increasing resistance in bacterium to antimicrobial drugs. Therefore it is prudent to monitor the development of antimicrobial resistance in species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> to common clinical treatment options.</p><p id="Par39">In the presented study, we investigated characteristics of strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolated from intestinal infections and extra-intestinal infection. Furthermore we evaluated virulence associated genes and antimicrobial resistance of species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Isolates of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></title><p id="Par40">Overall, 1286 stool samples were collected from adults over 14&#x02009;years old presenting with acute diarrhea at a general hospital in Beijng, China, between June and July 2015, 2017. Epidemiology related medical records were completed to assess clinical history and physical fitness of patients (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Samples of Stool were enriched in alkaline peptone water broth (Beijing landbrige, China) for 8&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and a loop of the resulting mixture was subcultured on a blood agar plate (Oxoid, UK) supplemented with 20% ampicillin (Sigma, USA) for 16&#x02013;24&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. An oxidase test (BioMerieuX, France) was performed to select the colonies which were different from Enterobacteriaceae. Microorganisms were identified by use of an automatic bacteriologic analyzer (VITEK2 Compact, BioMerieuX, France). <italic>Salmonella spp</italic>, <italic>Shigella spp</italic> and <italic>Vibrio spp</italic> were also detected on a routine basis. simultaneously.</p><p id="Par420">Extra-intestinal infections due to <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were monitored and the strains were isolated between 2015 and 2017. Clinical samples of blood or bile were cultured in a BACTEC FX400 (BD Diagnostic Instrument Systems, USA). Samples positive for <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were simultaneously subcultured on a blood agar plate and a Maconkey agar plate (BioMerieuX, France). Identification of the isolated microorganisms was completed by use of an automatic bacteriologic analyzer (VITEK2 Compact, BioMerieuX, France). Concurrently, medical records of the patients with extra-intestinal infections due to species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were reviewed and age, gender, underlying conditions, microbiological findings and outcome were assembled.</p><p id="Par43">Strains were stored in a Luria broth: glycerol mixture (80:20) at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until identification was performed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Molecular identification and subtyping of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates</title><p id="Par44">Molecular identification and subtyping of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates was completed by use of 16S rRNA sequencing and MLPA. Total chromosomal DNA from <italic>Aeromonas</italic> was prepared by use of the DNA purification kit (Tiangen Biotech, China) as specified by the manufacturer. PCR amplification was performed by use of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Taq PCR MasterMix (Tiangen Biotech, China). Primers synthesis and sequencing of PCR products were conducted (Shanghai Sangon Biotech, China). Due to the limitations of molecular identification by 16S rRNA sequencing, phylogenetic analysis of the seven selected housekeeping genes <italic>gyrB</italic>, <italic>rpoD</italic>, <italic>recA</italic>, <italic>dnaJ</italic>, <italic>gyrA</italic>, <italic>dnaX</italic> and <italic>atpD</italic> was completed to identify strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>. Primers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] used for PCR amplification are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>. Concatenated 7-gene phylogenetic trees were constructed and compared with representative species by use of MLPA as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Unrooted neighbour-joining phylogenetic trees were prepared by use of MEGA 5.0 software with Bootstrap values calculated by use of 1000 replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Detection of virulence-associated genes</title><p id="Par45">The presence of 10 genes encoding virulence factors was determined by use of PCR. Primers are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, including <italic>alt</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], <italic>ast</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], <italic>hlyA</italic>, <italic>aerA, act, ascF-G</italic> of TTSS, <italic>laf</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], <italic>lip</italic>, <italic>fla</italic>, and <italic>ela</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. PCR amplification reactions were performed at a final volume of 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;l, containing 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Taq PCR MasterMix (2&#x000d7;), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M primer, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l DNA template (~&#x02009;30-40&#x02009;ng), and 17&#x02009;&#x003bc;l ddH<sub>2</sub>O. Cycling conditions consisted of an initial single cycle at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min, followed by 30&#x02009;cycles of denaturation at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s, annealing was completed at 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C&#x02013;60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s, elongation was completed at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;min and followed by a final cycle at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 7&#x02009;min. The PCR products were sequenced for further confirmation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Antibiotic susceptibility test</title><p id="Par46">Antibiotic susceptibility tests were performed by use of the microbroth dilution method according to guidelines of the current Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI). Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> strains to 15 antibiotics were determined and included; gentamycin (GEN), imipenem (IPM), ampicillin (AMP), cefoxitin (FOX), ceftriaxone (CRO), amoxicillin-clavulanate (AMC), nalidixic acid (NAL), ciprofloxacin (CIP), chloramphenicol (CHL), tetracycline (TCY), doxycycline (DOX), azithromycin (AZM), cefepime (FEP), sulfonamides (Sas) and trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (SXT). <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922 was used as the quality-control strain for susceptibility testing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Definitions</title><p id="Par47">Multiple drug resistance (MDR) was was defined as acquired non-susceptibility to at least one agent in three or more antimicrobial categories, according the criteria for defining MDR, XDR and PDR in <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">Intestinal infections related to a strain of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were diagnosed as patients presenting with acute diarrhea and a sample culture positive for a strain of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>. Extra-intestinal infections related to a strain of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were diagnosed as patients presenting with inflammation in a region not identified as intestinal and a sample culture positive for a strain of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical methods</title><p id="Par49">Data were analyzed by use of the x<sup>2</sup> test and Fisher&#x02019;s exact test (SPSS 15.0), When <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 results were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Clinical features</title><p id="Par50"><italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> were identified as the causative agent of diarrhea in 98 (7.6%) of 1286 patients. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics were shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>. Gender ratio (male: female) was 0.94 (46/49) among 98 patiens presenting with diarrhea caused by strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>. Sources of infections were largely unknown and likely originate from contaminated food. However, 3% of patients identified seafood, cooked food or frozen drinks as likely sources. Twenty percent of patients presented with vomiting, 35.8% abdominal pain, 11.6% fever (body temperature&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;37.7&#x02009;&#x000b0;C), and 9.1% had mild dehydration. Approximately 70% of patients presenting with diarrhea caused by a strain of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> had loose stools for &#x02265;3 times per day, 29.4% had watery stools, and 1.0% had mucus-like stool. Erythrocytes and leukocytes were present in 28.4 and 11.6% of samples of stool collected from patients infected by strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> when observed by use of high magnification (HP, &#x000d7;&#x02009;40). In addition, 6.3% of stool samples presented with erythrocytes and leukocytes. Infection of patients by other enteropathogens was observed in three patients (3/98, 3.1%). Combinations of infectious species included; <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> with <italic>A.caviae</italic>, <italic>Vibrio fluvialis</italic> with <italic>A. veronii</italic> and <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> with <italic>A. veronii.</italic></p><p id="Par51">Between 2015 and 2017, 17 strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> causing extra-intestinal infections were identified (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). With the excepted for 3 children accepting a liver transplant (age&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;4&#x02009;years), the average age of the 14 patients was 58.5&#x02009;years old. The gender ratio (male: female) was 1.83 (11/6). None of the 17 patients were ICU admissions nor was there any acute respiratory failure or mortality. Six (35.3%) patients suffered from <italic>Aeromonas</italic>-related cholecystitis following a liver transplant and 6 (35.3%) pantients presented with malignant tumors. Overall, the most common underlying conditions of patients presenting with <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infections were liver transplantation and malignancy (12/17), In addition, patients presenting with <italic>Aeromonas</italic> related infections were associated with increased prevalence of lung cancer in our study.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical characteristics of 17 patients presenting with extra-intestinal infections likely caused by species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Strains</th><th>Species</th><th>Disease spectrum</th><th>Underlying condition</th><th>Polymicrobial infection</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>BJ127</td><td>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</td><td>Wound infection after cholecystectomy</td><td>Liver cirrhosi and Gallbladder cyst</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ069</td><td>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</td><td>Bacteremia</td><td>Pneumonia</td><td>
<italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ123</td><td>
<italic>A. media</italic>
</td><td>Bacteremia</td><td>Pneumonia and uremia</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ015</td><td>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</td><td>Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>
<italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ022</td><td>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</td><td>Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>
<italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ016</td><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>
<italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ093</td><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ128</td><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>Chronic Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>
<italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ124</td><td>
<italic>A. sanarellii</italic>
</td><td>Cholecystitis</td><td>Post Liver transplantation</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ042</td><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>Urinary infection</td><td>Renal tuberculosis</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ043</td><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>Urinary infection</td><td>Renal insufficiency</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ126</td><td>
<italic>A. veronii</italic>
</td><td>Wound infection after Rectal cancer radical resection</td><td>Rectal cancer and Esophagus cancer</td><td>
<italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>BJ014</td><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>Hydrothorax</td><td>Lung cancer</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ017</td><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>Hydrothorax</td><td>Lung cancer</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ018</td><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>Wrapped empyema</td><td>Lung cancer</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ054</td><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>Hydrothorax</td><td>Esophagus cancer</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>BJ125</td><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>Wound infection after mastectomy</td><td>Breast cancer</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par52">Eleven patients presented with monomicrobial related Aeromonas infections, and 6 patients presented with polymicrobial <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infections (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Of polymicrobial infections, two consisted of <italic>A.caviae</italic> and <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>; and two were <italic>A.aquariorum</italic> with <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae.</italic> One patient presented with <italic>A.aquariorum</italic> and <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> and one patient with <italic>A.veronii</italic> and <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>. <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> was the most common combined pathogen (66.7%, 4/6).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Genotyping of species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></title><p id="Par53">Results of MLPA performed with the concatenated 7-gene phylogenetic tree analysis classified 113 of 115 (98.3%) <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates to 8 different species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The four most prevalent species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were <italic>A. caviae</italic> (41.7%), <italic>A. veronii</italic> (31.3%), <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (13.9%), and <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> (5.2%). As presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, comparative analysis of genotyping demonstrated differences between intestinal and extra-intestinal isolates was completed. Overall, there was a significant difference in the assemblage of isolates as intestinal isolates generally contained species of <italic>A. caviae</italic> (43.9%), <italic>A. veronii</italic> (35.7%), and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (12.2%). In contrast, extra-intestinal isolates generally contained <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> (29.4%), <italic>A. caviae</italic> (29.4%), and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (23.5%). There was significant difference between intestinal and extra-intestinal isolates for the species <italic>A. veronii</italic> and <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, x<sup>2</sup> test). Five of 6 strains of <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> were isolated from patients with solid tumors, while only 1 strain of <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> was associated with an intestinal infection.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Unrooted neighbor -joined phylogenetic tree of species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolated patients presenting with intestinal or extra-intestinal infections (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1000 bootstrap replicates). The tree was constructed by use of MLPA of seven housekeeping genes (<italic>gyrB</italic>, <italic>rpoD</italic>, <italic>recA</italic>, <italic>dnaJ</italic>, <italic>gyrA</italic>, <italic>dnaX</italic> and <italic>atpD</italic>). Red tree lines and triangles represent species detected in this study, blue lines represent the numbers of the extra-intestinal infections due to species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>. The number of identified strains is indicated in brackets. Black tree lines and triangles represent other representative species</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2019_3766_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of species of <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> in isolates collected from intestinal and extra-intestinal samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Species</th><th>No. total strains (%)</th><th>No. intestinal isolates (%)</th><th>No. extra-intestinal isolates (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>A. veronii</italic>
</td><td>36 (31.3)</td><td>35 (35.7)</td><td>1 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</td><td>48 (41.7)</td><td>43 (43.9)</td><td>5 (29.4)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</td><td>16 (13.9)</td><td>12 (12.2)</td><td>4 (23.5)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. media</italic>
</td><td>2 (1.7)</td><td>1 (1.0)</td><td>1 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</td><td>6 (5.2)</td><td>1 (1.0)</td><td>5 (29.4)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. sanarellii</italic>
</td><td>2(1.7)</td><td>1 (1.0)</td><td>1 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. enteropelogenes</italic>
</td><td>2 (1.7)</td><td>2 (2.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>A. bivalvium</italic>
</td><td>1 (0.9)</td><td>1 (1.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td>Unknown</td><td>2 (1.7)</td><td>2 (2.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>115</td><td>98</td><td>17</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Distribution of virulence genes in strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></title><p id="Par54">Presence of multiple virulence genes was common among isolates of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> and 40 virulence combinations of 10 putative virulence genes were identified. The predominant combination (i.e. pattern) of virulence genes was <italic>alt</italic>/<italic>ela</italic>/<italic>lip</italic>/<italic>fla</italic> (pattern1), which presented in 27.0% of patients presenting with an infection related to a isolate of <italic>Aeromonas</italic>. In addition, the patterns of <italic>act</italic>/<italic>fla</italic> (pattern 2), <italic>alt</italic>/<italic>ela</italic>/<italic>lip</italic> (pattern 3) and <italic>act</italic>/<italic>ascF-G</italic>/<italic>fla</italic> (pattern 4) were prevalent among patients<italic>..</italic> As presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, the pattern of virulence genes varied among genus&#x02019;s. Of the four most prevalent species, the haemolytic genes <italic>act</italic> was prevalent in <italic>A. veronii</italic> and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>. The haemolytic genes <italic>hlyA</italic> was prevalent in <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>, and the haemolytic genes <italic>aerA</italic> was more prevalent in <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>. The enterotoxin gene <italic>ast</italic> was identified primarily in <italic>A. hydrophila</italic>. The enterotoxin gene <italic>alt</italic>, extracellular protease genes <italic>ela</italic> and <italic>lip</italic> were less prevalent in <italic>A. veronii</italic>. The TTSS genes (<italic>ascF-G</italic>) was prevalent in <italic>A. hydrophila</italic>. <italic>A. veronii</italic> carried pattern 2 and 4 and <italic>A. caviae</italic> carried pattern1 and 3. The species <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> and <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> had diverse virulence patterns, 93.3% <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> and 100% <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> had 5 or more virulence genes.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Virulence related genes identified in isolates of species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Gene</th><th>
<italic>A.veronii</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>A. caviae</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>A. dhakensis</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>A. hydrophila</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th>No. strains (%)</th><th>No. strains (%)</th><th>No. strains (%)</th><th>No. strains (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>ast</italic>
</td><td>2 (5.6)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>3 (18.8)</td><td>6 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>act</italic>
</td><td>36 (100.0)</td><td>1 (2.1)</td><td>10 (62.5)</td><td>1 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>alt</italic>
</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>43 (89.6)</td><td>14 (87.5)</td><td>4 (66.7)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>hlyA</italic>
</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>14 (87.5)</td><td>5 (83.3)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>aerA</italic>
</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td>10 (62.5)</td><td>1 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>ascF-G</italic>
</td><td>14 (38.9)</td><td>2 (4.2)</td><td>4 (25.0)</td><td>4 (66.7)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>ela</italic>
</td><td>6 (16.7)</td><td>48 (100.0)</td><td>16 (100.0)</td><td>6 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>lip</italic>
</td><td>3 (8.3)</td><td>48 (100.0)</td><td>15 (93.8)</td><td>6 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>fla</italic>
</td><td>29 (80.6)</td><td>38 (79.2)</td><td>16 (100.0)</td><td>6 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>laf</italic>
</td><td>2 (5.6)</td><td>2 (4.2)</td><td>1 (6.3)</td><td>2 (33.3)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Susceptibility to antimicrobials</title><p id="Par55">Resistance profiles of the 115 <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates to 15 antimicrobial agents were shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. High resistance to ampicillin (93.9%) and Nalidixic acid (54.8%) was observed in <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates. The majority of isolates (&#x02265;80%) were susceptible to chloramphenicol, gentamicin and the new generation antibiotics ciprofloxacin, ceftriaxone, cefepime, imipenem, sulfonamides, trimethoprim- sulfamethoxazole, doxycycline and azithromycin. Resistance was most prevalent for ciprofloxacin, amoxicillin-clavulanate, cefoxitin, ceftriaxone, sulfonamides, gentamicin and azithromycin in <italic>A. hydrophila</italic>, as a resistance of 66.7, 100.0, 66.7, 66.7, 50.0, 50.0, and 66.7% was observed, respectively. Higher rates of resistance to cefoxitin was also observed in <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> (87.5%). Only 3 strains exhibited resistance to imipenem, all of which were identified as belonging to <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>. Significantly higher rates of resistance to 10 antibiotics (ciprofloxacin, nalidixic acid, amoxicillin-clavulanate, cefoxitin, ceftriaxone, cefepime, sulfonamides, trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, gentamicin and azithromycin) were found among extra-intestinal isolates when compared with intestinal isolates (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, x<sup>2</sup> test).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Antibiotic susceptibility patterns of species of <italic>Aeromonas</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="3">Total</th><th colspan="3">Intestinal infection</th><th colspan="3">Extra-intestinal infection</th></tr><tr><th>Antibiotic</th><th>R<sup>a</sup> [n (%)]</th><th>I [n (%)]</th><th>S [n (%)]</th><th>R [n (%)]</th><th>I [n (%)]</th><th>S [n (%)]</th><th>R [n (%)]</th><th>I [n (%)]</th><th>S [n (%)]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Ampicillin<sup>c</sup></td><td>108(93.9)</td><td>3(2.6)</td><td>4(3.5)</td><td>92(93.9)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>4(4.1)</td><td>16(94.1)</td><td>1(5.9)</td><td>0(0.0)</td></tr><tr><td>Amoxicillin-clavulanate<sup>c</sup></td><td>15(13.0)</td><td>76(66.1)</td><td>24(20.9)</td><td>8(8.2)</td><td>68(69.4)</td><td>22(22.4)</td><td>7(41.2)</td><td>8(47.1)</td><td>2(11.8)</td></tr><tr><td>Imipenem<sup>b</sup></td><td>3(2.6)</td><td>10(8.7)</td><td>102(88.7)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>7(7.1)</td><td>88(89.8)</td><td>1(5.9)</td><td>3(17.6)</td><td>14(82.4)</td></tr><tr><td>Ceftriaxone<sup>b</sup></td><td>17(14.8)</td><td>3(2.6)</td><td>95(82.6)</td><td>5(5.1)</td><td>3(3.1)</td><td>90(91.8)</td><td>12(70.6)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>5(29.4)</td></tr><tr><td>Cefepime<sup>b</sup></td><td>5(4.3)</td><td>3(2.6)</td><td>107(93.0)</td><td>1(1.0)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>97(99.0)</td><td>4(23.5)</td><td>3(17.6)</td><td>10(58.8)</td></tr><tr><td>Cefoxitin<sup>b</sup></td><td>28(24.3)</td><td>6(5.2)</td><td>81(70.4)</td><td>17(17.3)</td><td>5(5.1)</td><td>76(77.6)</td><td>11(64.7)</td><td>1(5.9)</td><td>5(29.4)</td></tr><tr><td>Gentamicin<sup>b</sup></td><td>6(5.2)</td><td>4(3.5)</td><td>105(91.3)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>94(95.9)</td><td>4(23.5)</td><td>2(11.8)</td><td>11(64.7)</td></tr><tr><td>Nalidixic acid<sup>c</sup></td><td>63(54.8)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>52(45.2)</td><td>49(50.0)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>49(50.0)</td><td>14(82.4)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>3(17.6)</td></tr><tr><td>Ciprofloxacin<sup>b</sup></td><td>7(6.1)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>108(93.9)</td><td>1(1.0)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>97(99.0)</td><td>6(35.3)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>11(64.7)</td></tr><tr><td>Chloramphenicol<sup>b</sup></td><td>10(8.7)</td><td>2(1.7)</td><td>103(89.6)</td><td>8(8.2)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>88(89.8)</td><td>2(11.8)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>15(88.2)</td></tr><tr><td>Tetracycline<sup>b</sup></td><td>21(18.3)</td><td>5(4.3)</td><td>89(77.4)</td><td>15(15.3)</td><td>3(3.1)</td><td>80(81.6)</td><td>6(35.3)</td><td>2(11.8)</td><td>9(52.9)</td></tr><tr><td>Doxycycline<sup>c</sup></td><td>4(3.5)</td><td>4(3.5)</td><td>107(93.0)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>2(2.0)</td><td>94(95.9)</td><td>2(11.8)</td><td>2(11.8)</td><td>13(76.5)</td></tr><tr><td>Azithromycin<sup>c</sup></td><td>5(4.3)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>110(95.7)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>98(100.0)</td><td>5(29.4)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12(70.6)</td></tr><tr><td>Trimethoprim- Sulfamethoxazole<sup>b</sup></td><td>6(5.2)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>109(94.8)</td><td>1(1.0)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>97(99.0)</td><td>5(29.4)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>12(70.6)</td></tr><tr><td>Sulfonamides<sup>c</sup></td><td>19 (16.5)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>96(83.5)</td><td>12(12.2)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>86(87.8)</td><td>7(41.2)</td><td>0(0.0)</td><td>10(58.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>R: Resistant; I: Intermediate; S: Sensitive</p><p><sup>b</sup>Breakpoints are based on the CLSI&#x000a0;M45-A3 standards for <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic></p><p><sup>c</sup>Other breakpoints refer to the CLSI&#x000a0;M100-S26E criteria for <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par56">Of the 115 strains, 33 strains (28.7%) exhibited 35 multiple-drug resistance (MDR) patterns to 15 antimicrobial agents. Eighty-three percent (5/6) of strains of <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> and 81.2% (13/16) of strains of <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> presented with MDR, while less MDR isolates were found in <italic>A.caviae</italic> (39.6%, 19/48) and <italic>A.veronii</italic> (16.7%, 6/36). Intestinal strains (30.6%, 30/98) presented with significantly less rates of MDR when compare to isolates from extra-intestinal strains (82.3%, 14/17), indicating acquisition of MDR was likely from in the hospital.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par57">In the presented study, 115 isolates of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were collected from a general hospital in Beijing between 2015 and 2017. Overall, the abundance and prevalence of strains of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> were different between intestinal and extra-intestinal infections. In our study, 1% of samples isolated from samples of stool of patients with intestinal infection were positive for <italic>A. hydrophila,</italic> while in 29.4% of extra-intestinal infections. Thus, results of this study indicated that the <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> was not the primary pathogen contributing to acute gastroenteritis, however it was more prevalent in extra-intestinal infections when compared to samples from patients with intestinal infections. Interestingly, 5 strains of <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> strains from extra-intestinal infections were present in patients presented with malignant tumor. These results might indicate a preference of strains of <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> and other <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> to colonize differently<italic>. A. veronii</italic> was more common in samples of patients presenting with acute gastroenteritis (35.7%) but was rare in patients with extra-intestinal infections (5.9%), which was similar to previous results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par58">In addition, results of our study demonstrate a potential relationship between <italic>Aeromonas</italic> and clinical cirrhosis or malignancy as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and liver-transplant related cholecystitis. These results might be related to bacterial translocation, use of antacids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] or immunosuppressive agents following liver transplantation.</p><p id="Par59">Prevalence of antimicrobial-resistance was greater in extra-intestinal isolates when compared to the previous study. In our study, rates of resistance to ceftriaxone, ciprofloxacin, gentamicin and imipenem was 70.6, 35.3, 23.5 and 5.9%, while a study completed in Taiwan was 7.7, 6, 3.3 and 1.1%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] . Additionally, a study completed in Korea the rates of resistance were 15.5, 10.1, 7.1 and 9.8%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. When compared with the rates of intestinal isolates, the rate of MDR in extra-intestinal isolates was greater. These findings indicate selective pressures in hospitals on strains of infectious bacteria due to the extensive use of antimicrobial agents and warrants more attention in the future.</p><p id="Par60">In our study, two bacteremia-related <italic>Aeromonas</italic> species were identified; <italic>A. media</italic> and <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>. These results were different from previous results where <italic>A. caviae</italic> was identified as bacteremia-related <italic>Aeromonas</italic> species in Japan, <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> and <italic>A. veronii biovar sobria</italic> in Taiwan, and <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> and <italic>A. caviae</italic> in Korea and Taiwan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">A study completed in Southern India reported a resistance rate to ceftriaxone resistant of 31% (9/29) for isolates of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> from samples of stool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In our study resistance rates for ceftriaxone, ciprofloxacin and gentamicin and imipenem were 5.1, 1.0, 2.0 and 2.0% in <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates of patients presenting with diarrhea and were similar to rates in Shanghai (5.7, 3.6, 0.5, and 2.6%, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. These results along with results of the study competed in Shanghai indicate that 3rd generation cephalosporins, fluoroquinolones and aminoglycosides are a treatment option for severe diarrhea but not for extra-intestinal infections originating in Eastern China.</p><p id="Par62">It is important to note that only 3 strains exhibited resistance to imipenem, all of which belonged to the genus <italic>A. dhakensis</italic>. The genus <italic>A. dhakensis</italic> should be the focus of future research as they harbored high numbers of virulence genes, high rates of drug resistance and a high degree of infection in intestinal and extra-intestinal samples. In addition, <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> presented with a high number of virulence genes and high rates of drug resistance. <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> have previously been isolated from wounds in two cases as reported by Christopher J. Grim et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], and were classified as having MDR and multiple virulence genes.</p><p id="Par63">In the presented study, <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> was the most common combined pathogen. These results demonstrate that cholecystitis post Liver transplant predisposed patients to polymicrobial <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infections, while malignant cancers, such as rectal cancer, might predispose patients to monomicrobial <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infection. A previous study in Taiwan found that <italic>E. coli</italic> was the most common pathogen (42%) in polymicrobial infections, then <italic>Klebsiella spp.</italic> (24%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Conversely, cirrhosis predisposed patients to monomicrobial <italic>Aeromonas</italic> bacteremia while malignant cancer predisposed patients to polymicrobial <italic>Aeromonas</italic> bacteremia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. This difference indicates a high degree of heterogeneity in the distribution of intestinal bacteria, and region specific presence of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> infections.</p><p id="Par65">The pathogenic mechanism of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> was multifactorial and complex, and likely involves a series of virulence genes involved in this process. Despite <italic>Aeromonas</italic> harboring different numbers and types of virulence genes, there was no significant correlation found between infection and virulent genes of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> in intestinal infections and extra-intestinal infections. For example, intestinal infections, <italic>alt</italic> have been reported as associated with loose stool, <italic>alt</italic> plus <italic>ast</italic> with watery stools, and <italic>act</italic> with bloody diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In the presented study, 3 watery stool samples were associated with <italic>ast</italic>, however 25 samples of watery stool were not. In addition, a relationship between infection and presence of virulent genes was not observed and might be related to the limited number of strains isolated in extra-intestinal infections. Similarly, a study completed by Wu et al. found no association between the presence of the genes <italic>aerA, hlyA, alt, ast, ascFG</italic> in isolates of Aeromonas and development of extra-intestinal infections or bacterium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">In conclusion, <italic>Aeromonas spp</italic>. should be considered as a causative infectious agent in immunocompromised patients especially those presenting with malignancy, liver cirrhosis and following a liver transplant. In addition, <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> was more prevalent in extra-intestinal infections when compared to intestinal infections, especially for patients presenting with a malignancy. Extra-intestinal <italic>Aeromonas</italic> isolates possessed higher rates of drug resistance<italic>.</italic> However, 3rd generation cephalosporins, fluoroquinolones and aminoglycosides remain as effective treatments for patients presenting with severe diarrhea but not for extra-intestinal infections. In addition, increasing prevalence of drug resistance and MDR in extra-intestinal isolates of <italic>Aeromonas</italic> requires attention and further monitoring.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12879_2019_3766_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Medical Record table upload. (DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12879_2019_3766_MOESM2_ESM.doc"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Sequence of primers used for amplification of housekeeping genes and virulence factor genes. (DOC 58 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12879_2019_3766_MOESM3_ESM.xls"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p>Clinical data, genes of toxins and drug resistant patterns for 95 diarrhea patients related to <italic>Aeromonas spp. (XLS 578 kb)</italic></p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12879_2019_3766_MOESM4_ESM.xls"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p>Clinical data, genes of toxins and drug resistant patterns for 17 patients related to <italic>Aeromonas spp.</italic> in extra-intestinal infections. (XLS 49 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>Act</term><def><p id="Par5">aerolysin-related cytotoxic enterotoxin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AerA</term><def><p id="Par6">aerolysin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Alt</term><def><p id="Par7">heat-labile cytotonic enterotoxin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMC</term><def><p id="Par8">amoxicillin-clavulanate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMP</term><def><p id="Par9">ampicillin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ast</term><def><p id="Par10">heat-stable cytotonic toxins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AZM</term><def><p id="Par11">azithromycin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CHL</term><def><p id="Par12">chloramphenicol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CIP</term><def><p id="Par13">ciprofloxacin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CLSI</term><def><p id="Par14">Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRO</term><def><p id="Par15">ceftriaxone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DOX</term><def><p id="Par16">doxycycline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ela</term><def><p id="Par17">elastase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FEP</term><def><p id="Par18">cefepime</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FOX</term><def><p id="Par19">cefoxitin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GEN</term><def><p id="Par20">gentamycin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HlyA</term><def><p id="Par21">hemolysin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HP</term><def><p id="Par22">high magnification</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPM</term><def><p id="Par23">imipenem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Lip</term><def><p id="Par24">lipase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDR</term><def><p id="Par25">multiple-drug resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC</term><def><p id="Par26">minimum inhibitory concentrations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLPA</term><def><p id="Par27">multilocus phylogenetic analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NAL</term><def><p id="Par28">nalidixic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p id="Par29">Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Sas</term><def><p id="Par30">sulfonamides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SXT</term><def><p id="Par31">trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCY</term><def><p id="Par32">tetracycline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TTSS</term><def><p id="Par33">type III secretion system</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the medical staff from the intestinal clinic of Beijing Friendship Hospital.</p><p>for registering the information of diarrhea patients. We also would like to thank Dr. Duochun Wang for the helpful expert technical assistance.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par67">This work was supported by Capital&#x02019;s Funds for Health Improvement and Research (No.2016&#x02013;4-1101) and Beijing Natural Science Foundation (No.7164249). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par68">The datasets used during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>YD and SJ designed the study. ZY, YL, NZ, ZP performed experiments. KB revised it critically for important intellectual content. All authors contributed to the data analysis and writing. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The study obtained ethical approval (2017-P2&#x02013;095-01) from the Medical Ethics Committee of Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, P.R China. Given that the study was retrospective without any interventions in treatment and all the data were collected and analyzed anonymously, the requirement for informed consent was waived. Permissions for obtaining related medical records were approved by hosipital.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>International committee on systematics of prokaryotes subcommittee on the taxonomy of Aeromonadaceae, Vibrionaceae and related organisms &#x00026;nbsp;minutes of the meetings, 31 march 2016, Roscoff, France</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.001675</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28368240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28368240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Igbinosa IH, Igumbor EU, Aghdasi F, et al. Emerging Aeromonas species infections and their significance in public health. ScientificWorldJournal 2012; 2012: 625023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pablos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Remacha</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Calleja</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identity, virulence genes, and clonal relatedness of Aeromonas isolates from patients with diarrhea and drinking water</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-010-0982-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20549532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20549532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus Aeromonas: taxonomy, pathogenicity, and infection</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00039-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20065325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20065325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Murcia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Monera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Saavedra MJ, et al.Multilocus phylogenetic analysis of the genus Aeromonas</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbio</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2010.11.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Murcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaz-Hidalgo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Svec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Aeromonas</italic> cavernicola sp. nov., isolated from fresh water of a brook in a cavern</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-012-0253-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23129345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23129345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Murcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaz-Hidalgo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aeromonas lusitana sp. nov., isolated from untreated water and vegetables</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>72</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-016-0997-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26868258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26868258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueras</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Latif-Eugenin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x02018;Aeromonas intestinalis&#x02019; and &#x02018;Aeromonas enterica&#x02019; isolated from human faeces, &#x02018;Aeromonas crassostreae&#x02019; from oyster and &#x02018;Aeromonas aquatilis&#x02019; isolated from lake water represent novel species</article-title><source>New Microbes New Infect</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nmni.2016.11.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28050251?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28050251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schleifer</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of Bacteria and archaea: past, present and future</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>32</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2009.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19819658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaz-Hidalgo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strategies to avoid wrongly labelled genomes using as example the detected wrong taxonomic affiliation for aeromonas genomes in the GenBank database</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0115813</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25607802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and therapeutic implications of Aeromonas bacteremia: 14 years nation-wide experiences in Korea</article-title><source>Infect Chemother</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3947/ic.2016.48.4.274</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28032485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28032485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravena-Roman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harnett</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aeromonas aquariorum is widely distributed in clinical and environmental specimens and can be misidentified as Aeromonas hydrophila</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>49</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3006</fpage><lpage>3008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00472-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21697316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21697316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Occurrence, molecular characterization, and antimicrobial susceptibility of Aeromonas spp. in marine species of shrimps cultured at inland low salinity ponds</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2014.11.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25583334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25583334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution, virulence-associated genes and antimicrobial resistance of Aeromonas isolates from diarrheal patients and water, China</article-title><source>J Inf Secur</source><year>2015</year><volume>70</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>608</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaz-Hidalgo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Murcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueras</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reclassification of Aeromonas hydrophila subsp. dhakensis Huys et al. 2002 and Aeromonas aquariorum Martinez-Murcia et al. 2008 as Aeromonas dhakensis sp. nov. comb nov. and emendation of the species Aeromonas hydrophila</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2012.12.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23485124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23485124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The main Aeromonas pathogenic factors</article-title><source>ISRN Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>256261</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5402/2012/256261</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23724321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23724321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cloning, expression, and sequence analysis of a cytolytic enterotoxin gene from Aeromonas hydrophila</article-title><source>Can J Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>39</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/m93-073</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8330262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8330262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of various enterotoxins in Aeromonas hydrophila-induced gastroenteritis: generation of enterotoxin gene-deficient mutants and evaluation of their enterotoxic activity</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1924</fpage><lpage>1935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.70.4.1924-1935.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11895956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11895956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heuzenroeder</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Flower</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of two hemolytic toxin genes in clinical and environmental isolates of Aeromonas spp.: correlation with virulence in a suckling mouse model</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>174</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1999.tb13559.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10234831?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10234831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A type III secretion system is required for Aeromonas hydrophila AH-1 pathogenesis</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2004</year><volume>72</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.72.3.1248-1256.2004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14977925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabaan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gryllos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Motility and the polar flagellum are required for Aeromonas caviae adherence to HEp-2 cells</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2001</year><volume>69</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>4257</fpage><lpage>4267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.69.7.4257-4267.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11401962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11401962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Altarriba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lateral flagella are required for increased cell adherence, invasion and biofilm formation by Aeromonas spp</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2003</year><volume>224</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1097(03)00418-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12855171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12855171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cascon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yugueros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Temprano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A major secreted elastase is essential for pathogenicity of Aeromonas hydrophila</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2000</year><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3233</fpage><lpage>3241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.68.6.3233-3241.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10816468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10816468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis and expression of the extracellular lipase of Aeromonas hydrophila MCC-2</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>143</volume><issue>Pt 3</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-143-3-803</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9084164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9084164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro antimicrobial susceptibility of clinical isolates of Aeromonas caviae, Aeromonas hydrophila and Aeromonas veronii biotype sobria</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2002</year><volume>49</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/49.4.701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11909850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tena</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Praetorius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimeno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extraintestinal infection due to Aeromonas spp.: review of 38 cases</article-title><source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1157/13100463</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17386217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17386217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghenghesh</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahouma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorgani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aeromonas in Arab countries: 1995-2014</article-title><source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cimid.2015.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26577192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26577192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltan Dallal</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazaheri Nezhad Fard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavan Talkhabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, virulence and antimicrobial resistance patterns of Aeromonas spp. isolated from children with diarrhea</article-title><source>Germs</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11599/germs.2016.1094</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27622161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27622161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Willayat</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multiplex PCR for detection of enterotoxin genes in Aeromonas species isolated from foods of animal origin and human diarrhoeal samples</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>117</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1721</fpage><lpage>1729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12641</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25195707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25195707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Calleja</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Foodborne and indicator bacteria in farmed molluscan shellfish before and after depuration</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-72.7.1443</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19681267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19681267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of six virulence factors in Aeromonas species isolated from US drinking water utilities: a PCR identification</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>97</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2004.02398.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15479425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magiorakos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puthucheary</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Puah</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of clinical isolates of Aeromonas species from Malaysia</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e30205</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030205</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22383958?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical significance and distribution of putative virulence markers of 116 consecutive clinical Aeromonas isolates in southern Taiwan</article-title><source>J Inf Secur</source><year>2007</year><volume>54</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lay</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Different clinical characteristics between polymicrobial and monomicrobial Aeromonas bacteremia--a study of 216 cases</article-title><source>Intern Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2415</fpage><lpage>2421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.49.4117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21088342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21088342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations of bacteremia caused by Aeromonas species in southern Taiwan</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e91642</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0091642</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24614100?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24614100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinoop</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of ceftriaxone-resistant Aeromonas spp. isolates from stool samples of both children and adults in southern India</article-title><source>J Health Popul Nutr</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41043-015-0036-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26825984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grim</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Aeromonas hydrophila wound pathotypes by comparative genomic and functional analyses of virulence genes</article-title><source>MBio</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e00064</fpage><lpage>e00013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00064-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23611906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23611906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansaruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Talukder</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of enterotoxin genes in Aeromonas spp. isolated from children with diarrhea, healthy controls, and the environment</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3785</fpage><lpage>3790</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11015403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11015403</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>