<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4703304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26735303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-42010</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular Evolution of the Nuclear Factor (Erythroid-Derived 2)-Like 2 Gene <italic>Nrf2</italic> in Old World Fruit Bats (Chiroptera: Pteropodidae)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Molecular Evolution of <italic>Nrf2</italic> Gene in Old World Fruit Bats</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Qiuyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Di</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shuyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Yi-Hsuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff007"><sup>7</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Ecology and Evolution, Shanghai Engineering Research Center of Molecular Therapeutics and New Drug Development, East China Normal University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label>
<addr-line>Kunming College of Life Science, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Ecology and Evolution, Institute of Estuarine and Coastal Research, East China Normal University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff005"><label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiology, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff006"><label>6</label>
<addr-line>College of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine, Shenyang Agricultural University, Shenyang, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff007"><label>7</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Ecology and Evolution, School of Life Sciences, East China Normal University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>Antonis</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Vanderbilt University, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: QY LZ YP SZ. Performed the experiments: QY LZ DL. Analyzed the data: QY LZ YP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SZ. Wrote the paper: QY LZ DMI YP.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>szhang_sau@126.com</email> (SZ); <email>yihsuanp@gmail.com</email> (YP)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0146274</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 Yin et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yin et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0146274.pdf"/><abstract><p>Mammals developed antioxidant systems to defend against oxidative damage in their daily life. Enzymatic antioxidants and low molecular weight antioxidants (LMWAs) constitute major parts of the antioxidant systems. Nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2 (Nrf2, encoded by the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene) is a central transcriptional regulator, regulating transcription, of many antioxidant enzymes. Frugivorous bats eat large amounts of fruits that contain high levels of LMWAs such as vitamin C, thus, a reliance on LMWAs might greatly reduce the need for antioxidant enzymes in comparison to insectivorous bats. Therefore, it is possible that frugivorous bats have a reduced need for Nrf2 function due to their substantial intake of diet-antioxidants. To test whether the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene has undergone relaxed evolution in fruit-eating bats, we obtained <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences from 16 species of bats, including four Old World fruit bats (Pteropodidae) and one New World fruit bat (Phyllostomidae). Our molecular evolutionary analyses revealed changes in the selection pressure acting on <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene and identified seven specific amino acid substitutions that occurred on the ancestral lineage leading to Old World fruit bats. Biochemical experiments were conducted to examine Nrf2 in Old World fruit bats and showed that the amount of catalase, which is regulated by Nrf2, was significantly lower in the brain, heart and liver of Old World fruit bats despite higher levels of Nrf2 protein in Old World fruit bats. Computational predictions suggest that three of these seven amino acid replacements might be deleterious to Nrf2 function. Therefore, the results suggest that <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene might have experienced relaxed constraint in Old World fruit bats, however, we cannot rule out the possibility of positive selection. Our study provides the first data on the molecular adaptation of <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene in frugivorous bats in compensation to the increased levels of LWMAs from their fruit-diet.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the National Science Foundation of China (No. 31100273/C030101) to YP, and the Key Construction Program of the National &#x02018;985 Project&#x02019; and &#x02018;211 Project&#x02019; and Shanghai Excellent Academic Leaders Project (No. 11XD1402000) and the National Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31172077, 31570382) to SZ. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All Nrf2 sequence files are available from the GeneBank database (accession number(s) KT345715, KT345716, KT345717, KT345718, KT345719, KT345720, KT345721, KT345722, KT345723, KT345724, KT345725). Datasets supporting the results are available in the Dryad digital repository, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link> (DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All Nrf2 sequence files are available from the GeneBank database (accession number(s) KT345715, KT345716, KT345717, KT345718, KT345719, KT345720, KT345721, KT345722, KT345723, KT345724, KT345725). Datasets supporting the results are available in the Dryad digital repository, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link> (DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Free radicals, including reactive oxygen (ROS) and nitrogen species (RNS), are continuously produced by aerobic metabolism and from external exposure. Under normal physiological conditions, the major endogenous source of ROS is proton leakage from the electron transport chain (ETCs) in the mitochondria [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Escaped protons react with oxygen, with approximately 1&#x02013;2% of the oxygen consumed by cell being diverted to generate hydrogen peroxide [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and superoxide (O<sub>2</sub><sup><bold>&#x000b7;-</bold></sup>) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], which are the primary ROS found in living cells. These reactive species can attack DNA, protein and other macromolecules leading to oxidative damage [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The uncontrolled generation of reactive species results in oxidative stress and is harmful to organisms as it causes pathological changes.</p><p>Organisms have developed antioxidant defense systems to protect against oxidative damage and maintain cellular homeostasis. Antioxidant defense systems consist of functionally connected groups of enzymes and low molecular weight antioxidants (LMWAs) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Antioxidant enzymes, for example catalase and superoxide dismutase, are endogenously produced and are highly efficient at scavenging ROS. Transcription of genes for these enzymes is regulated by nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2 (Nrf2), a member of the cap &#x02018;n&#x02019; collar (CNC) subfamily of basic region leucine zipper (bZip) transcription factors [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Nrf2 regulates the transcription of targeted genes via <italic>cis</italic>-acting enhancer elements known as the antioxidant response elements (AREs), located in the promoter regions, with the core sequence of the ARE being 5&#x02019;-RTGAYNNNGCR-3&#x02019; [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Nrf2 is ubiquitously expressed in tissues and is the main regulator of the redox response. Nrf2 knockout mice display substantially increased susceptibility to oxidative stress [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and exhibit large decreases in the expression of catalase [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and NQO1 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. On the other hand, some reactive species scavengers are not enzymes, but instead are LMWAs. LMWAs are a group of compounds that originate from endogenous sources or exogenously from diet, which are capable of eliminating reactive species in direct or indirect ways [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Examples of diet-derived antioxidants are vitamins A, C and E and the carotenoids, which play major roles in mitigating the negative effects of reactive species [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Bats (order: Chiroptera) are one of the most widespread and diversified mammalian groups with over 1100 species in the world [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Like other mammals, bats also possess antioxidant defense systems to protect against damage caused by ROS. Numerous studies in bats have linked oxidative stress with longevity, with lower levels of radicals associated with longer life [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Antioxidants might have a role in this process, as bats are exceptional long-lived, compared with nonflying mammals of similar size and basal metabolic rate [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Bats exhibit a great diversity in food habits including frugivory, nectarivory, insectivory, piscivory, carnivory and sanguivory [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. This diversity in food habits is considered to have evolved independently several times from insectivorous bat ancestors [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Old World fruit bats (OWFBs; Suborder: Yinpterochiroptera; Family: Pteropodidae) and New World fruit bats (NWFBs; Suborder: Yangochiroptera; Family: Phyllostomidae) evolved fruit and nectar-eating habits independently. However, some New World fruit bats switch their food preference to insects when fruits are less abundant [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Megabats, especially Old World fruit bats, feed only upon plants, fruits, and leaves. Marshall reported that nearly 188 kinds of plant genera are the food source of megabats, with 144 of them being fruits [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Bats belonging to Pteropodidae can ingest up to 2.5 times their body mass in fruit per night [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Fruits contain large amounts of vitamin C, &#x003b1;-tocopherol and &#x003b2;-carotene, molecules that are dietary antioxidants and play important roles in antioxidant systems [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It was also reported that the daily intake of fruits by <italic>Artibeus jamaicensis</italic> is more than 50% of its body weight and contained nearly 45mg ascorbate [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The GSH and &#x003b1;-tocopherol contents of frugivorous bats have been reported to higher than those of insectivorous bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Schneeberger et al. argued that LWMAs-rich diets might enable frugivorous bats to more efficiently remove pro-oxidants [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Danilo et al. studied antioxidative enzymes in five bats species, finding that the activities of catalase and SODs in frugivorous bats were lower than in insectivorous bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These results suggest that frugivorous bats have a lower reliance on antioxidative enzymes, as their decreased levels of enzymatic antioxidant systems are balanced through an increased dietary input of LMWAs. The finding of a lower levels of antioxidative enzymes in frugivorous bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], lead us to speculate that <italic>Nrf2</italic>, which is the central regulator of antioxidant enzyme gene transcription, may have undergone relaxed evolution in these bats.</p><p>To test our hypothesis, we sequenced the coding region of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene from 11 species of bats, which were then combined with the sequences from 5 other bat species databases. The molecular evolution of these sequences was then studied in bats and other mammals. To validate the results from our molecular evolutionary analyses, we investigated the expression levels of Nrf2 protein and a downstream antioxidant enzyme in representative species of frugivorous and insectivorous bats. While expanding our knowledge on antioxidant adaptations in frugivorous and insectivorous bats, our study might also provide additional insight into understanding the longevity of bats.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The Animal Ethics Committee of East China Normal University approved all procedures, including the collection of bats species and tissues (ID No: AR2012/03001). The capture of bats were permitted by the local Protection and Research Center and the locations of all samples are listed in <xref rid="pone.0146274.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. None of the bat species used in this study are considered endangered. Animals used in this study were sacrificed by rapid decapitation after capture and all efforts were made to minimize potential pain and suffering.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Animal and Tissue Collections</title><p>Details and capture locations of the bat species used in molecular cloning are listed in <xref rid="pone.0146274.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Neotropical bats used for molecular cloning were captured in Mexico during April, 2010, for a previous study [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Four representative bat species was adopted in the biochemical experiments, two insectivorous bats: <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic> (Suborder: Yangochiroptera), <italic>Rhinolophus ferrumequinum</italic> (Suborder: Yinpterochiroptera), and two frugivorous bats: <italic>Rousettus leschenaultia</italic> and <italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic> (Old World fruit bats). Three male individuals from these of the four bats species were captured from different locations in China: <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic> from Fangshan Cave in Beijing (39&#x000b0;48'N, 115&#x000b0;42'E); <italic>Rhinolophus ferrumequinum</italic> from Fish Cave in Anhui Province (30&#x000b0;20'N, 117&#x000b0;50'E); <italic>Rousettus leschenaultia</italic> from Jinlun Cave of Mashan County in Guangxi Province (23&#x000b0;55'N, 108&#x000b0;26'E) and <italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic> from Haikou Park in Hainan Province (20&#x000b0;02'N, 110&#x000b0;20'E), during August to September, 2013. Bats were immediately transported to the laboratory and housed in a large cage (150 cm &#x000d7; 180 cm &#x000d7; 200 cm) until they adapted to the new environment. For each of these species, three individuals were sacrificed by cervical dislocation under conditions that were as similar as possible. Tissues were sampled and immediately stored at -80&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Isolation, Amplification and Sequencing of <italic>Nrf2</italic> Coding Sequences</title><p>Total RNA from 11 bats was isolated from brain tissue using TRizol reagent (Invitrogen) following the standard protocol. RNA was reverse-transcribed into cDNA using a SuperScript<sup>TM</sup> &#x02162; Reverse Transcriptase Kit (Invitrogen). PCR reactions were conducted with primers designed within the coding region of published <italic>Nrf2</italic> cDNA sequences (<xref rid="pone.0146274.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Resulting PCR products were separated using a 1.5% agarose gel and purified with a Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen), and then ligated into pGEM-T Easy vectors (Promega), with positive clones sequenced on an ABI sequencer (Applied Biosystems).</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Taxonomic Coverage</title><p>We sequenced most of the coding region of <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene from 11 bats species representing eight of the 17 chiropteran families. In suborder Yinpterochiropetra, we included two Old World fruit bats from family Pteropodidae (<italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic>, <italic>Rousettus leschenaultia</italic>); we also included four insectivorous bats from the Yinpterochiropetra suborder: <italic>Rhinolophus pusillus</italic> (Rhinolophidae), <italic>Hipposideros pratti</italic> (Hipposideridae) and <italic>Megaderma lyra</italic> and <italic>Megaderma spasma</italic> (Megadermatidae). From the suborder Yangochiroptera, we included one New World fruit bat <italic>Artibeus jamaicensis</italic> (Phyllostomidae) and four insectivorous bats from three families: <italic>Pteronotus parnelli</italic> (Mormoopidea), <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic>, <italic>Pipistrellus abramus</italic> (Vespertilionidae) and <italic>Taphozous melanopogon</italic> (Emballonuridae). <italic>Nrf2</italic> genes from five additional species were retrieved from GeneBank, and included <italic>Pteropus vampyrus</italic> and <italic>Pteropus alecto</italic> (Pteropodidae), <italic>Myotis brandtii</italic>, <italic>Myotis lucifugus</italic> and <italic>Myotis davidii</italic> (Vespertilionidae). All new sequences were deposited into GeneBank with accession numbers KT345715-KT345725.</p><p><italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences from five other mammal species were obtained from the Ensembl Database: <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (ENSG00000116044), <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> (ENSPTRG00000012677), <italic>Canis familiaris</italic> (ENSCAFG00000013506), <italic>Bos taurus</italic> (ENSBTAG00000019255), and <italic>Ictidomys tridecemlineatus</italic> (ENSSTOG00000000313). Details on all bats species and their corresponding <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene accession numbers are listed in <xref rid="pone.0146274.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Phylogenetic Reconstruction</title><p><italic>Nrf2</italic> coding sequences from 16 bats and 5 other mammals were aligned using CLUSTAL W implemented in MEGA 6 with default setting [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. First, we examined whether there was any evidence for recombination within our dataset, as recombination would have adverse effects on the power and accuracy of phylogenetic reconstruction and molecular evolutionary analyses [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. We used GARD [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>](from the Hyphy/Datamonkey web server [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]) with &#x003b2;&#x02013;&#x00393; rate variation and three and four rate classes to detect evidence of recombination breakpoints and test their statistical significance. The program jModelTest 0.1 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] was used to evaluate the best nucleotide substitution model. A Bayesian phylogenetic tree was reconstructed based on the aligned nucleotide sequences using MrBayes 3.1.2 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] with the GTR+G nucleotide substitution model, as selected by jModelTest 0.1. For the Bayesian analysis, ten million generations was set for the Markov chain, with the first two million discarded as burn in. The standard deviations of the split frequencies were stable below 0.01 after two million generations of MCMC. The MCMC was run in default setting of MrBayes 3.1.2. Datasets supporting the results are available in the Dryad digital repository, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link> (DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.kh186">10.5061/dryad.kh186</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Reconstruction of Ancestral Characters and Molecular Evolutionary Analyses</title><p><italic>Nrf2</italic> coding sequence from 21 species used in this study were aligned by CLUSTAL W implemented in MEGA 6 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and checked for accuracy by eye. The alignment was then translated into amino acid sequences. In the process of sequence alignment, we identified seven amino acid changes that occurred in the Old World fruit bats. To trace the ancestral states for these lineage-specific amino acid changes, we assessed these substitutions using the maximum parsimony method with Mesquite 2.74 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], the parameters set as defaults. For ancestral state reconstruction and selection tests, we used the phylogenetic tree topology based on the accepted species relationships [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p><p>To test the selective pressure on <italic>Nrf2</italic> genes in bat lineages, we estimated the rates of nonsynonymous (dN) and synonymous substitutions (dS) using CODEML from the PAML 4 package [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>, we labeled four branches for testing: A, ancestral branch of Old World fruit bats; B, ancestral branch of insectivorous bats in suborders Yinpterochiroptera; C, ancestral branch of Yangochiroptera; and D, ancestral branch of New World fruit bats. We first performed the two-ratio model test, which assumes the focal lineage(s) have a different &#x003c9; value (d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub>) compared with other lineages. First, we tested the ancestral lineage leading to Old World fruit bats (branch A) and the branch leading to New World fruit bats (branch D). In addition, to compare the evolutionary pattern of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene between frugivorous bats and insectivorous bats, separate two-ratio model tests were conducted with the ancestral branches for insectivorous bats in suborders Yinpterochiroptera (branch B) and Yangochiroptera (branch C). The one-ratio model served as the null hypothesis for all comparisons, which assumes the &#x003c9; value is equal among all branches.</p><fig id="pone.0146274.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Unconstrained <italic>Nrf2</italic> Bayesian phylogenetic tree and species tree.</title><p>(A) Unconstrained Bayesian phylogenetic tree based on <italic>Nrf2</italic> coding sequences, under the GTR+G model. Values on the nodes are posterior probabilities. (B) Species tree of the 21 mammals used in this study based on their accepted relationships. Four branches tested by the two-ratio model tests and the branch-site model tests are marked as A, B, C, and D. The four species with orange labels are Old World fruit bats. The seven amino acid substitutions specific to Old World fruit bats are shown (A100D, N133D, D205F, D224G, T279I, T350R and N424S).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146274.g001"/></fig><p>To further test the selection pressure on the amino acid sites of <italic>Nrf2</italic> genes, we carried the branch-site model A combined with Bayes empirical Bayes (BEB) estimation [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The focal branches in these tests were the ancestors of Old World fruit bats (branch A), New World fruit bat (branch D), and insectivorous bats in the suborders Yinpterochiroptera (branch B) and Yangochiroptera (branch C). The remaining branches were set as background. Four site classes of codons are assumed (class 0, class 1, class 2a, and class 2b), class 0 and class 1 codons are assumed to evolve under purifying selection (0 &#x0003c; &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> &#x0003c; 1) and neutral selection (&#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1), respectively. Class 2a and class 2b evolve under purifying selection and neutral selection on the background, respectively, while codons in these classes are combined together, as class 2, and assumed to evolve under positive selection (&#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; 1) on the foreground lineage. We applied test1 and test2 of branch-site model A to these four branches (A, B, C, and D), in which branch-site model A as the alternative hypothesis. In test1, the null hypothesis is the M1a model (Nearly neutral), which allowed two site classes (0 &#x0003c; &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> &#x0003c; 1 and &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1). However, in test2, the modified branch-site model A with &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> fixed as 1 was the null hypothesis. To investigate the distribution of selection pressure on sites along the Nrf2 protein sequence, we performed test2 of branch-site model A to calculate the &#x003c9; value of each amino acid in the ancestral branches leading to Old World fruit bats (branch A), insectivorous bats of suborders Yinpterochiroptera (branch B) and Yangochiroptera (branch C), and the only species of New World fruit bat (<italic>Artibeus lituratus</italic>) (branch D). The statistic 2<italic>&#x00394;&#x02113;</italic> (twice the log likelihood difference between the null and alternative hypothesis models) was compared through likelihood ratio tests (LRTs) with the Chi-square test in PAML. Finally, to gain more information on the seven amino acid substitutions in Old World fruit bats, we used different computational methods to predict the biological impact of these mutations on protein function. Protein Variation Effect Analyzer (PROVEAN) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and Sorting Intolerant From Tolerant (SIFT) program [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] were used to determine whether a given substitution is deleterious to protein function based on comparison with homologous amino acid sequences. The threshold was set as -1.5 in PROVEAN and 0.05 in the SIFT program.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Western Blot Validation</title><p>Expression levels of Nrf2 protein and the downstream enzyme catalase (CAT) were investigated, and compared, between frugivorous and insectivorous bats. Proteins from brain, heart, and liver were extracted from four representative bat species: <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic> (yangochiropteran insectivorous bats), <italic>Rhinolophus ferrumequinum</italic> (yinpterochiropteran insectivorous bats) and <italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic>, and <italic>Rousettus leschenaultia</italic> (frugivorous bats from Old World fruit bats). Three individuals were examined for each species. Proteins from rat tissues were used as a positive loading control. Brain, heart, and liver tissues were homogenized using Precellys 24 grinder (Bertin technologies, France) with lysis buffer (10% Glycerol, 2% SDS, 1.25% 2-beta-mercaptoethanol, 25 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 6.8) and then heated at 100&#x000b0;C for 10min after a quick spin. The resulting homogenates were centrifuged at 12000 xg at 4&#x000b0;C for 10 min and supernatants were collected. The protein content of each sample was determined utilizing the Quick Start Bradford protein assay kit (Bio-Rad, USA). Proteins in each sample (40 &#x003bc;g/lane) were separated by 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred to 0.2 &#x003bc;m PVDF membranes (Roche, Switzerland). The PVDF membranes were blocked in blocking solution (5% skim milk and 1% BSA) at 4&#x000b0;C for 12 hours and then reacted with primary antibodies including anti-CAT (1:500) and anti-Nrf2 (1:500). Anti-CAT (21260-1-AP) and anti-Nrf2 (sc-722) were purchased from Proteintech Group, Inc. and Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., respectively. Antibodies were selected based on the ability to combine with the conserved epitopes of proteins in bats and rats. After washing with TBST, PVDF membranes were incubated with secondary antibody and then visualized using Immobilon<sup>TM</sup> Western Chemiluminescence HRP substrate kit (Millipore, USA). Images were captured with the ImageQuant<sup>TM</sup> LAS 4000 (GE healthcare Life Science, USA) and bands were quantified with ImageQuant<sup>TM</sup> TL software (version 7.0). Reversible ponceau staining of the membranes were conducted to examine the relative amount of proteins in each lane [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The intensity of each band was normalized to the corresponding ponceau stained protein band. Results are shown as mean &#x000b1; SD and the statistical significance of the difference in CAT and Nrf2 levels among the different species was determined by one-way ANOVA with <italic>post hoc</italic> Holm-Sidak tests. <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered statistic significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec010"><title>Results</title><p>Our final <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequence dataset contained 21 taxa, including four Old World fruit bats (family Pteropodidae), one New World fruit bat (family Phyllostomidae), eleven insectivorous bats and five other mammals. The alignment of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences spanned 1710 nucleotides (570 amino acids), representing 94.2% of the complete coding region. No insertions, deletions or stop codons, and no evidence for recombination breakpoints were detected in our dataset.</p><p>Bayesian phylogenetic reconstruction of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> nucleotide sequences revealed a tree where the main groupings were in agreement with the accepted mammalian species tree (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). The four Old Word fruit bats (<italic>P</italic>. <italic>vampyrus</italic>, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>alecto</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic>, and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultii</italic>) grouped with species of the family Rhinolophidae (<italic>R</italic>. <italic>pusillus</italic>), Hipposideridae (<italic>H</italic>. <italic>pratti</italic>) and Megadermatidae (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>lyra</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>spasma</italic>) to comprise suborder Yinpterochiroptera [Bayesian posterior probability (BPP) = 0.48]. The remaining bat species grouped together to comprise the suborder Yangochiroptera (BPP = 1.00).</p><p>From the Nrf2 protein sequence alignment, we identified seven amino acid substitutions (100D, 133D, 205F, 224G, 279I, 350R and 424S) shared by all Old World fruit bat species, while all other species, including insectivorous bats and outgroups, shared a different amino acid residue at these locations (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). No similar set of amino acid changes was observed in the New World fruit bat. To trace the evolutionary history of these sites, we used Mesquite 2.74 to reconstruct the ancestral amino acid sequences. The results of the ancestral state reconstruction showed that seven specific amino acid replacements (A100D, N133D, D205F, D224G, T279I, T350R and N424S) occurred on the ancestral branch leading to Old World fruit bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>), and these seven amino acid substitutions were specific to this lineage.</p><p>To investigate changes in the selection pressure acting on the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene in frugivorous and insectivorous bats, several two-ratio model tests were carried out on the four branches labeled A, B, C, and D in <xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>, which represent the ancestral branches of Old World fruit bats, insectivorous bats in suborders Yinpterochiroptera, ancestral branch of Yangochiroptera and New World fruit bat, respectively. The results of the two-ratio tests are shown in <xref rid="pone.0146274.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. However, a comparison of alternative hypotheses with the null hypothesis indicates that the two-ratio models for branches A, B, C, and D do not fit the data better than the one-ratio model.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0146274.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Results of the branch model tests of selection pressure on <italic>Nrf2</italic> in bats.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146274.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0146274.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">np<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02113;</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;<sub>O</sub><xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;<sub>#</sub><xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model Compared</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2&#x00394;&#x02113;</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.</bold> One ratio: &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>A</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>B</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>C</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7676.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24229</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.</bold> Two ratio: &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>B</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>C</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub>, &#x003c9;<sub>A</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7675.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2376</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3792</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 vs.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.</bold> Two ratio: &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>A</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>C</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub>, &#x003c9;<sub>B</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7676.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2427</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1951</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 vs.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.</bold> Two ratio: &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>A</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>B</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub>, &#x003c9;<sub>C</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7675.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2362</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3911</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 vs.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.</bold> Two ratio: &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>A</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>B</sub> = &#x003c9;<sub>C</sub>, &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7674.86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2498</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 vs.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup><bold>a</bold></sup>See <xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> for branch labels.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup><bold>b</bold></sup>np, number of parameters.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup><bold>c</bold></sup>&#x003c9;<sub>#</sub> (&#x003c9;<sub>A,</sub> &#x003c9;<sub>B,</sub> &#x003c9;<sub>C,</sub> &#x003c9;<sub>D</sub>) and &#x003c9;<sub>O</sub>, are the d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> values for branches A, B, C, D and other branches, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To further investigate the distribution of selection pressures on sites along the <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequence, we performed test2 of branch-site model A to calculate the &#x003c9; values for each amino acid on the ancestral branches leading to the Old World fruit bats (branch A), the insectivorous bats of suborder Yinpterochiroptera (branch B), bats of suborder Yangochiroptera (branch C) and the only species of New World fruit bat in our study (<italic>Artibeus lituratus</italic>) (branch D). Results show that the &#x003c9; values for amino acid sites on the ancestral branch for Old World fruit bats are higher than that for the other branches (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Specifically, the selection pressure for the seven amino acid replacement sites (A100D, N133D, D205F, D224G, T279I, T350R and N424S) were significantly elevated on the ancestral branch leading to Old World fruit bats (branch A) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Moreover, as shown in <xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, branch-site model A for the ancestral branch of Old World fruit bats did not fit the data better than the branch-site null model which fixed &#x003c9;<sub>2</sub> as 1 (2<italic>&#x00394;&#x02113;</italic> = 1.88, df = 1, <italic>P</italic> = 0.17; test2), however, branch-site model A for the ancestral branch of Old World fruit bats did fit the data better than M1a model (2<italic>&#x00394;&#x02113;</italic> = 7.72, df = 2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.021; test1) (details for test1 and test2 of the branch-site model A can be found in the Materials and Methods Section). Thus, we are unable to reject the possibility of relaxed selection since test1 of branch-site model A cannot distinguish relaxed constraints from positive selection [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. No evidence for positively selected sites was detected on the branch leading to New World fruit bats (branch D), as the null model cannot be rejected by either test1 or test2 (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Similar conclusions were also found for the ancestral branches leading to the insectivorous bats of suborder Yinpterochiroptera (branch B) and suborder Yangochiroptera (branch C) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0146274.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Omega (d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub>) values of sites along the Nrf2 protein sequence on selected branches.</title><p>(A) Ancestral branch of Yinpterochiroptera insectivorous bats, (B) ancestral branch of Yangochiroptera, (C) ancestral branch of Old World fruit bats (OWFBs), and (D) branch of New World fruit bat (NWFB). The red arrows indicate the positions of the seven amino acid replacements in OWFBs with elevated &#x003c9; values.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146274.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0146274.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Results of the branch-site model A tests for the detection of positively selected sites on bats lineages.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146274.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0146274.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branch-site model<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">np<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRT<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02113;</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site with elevated omega values<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>M1a (nearly Neutral)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.063, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alternative hypothesis for branch A</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.756, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.224, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.016, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.005</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7498.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100D, 133D, <underline>205F</underline>, 224G, 279I, 350R, 424S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.060, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.060, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.060, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 6.962, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 6.962</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Null hypothesis for branch A</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.684, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.203, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.087, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.026</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7499.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.059, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.059, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.059, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00,&#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alternative hypothesis for branch B</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Null hypothesis for branch B</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alternative hypothesis for branch C</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Null hypothesis for branch C</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alternative hypothesis for branch D</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Null hypothesis for branch D</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.771, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic><sub>2a</sub> = 0.000, <italic>P</italic><sub>2b</sub> = 0.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 7502.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not allowed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foreground: &#x003c9;<sub>0</sub> = 0.634, &#x003c9;<sub>1</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2a</sub> = 1.00, &#x003c9;<sub>2b</sub> = 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p><sup>a</sup>See <xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> for branch labels.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>b</sup>np, number of parameters.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p><sup>c</sup>LRT, likelihood ratio test.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn004"><p><sup>d</sup>location of sites with elevated omega values detected by branch-site model A test refer to <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> sequence.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn005"><p>The sites with BEB posterior probability&#x0003e;0.05 were highlighted by underline.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To test the potential influence of the seven amino acid substitutions on the function of Nrf2 protein in Old World fruit bats, we mapped these sites to the predicted secondary structure of the Nrf2 protein established in previous studies (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Nrf2 belongs to the CNC family of transcription factors and contains seven functional Neh domains, namely, Neh1 to Neh7 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Four of the seven amino acid replacements that occurred in Old World fruit bats locate to Neh domain (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The N133D replacement occurs within the Neh4 domain, D224G and T279I are located in the Neh7 domain and T350R is located in Neh6 domain (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The remaining three replacements (A100D, D205F, and N424S) are located in sequences between Neh domains in Nrf2 that are not associated with specific functions. To further investigate whether the seven amino acid substitutions potentially affect protein function, we predicted the functional consequences of the substitutions using PROVEAN software and the SIFT program. PROVEAN predicts that three of the seven replacements (D205F, T279I and T350R) were deleterious to Nrf2 protein function (score threshold is -1.3), with the remaining four changes predicted as neutral (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). SIFT suggested that two of the seven replacements (D205F and T350R) were predicted to affect protein function (threshold is 0.05) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These results suggest that replacements D205F and T350R are most likely damaging, as they were predicted to be deleterious by both programs.</p><fig id="pone.0146274.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Distribution of the seven OWFBs-specific amino acid replacements in the secondary structure of Nrf2 protein.</title><p>The locations of the seven amino acid replacements in OWFBs are labeled in red line. The seven Neh domains are shown, Neh1 to Neh7. Neh1 domain (residue 435&#x02013;561) is the CNC-bZIP domain. Neh2 domain (residue 27&#x02013;82) is a redox-sensitive regulatory domain that binds with the repressor Keap1, and also contains one of the three nuclear localization sequences (NLS: residue 42&#x02013;53, 494&#x02013;511 and 587&#x02013;593). Neh3 (residue 562&#x02013;605), Neh4 (residue 112&#x02013;134) and Neh5 (residue 183&#x02013;201) domains are involved in Nrf2 transactivation activity. Neh6 domain (residue 338&#x02013;388) is involved in Nrf2 stability. Neh7 domain (residue 209&#x02013;316) is involved in interactions with RXR&#x003b1; and functions as a transcriptional repressor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146274.g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0146274.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>PROVEAN and SIFT predictions of the functional consequences of the Nrf2 amino acid replacements in Old World fruit bats.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146274.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0146274.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="justify" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Variant in Nrf2 protein</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Domain</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">PROVEAN predictions</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">SIFT predictions</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PROVEAN Score</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted effects on Nrf2 protein (cutoff = -1.3)<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIFT Score</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted effects on Nrf2 protein (cutoff = 0.05)<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A100D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N133D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neh4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.936</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D205F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.378</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deleterious</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deleterious</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D224G</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neh7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T279I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neh7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.797</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deleterious</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T350R</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neh6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.826</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deleterious</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deleterious</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N424S</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> Positions with PROVEAN Score less than -1.3 are predicted to be deleterious, while those greater than -1.3 are neutral.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>b</sup> Positions with SIFT Score less than 0.05 are predicted to be deleterious, while those greater than 0.05 are neutral.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To further investigate, and compare, the functional effects of the amino acid replacements between Old World fruit bats and insectivorous bats, we first examined the amount of Nrf2 protein in two representative species of Old World fruit bats (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic>, <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultia</italic>) and two insectivorous bats (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>ricketti</italic> from suborder Yangochiroptera; <italic>R</italic>. <italic>ferrumequinum</italic> from Yinpterochiroptera) and the omnivorous rat as the positive loading control. Brain, heart and liver tissue from each species were examined since these three organs are the most vulnerable tissues to oxidative stress [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In the brain, level of Nrf2 protein in <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultia</italic> was significant higher than in the two insectivorous bats (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). However, no significant difference was found among <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>ricketti</italic> and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>ferrumequinum</italic>. In the heart, the amount of Nrf2 protein in the two Old World fruit bats was significantly higher compared to the two insectivorous bats (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). The level of Nrf2 in the heart of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic> was higher than in <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultia</italic>, with no significant difference found between <italic>M</italic>. <italic>ricketti</italic> and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>ferrumequinum</italic>. The same situation was observed in the liver, with significantly higher levels of Nrf2 protein in the two Old World fruit bats compared with the two insectivorous bats (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). Moreover, higher levels of Nrf2 protein were found in the livers of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic> and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>ferrumequinum</italic> in comparison with <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultia</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>ricketti</italic>, respectively (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 in two comparisons, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0146274.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146274.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>The levels of Nrf2 protein and catalase (CAT) in the brain, heart and liver of four bats species.</title><p>Four bats species were used in this study and are two insectivorous bats (<italic>M</italic>.<italic>ric</italic>: <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic>; <italic>R</italic>.<italic>fer</italic>: <italic>Rhinolophus ferrumequinum</italic>) and two Old World fruit bats (<italic>R</italic>.<italic>les</italic>: <italic>Rousettus leschenaultia</italic>; <italic>C</italic>.<italic>sph</italic>: <italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic>). Protein level of (A) Nrf2 protein and (B) catalase in representative bat species and rats (positive control) were determined by Western blotting. Relative levels are presented as mean &#x000b1; SD. Arrows indicate the predicted molecular weights (kDa) of the proteins. Statistical significance of the differences among species were determined by one-way ANOVA with <italic>post hoc</italic> Holm-Sidak tests: *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146274.g004"/></fig><p>To determine whether the elevated levels of Nrf2 protein in the three tissues of the Old World fruit bats resulted in enhanced transcriptional function, we conducted Western blot assays to examine the expression of a down-stream enzyme CAT, which is regulated by Nrf2 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. However, in contrast to expectations based on the elevated levels of Nrf2, our results showed that the amount of CAT in the brain, heart and liver of the two Old World fruit bats were remarkably lower than in the two insectivorous bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). In the three tissues from the insectivorous bats, CAT levels were significantly higher in <italic>M</italic>. <italic>ricketti</italic> compared to <italic>R</italic>. <italic>ferrumequinum</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). The level of Nrf2 in the liver of <italic>R</italic>. <italic>leschenaultia</italic> was significantly higher than in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sphinx</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, one way ANOVA, Holm-Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> test) (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). These results suggest that despite higher levels of Nrf2 protein in Old World fruit bats, the downstream antioxidant enzyme CAT was significantly lower in the three tissues than in insectivorous bats suggesting that the Old World fruit bat Nrf2 sequence have lower transcriptional activity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we examined the evolutionary history of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene, a central transcriptional regulator of antioxidant enzymes in mammals. Antioxidant enzymes are an important part of the antioxidant defense system, together with low molecular weight antioxidants (LMWAs) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. As the daily diet of frugivorous bats contains fruits that are high in LWMAs such as vitamins C and E [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], the abundance of LMWAs might lead to a reduced need for enzymatic antioxidants for free radical scavenging compared with insectivorous bats. <italic>Nrf2</italic>, as the gene encoding a transcriptional regulator of antioxidant enzyme genes, thus might have experienced relaxed constraint in the frugivorous bats. Comparing <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences among frugivorous and insectivorous bats provides the first data on the molecular adaptation of the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene in frugivorous bats. Phylogenetic reconstruction analyses showed that the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene tree is consistent with the accepted species tree (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) and the d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> ratio calculated by PAML on each branch was quite low (data not shown), results indicating that the <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences are evolving conservatively under purifying selection.</p><p>Interestingly, alignment of the 21 Nrf2 protein sequences in our dataset identified seven amino acid replacements that were specifically found exclusively in the four Old World fruit bat species (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). Ancestral state reconstruction using Mesquite 2.74 showed that all seven amino acid changes occurred precisely on the ancestral branch leading to Old World fruit bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Although the results of test1 in branch-site model A for Old World fruit bats revealed that the codons for the seven amino acid replacements had elevated &#x003c9; value, we cannot distinguish whether these elevated &#x003c9; values are the result of relaxed selection or positive selection acting on <italic>Nrf2</italic> since test1 was unable to distinguish relaxed constraints from positive selection [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In addition, although the &#x003c9; values for amino acid sites on the ancestral branch for Old World fruit bats are higher than for other branches, the &#x003c9; value for the ancestral branch leading to Old World fruit bats was 0.387 (data not shown), which is far below the standard for positive selection (&#x003c9; &#x0003e;&#x0003e; 1). The results of an explicit test for positive selection (test2) was negative, which indicates that there is no strict evidence for positive selection on the <italic>Nrf2</italic> sequences on the ancestral branch for Old World fruit bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Based on the fact that the frugivorous bats get an abundance of LWMAs from their daily diets, their demands for enzymatic antioxidants, which are regulated by <italic>Nrf2</italic>, should be reduced. We hypothesize that the seven amino acid replacements observed in the Old World fruit bat Nrf2 sequences have a functional consequence. To confirm this hypothesis, we performed a biochemical experiment to indirectly investigate the functional activity of Nrf2 by examining the level of the enzyme catalase (CAT), which is a downstream transcriptionally regulated target of Nrf2 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p><p>We examined the amount of CAT in three tissues, brain, heart and liver, as these tissues are most vulnerable to oxidative stress [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Our results showed that CAT level was significantly lower in the brain, heart and liver of the two Old World fruit bats compared to the two insectivorous bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). It might be assumed that the lower levels of CAT are a consequence of reduced Nrf2 expression in Old World fruit bats, however, this possibility can be ruled out as our biochemical results show that Nrf2 protein levels are significantly higher in the heart and liver of the two Old World fruit bats compared with the two insectivorous bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). CAT is a major enzymatic antioxidant in aerobic organisms that decomposes hydrogen peroxide to prevent the generation of hydroxyl radical [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], the highly mobile and chemically most reactive species of activated oxygen [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Several studies have suggested that <italic>Nrf2</italic> knockout mice are extremely susceptible to oxidative damage and have downregulated expression of CAT [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>Cat</italic> deficient mice were vulnerable to impairment of brain mitochondria [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Thus, the expression level of CAT should represent some of the functions of the transcription factor Nrf2. Combining the results of our molecular evolutionary analysis and biochemical assays, the changes in selection pressure observed at these seven amino acid sites likely are the main cause of the functional change in Nrf2 seen in Old Word fruit bats.</p><p>Upregulated Nrf2 expression in these three tissues of Old World fruit bats could also be explained as a compensatory adaptation of the organisms. If the seven amino acid replacements seen in the Old World fruit bat sequences affect Nrf2 protein function, then the increased levels of Nrf2 protein might represent an attempt to compensate for their normal functions [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. However, although the level of Nrf2 in Old World fruit bats is upregulated, the level of the downstream enzyme CAT is still markedly lower than in insectivorous bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>), suggests that upregulation did not completely attenuate the Nrf2 function in Old World fruit bats.</p><p>Although the results of the two-ratio test on the ancestral branch leading to Old World fruit bats did not fit the data better than the one-ratio test, we are unable to conclude that <italic>Nrf2</italic> has undergone purifying selection, as the &#x003c9; value calculated by the branch model is the average of nonsynonymous and synonymous rates over all sites in the protein sequence and over all evolutionary history [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In order to maintain the function of a protein, most amino acid sites are highly conserved, which results in the signal of elevated &#x003c9; values at specific sites being overwhelmed by the ubiquitous purifying selection occurring at the vast majority of other sites [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Alignment of the protein sequences in our dataset indicates that most amino acid sites in the Nrf2 protein are conserved throughout mammals, thus, the two-ratio test for the ancestral branch of Old World fruit bats was unable to reject the possibility of one-ratio test even when the seven amino acid replacements, with elevated &#x003c9; values, occurred in Old World fruit bats (Tables <xref rid="pone.0146274.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p>To further investigate the potential impact of the seven amino acid substitutions on the function of Nrf2 protein in Old World fruit bats, we mapped these substitutions to the secondary structure of the Nrf2 protein (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Nrf2 belongs to the CNC family of transcription factors and contains seven functional Neh domains [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Three of the seven amino acid substitutions (D205F, T279I and T350R) in Old World fruit bats are predicted deleterious to Nrf2 function by PROVEAN, with two of these substitutions (D205F and T350R) predicted to be deleterious by the SIFT program (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The D205F replacement is not located in any of the seven characterized Neh domain, but this substitution is a radical change with the charged and polar amino acid aspartic acid (D) that prefers to be exposed to aqueous environment replaced by phenylalanine (F), which prefers to bury in protein hydrophobic core [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. This D205F replacement, thus might lead to a change in the structure of Nrf2 that impacts function or cellular localization. The second substitution that was predicted to be deleterious by both methods, T350G, is located in the redox-insensitive Neh6 domain, a domain that is essential for the stability of Nrf2 [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], thus this substitution might affect this function. The T279I replacement, which was predicted to be damaging by PROVEAN but not SIFT, is located in the Neh7 domain of Nrf2, a domain that allows Nrf2 to interact with RXR&#x003b1; and to function as a repressor of ARE-driven gene expression [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], thus could have a functional impact. In support of this, the T279I replacement in Nrf2 is adjacent to residue 278, a residue with a missense mutation in COSMIC database of cancer-associated mutations [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], suggesting that changes near this site have functional consequences. Together, the results of our biochemical assessment of Nrf2 and CAT protein levels, and the predicted deleterious consequences of some replacements in the Nrf2 sequences of Old World fruit bats, suggests that Old World fruit bats produce more Nrf2 protein than insectivorous bats, but that high level of Nrf2 lead to lower amounts of CAT protein (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). The data suggest that the amino acids replacements, which occurred during the evolution of <italic>Nrf2</italic>, might have yielded an Nrf2 protein that has reduced transcriptional activity that cannot be fully compensated by upregulation. Additional detailed studies are needed in Old World fruit bats to provide direct evidence and understand the consequences of these substitutions on Nrf2 function and structure, which may yield results that are informative for understanding human diseases.</p><p>Although New World fruit bats and Old World fruit bats have similar food habits, we did not find evidence of similar evolutionary forces acting on the Nrf2 gene in New World fruit bats (<xref rid="pone.0146274.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). None of the seven amino acid replacements observed in the Old World fruit bats were detected in the New World fruit bat (<xref rid="pone.0146274.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). This evolutionary discrepancy between Old World fruit bats and New World fruit bats can be explained in three ways. First, the Old World fruit bats evolved their frugivorous diets earlier than New World fruit bats (at least 28 mya compared with nearly 20 mya) [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], therefore, New World fruit bats may still retain normal Nrf2 protein function due to their shorter period of time to accumulate sequence changes. Second, it is possible that the retained Nrf2 function in New World fruit bats is due to their divergence from their insectivorous ancestor in the family Phyllostomidae [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Third, sequence changes may have occurred in the regulatory region of the Nrf2 gene in New World fruit bats instead of the coding regions. It is noteworthy that several other recent molecular evolution studies on diet-related genes in bats have also found similar evolutionary discrepancies between Old and New World fruit bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. For example, PCK1, which plays an important role in glucose homeostasis during fasting, also has specific amino acid changes in the Old World fruit bats but not in New World fruit bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The <italic>tat</italic> gene, which encodes tyrosine aminotransferase (TAT) that is involved in amino acid metabolism, has undergone relaxed evolution in Old World fruit bats but not in New World fruit bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Since our results were obtained from a single New World fruit bat of the family Phyllostomidae, more sampling of New World fruit bats is needed to further confirm this finding.</p><p>In addition to its critical role in regulating antioxidant enzymes, Nrf2 is also involved in many other cytoprotective pathways that are associated with the aging process [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Our results suggest that Nrf2 function is attenuated in Old World fruit bats but maintained in insectivorous bats. Some studies have found that frugivorous bats have shorter lifespans than insectivorous bats [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146274.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Since there is a close association between oxidative stress and longevity [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], it is possible that changes in chiropteran longevity are associated with changes in the selective constraint on <italic>Nrf2</italic>. However, further studies are needed to reveal correlations between <italic>Nrf2</italic> function and chiropteran longevity.</p><p>In conclusion, our molecular evolutionary study combined with biochemical characterization shows that <italic>Nrf2</italic> might have experienced relaxed constraint in Old World fruit bats, however, we cannot rule out the possibility of positive selection. The amino acid replacements that occurred during the evolution of <italic>Nrf2</italic> might have functional effects on the Nrf2 protein in Old World fruit bats, potentially due to their LMWAs-rich diets. Our study provides evidence of how diet habit influences metabolic evolution in mammals [<xref rid="pone.0146274.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and might also provide novel insight and more information into understanding chiropteran longevity. Additional in-depth studies are needed to investigate the mechanisms of how these amino acid replacements influence Nrf2 protein function in Old World fruit bats, and we speculate that additional research will discover more genes associated with antioxidant regulation in frugivorous bats that have experienced changes in selection pressure due to their LMWAs-rich diets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec012"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146274.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Species tree of the 21 mammals with Old World fruit bats specific amino acid substitutions identified by ancestral sequence reconstruction using the maximum parsimony method.</title><p>(A) A100D, (B) N133D, (C) D205F, (D) D224G, (E) T279I, (F) T350R and (G) N424S. Branch lengths are not shown.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146274.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146274.s002"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title><italic>Nrf2</italic> genes with taxa information.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146274.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146274.s003"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Primers used for the amplification of <italic>Nrf2</italic> by PCR.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146274.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Haijian Sun for technical advice on sequence preparation, and Dr. Libiao Zhang, in fieldwork. We also thank Dr. Bin Shen for the kind advice in processing the final draft.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0146274.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mitochondrial free radical generation, oxidative stress, and aging</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moghaddas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoppel</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lesnefsky</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Production of reactive oxygen species by mitochondria central role of complex III</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>278</volume>(<issue>38</issue>):<fpage>36027</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12840017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hydroperoxide metabolism in mammalian organs</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 37532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nyska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Invited review: Oxidation of biological systems: oxidative stress phenomena, antioxidants, redox reactions, and methods for their quantification</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Pathol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12512863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12512863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaspar</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niture</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nrf2: INrf2 (Keap1) signaling in oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.07.035</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19666107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Motohashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nrf2&#x02013;Keap1 defines a physiologically important stress response mechanism</article-title>. <source>Trends Mol Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15519281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15519281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomso</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chorley</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kleeberger</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Identification of polymorphic antioxidant response elements in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17409198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17409198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prawan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Increased susceptibility of Nrf2 knockout mice to colitis-associated colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Prev Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nrf2 is essential for protection against acute pulmonary injury in mice</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>12731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10535991?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nrf2 signaling in coordinated activation of antioxidant gene expression</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15110384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Grune</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biesalski</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Low molecular weight antioxidants</chapter-title>
<source>Reactions, Processes</source>: <collab>Springer</collab>; <year>2005</year> p. <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Mammal species of the world: a taxonomic and geographic reference</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>JHU Press</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brunet-Rossinni</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reduced free-radical production and extreme longevity in the little brown bat (<italic>Myotis lucifugus</italic>) versus two non-flying mammals</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14706233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14706233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Free radical theory of aging: an update</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1067</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16803965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brunet-Rossinni</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Austad</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ageing studies on bats: a review</article-title>. <source>Biogerontology</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15314271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilhelm Filho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Althoff</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dafr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antioxidant defenses, longevity and ecophysiology of South American bats</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol C Toxicol Pharmacol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17257902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Neuweiler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The biology of bats</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Bats: a natural history</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ Press</publisher-name>; <year>1984</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Bat ecology</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altube</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Cordero</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sources of assimilated protein in five species of New World frugivorous bats</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28466224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>MARSHALL</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Old World phytophagous bats (Megachiroptera) and their food plants: a survey</article-title>. <source>Zool J Linn Soc</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fruit intake and energy budgets of frugivorous bats</article-title>. <source>Physiol Zool</source>
<year>1984</year>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harasym</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oledzki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of fruit and vegetable antioxidants on total antioxidant capacity of blood plasma</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2013.08.019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24698344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenness</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ascorbic acid content of neotropical plant parts available to wild monkeys and bats</article-title>. <source>Experientia</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3104078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3104078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Czirj&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>G&#x000c1;</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Frugivory is associated with low measures of plasma oxidative stress and high antioxidant concentration in free-ranging bats</article-title>. <source>Naturwissenschaften</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00114-014-1155-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24515336?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24515336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avila-Flores</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prestin shows divergent evolution between constant frequency echolocating bats</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00239-011-9460-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21947331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21947331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>4876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9396791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of recombination on the accuracy of phylogeny estimation</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11847565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>SLK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gravenor</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woelk</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>. <article-title>GARD: a genetic algorithm for recombination detection</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>3096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17110367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>SLK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muse</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>HyPhy: hypothesis testing using phylogenies. Statistical methods in molecular evolution</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year> p. <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msn083</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18397919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12912839?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maddison W, Maddison D. Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.75. 2011. URL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mesquiteproject.org">http://mesquiteproject.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A molecular phylogeny for bats illuminates biogeography and the fossil record</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>307</volume>(<issue>5709</issue>):<fpage>580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15681385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsagkogeorga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stupka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogenomic analyses elucidate the evolutionary relationships of bats</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2013.09.014</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24184098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogenomic analysis resolves the interordinal relationships and rapid diversification of the Laurasiatherian mammals</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syr089</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21900649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17483113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bayes empirical Bayes inference of amino acid sites under positive selection</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15689528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Choi Y, Sims GE, Murphy S, Miller JR, Chan AP. Predicting the functional effect of amino acid substitutions and indels. 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>SIFT: Predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3812</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12824425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Romero-Calvo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Moya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zarzuelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Augustin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Reversible Ponceau staining as a loading control alternative to actin in Western blots</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>401</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2010.02.036</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20206115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20206115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of an improved branch-site likelihood method for detecting positive selection at the molecular level</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16107592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16107592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boutten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goven</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Artaud-Macari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boczkowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>NRF2 targeting: a promising therapeutic strategy in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>Trends Mol Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmed.2011.02.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21459041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21459041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>RXR&#x003b1; inhibits the NRF2-ARE signaling pathway through a direct interaction with the Neh7 domain of NRF2</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-3386</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23612120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23612120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garbarino</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buffenstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of oxidative stress resistance in the brain: Lessons learned from hypoxia tolerant extremophilic vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agnoletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bachetti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cargnoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oxidative stress during myocardial ischaemia and heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>B2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9519346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9519346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cederbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <article-title>editors. Oxidative stress and alcoholic liver disease</article-title>. <source>Semin Liver Dis</source>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reisman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klaassen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increased Nrf2 activation in livers from Keap1-knockdown mice increases expression of cytoprotective genes that detoxify electrophiles more than those that detoxify reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>:<fpage>kfn267</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mice lacking catalase develop normally but show differential sensitivity to oxidant tissue injury</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biochem</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>32804</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arg&#x000fc;elles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lipid peroxidation: production, metabolism, and signaling mechanisms of malondialdehyde and 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal</article-title>. <source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source>. <year>2014</year>;2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dreger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stangl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meiners</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Nrf2-dependent upregulation of antioxidative enzymes: a novel pathway for proteasome inhibitor-mediated cardioprotection</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>. <year>2009</year>:<fpage>cvp107</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maisnier-Patin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptation to the deleterious effects of antimicrobial drug resistance mutations by compensatory evolution</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>155</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15207868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15207868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>In search of molecular Darwinism</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>385</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8990106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8990106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>The power of phylogenetic comparison in revealing protein function</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15728394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>A-MK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Codon-substitution models for heterogeneous selection pressure at amino acid sites</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>155</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10790415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10790415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Bioinformatics for geneticists</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Redox-regulated turnover of Nrf2 is determined by at least two separate protein domains, the redox-sensitive Neh2 degron and the redox-insensitive Neh6 degron</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biochem</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>31556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gunasekaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bindal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutselakis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>COSMIC: exploring the world's knowledge of somatic mutations in human cancer</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25355519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Datzmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Helversen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of nectarivory in phyllostomid bats (Phyllostomidae Gray, 1825, Chiroptera: Mammalia)</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple adaptive losses of alanine-glyoxylate aminotransferase mitochondrial targeting in fruit-eating bats</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss013</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22319153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptive evolution in the glucose transporter 4 gene Slc2a4 in Old World fruit bats (Family: Pteropodidae)</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e33197</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033197</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22493665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22493665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phosphoenolpyruvate Carboxykinase 1 Gene (<italic>Pck1</italic>) Displays Parallel Evolution between Old World and New World Fruit Bats</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relaxed evolution in the tyrosine aminotransferase gene Tat in old world fruit bats (Chiroptera: Pteropodidae)</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>) <year>2014</year>; <fpage>e97483</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097483</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24824435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24824435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buffenstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nrf2, a guardian of healthspan and gatekeeper of species longevity</article-title>. <source>Integr Comp Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/icq034</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21031035?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21031035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brunet-Rossinni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Methods for age estimation and the study of senescence in bats</article-title>. <source>Ecological and behavioral methods for the study of bats</source>. <year>2009</year>:<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>South</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Life history, ecology and longevity in bats</article-title>. <source>Aging cell</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12882342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146274.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Birdsey</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Danpure</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparative analysis of the evolutionary relationship between diet and enzyme targeting in bats, marsupials and other mammals</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>272</volume>(<issue>1565</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>