<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SC</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">CSHCBM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chemical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2041-6520</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2041-6539</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Royal Society of Chemistry</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8152809</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">d0sc01197e</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d0sc01197e</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Trends in trigonal prismatic Ln-[1]ferrocenophane complexes and discovery of a Ho<sup>3+</sup> single-molecule magnet<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref></article-title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available: CCDC <uri>1986607</uri> (<bold>1</bold>), <uri>1986530</uri> (<bold>2</bold>), <uri>1986548</uri> (<bold>2-py</bold>), <uri>1986581</uri> (<bold>2-THF*</bold>), <uri>1986886</uri> (<bold>3</bold>), <uri>1986808</uri> (<bold>4</bold>), <uri>1986810</uri> (<bold>5</bold>), <uri>1986941</uri> (<bold>5iso</bold>), <uri>1986815</uri> (<bold>6</bold>), <uri>1986828</uri> (<bold>6iso</bold>). For ESI and crystallographic data in CIF or other electronic format see DOI: <uri>10.1039/d0sc01197e</uri></p></fn></fn-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Latendresse</surname><given-names>Trevor P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6375-4537</contrib-id><name><surname>Vieru</surname><given-names>Veacheslav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affb"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affc"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>Apoorva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affd"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuvanesh</surname><given-names>Nattamai S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>Liviu F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affb"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1091-4677</contrib-id><name><surname>Nippe</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa"/></contrib><aff id="affa">
<institution>Department of Chemistry, Texas A&#x00026;M University</institution>
<addr-line>3255 TAMU</addr-line>
<city>College Station</city>
<state>Texas 77843</state>
<country>USA</country>
<email>nippe@chem.tamu.edu</email>
</aff><aff id="affb">
<institution>Theory of Nanomaterials Group, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</institution>
<addr-line>Celestijnenlaan 200F</addr-line>
<city>3001 Leuven</city>
<country>Belgium</country>
<email>Liviu.Chibotaru@chem.kuleuven.be</email>
</aff><aff id="affc">
<institution>Maastricht Science Programme, Faculty of Science and Engineering, Maastricht University</institution>
<city>Maastricht</city>
<country>Netherlands</country>
</aff><aff id="affd">
<institution>Department of Chemistry, Wayne State University</institution>
<addr-line>5101 Cass Ave</addr-line>
<city>Detroit</city>
<state>MI 48202</state>
<country>USA</country>
</aff></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2020-03-24"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2020-04-21"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>3936</fpage><lpage>3951</lpage><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2020-02-27"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2020-03-23"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>This journal is &#x000a9; The Royal Society of Chemistry</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Royal Society of Chemistry</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2020-03-24">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref></license><?release-delay 0|0?></permissions><abstract><p>Lanthanide metallocenophanes are an intriguing class of organometallic complexes that feature rare six-coordinate trigonal prismatic coordination environments of 4f elements with close intramolecular proximity to transition metal ions. Herein, we present a systematic study of the structural and magnetic properties of the ferrocenophanes, [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, of the late trivalent lanthanide ions (Ln = Gd (<bold>1</bold>), Ho (<bold>2</bold>), Er (<bold>3</bold>), Tm (<bold>4</bold>), Yb (<bold>5</bold>), Lu (<bold>6</bold>)). One major structural trend within this class of complexes is the increasing diferrocenyl (Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) average twist angle with decreasing ionic radius (<italic>r</italic><sub>ion</sub>) of the central Ln ion, resulting in the largest average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angles for the Lu<sup>3+</sup> compound <bold>6</bold>. Such high sensitivity of the twist angle to changes in <italic>r</italic><sub>ion</sub> is unique to the here presented ferrocenophane complexes and likely due to the large trigonal plane separation enforced by the ligand (&#x0003e;3.2 &#x000c5;). This geometry also allows the non-Kramers ion Ho<sup>3+</sup> to exhibit slow magnetic relaxation in the absence of applied dc fields, rendering compound <bold>2</bold> a rare example of a Ho-based single-molecule magnet (SMM) with barriers to magnetization reversal (<italic>U</italic>) of 110&#x02013;131 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In contrast, compounds featuring Ln ions with prolate electron density (<bold>3&#x02013;5</bold>) don't show slow magnetization dynamics under the same conditions. The observed trends in magnetic properties of <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold> are supported by state-of-the-art <italic>ab initio</italic> calculations. Finally, the magneto-structural relationship of the trigonal prismatic Ho-[1]ferrocenophane motif was further investigated by axial ligand (THF in <bold>2</bold>) exchange to yield [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF*)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<bold>2-THF*</bold>) and [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<bold>2-py</bold>) motifs. We find that larger average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angles (in <bold>2-THF*</bold> and <bold>2-py</bold> as compared to in <bold>2</bold>) result in faster magnetic relaxation times at a given temperature.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Lanthanide ferrocenophanes are an intriguing class of organometallic complexes that feature rare six-coordinate trigonal prismatic coordination environments of 4f elements with close intramolecular proximity to iron ions.<graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-ga.jpg" id="ga" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Science Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000001</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CHE-1753014</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Fonds Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003130</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Unassigned</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Welch Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000928</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>A-1880</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Science and Engineering Research Board</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001843</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Unassigned</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Indo-US Science and Technology Forum</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001429</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Unassigned</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pubstatus</meta-name><meta-value>Paginated Article</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Single-molecule magnets (SMMs) are discrete molecules having a bistable magnetic ground state and a sufficient energy barrier to magnetization reversal (<italic>U</italic>) which can lead to magnetic hysteresis of purely molecular origin.<sup><xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> SMMs represent the smallest magnetic units that can be predictively modified with synthetic chemistry. This renders SMMs highly attractive research targets and highlights their potential utility as memory components in future data processing and data storage devices.<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2,3</xref></sup> In recent years, SMM design has largely involved exploiting the magnetic anisotropy of a single metal ion with a finely tuned ligand-field environment. In contrast to the traditional &#x0201c;giant spin&#x0201d; approach in multinuclear metal complexes, designing SMMs with only a single paramagnetic ion offers the inherent advantage of simplified control of the molecular magnetic anisotropy thereby allowing the magnetic anisotropy of a single-ion to be maximized when it resides in an optimal ligand coordination environment. Although significant progress is being reported for transition metal based mononuclear SMMs,<sup><xref rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref></sup> the majority of mononuclear SMMs aim to exploit the intrinsically large single-ion magnetic anisotropy of lanthanide ions which is due to their unquenched orbital angular momentum and can lead to large magnetic moments, especially in the latter half of the lanthanide series.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7&#x02013;11</xref></sup> Indeed, lanthanide-based SMMs can be considered the best performing SMMs to-date, especially given the family of bis-cyclopentadienyl lanthanide based cations, which led most recently to molecules that exhibit magnetic hysteresis at temperatures as high as 80 K.<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12&#x02013;18</xref></sup></p><p>SMM performance is highly dependent on the geometry enforced by the ligands surrounding the central ion. The ligand coordination environment dictates the height of the energy barrier to magnetization reversal (<italic>U</italic>) as well as influences the rate of quantum tunneling of the magnetization (QTM). For lanthanide ions, the crystal field potential acts as a perturbation on the ground spin&#x02013;orbit coupled, <italic>J</italic>, term (within the <sup>2S+1</sup>L<sub>J</sub> coupling scheme) thereby determining the energy spacing between ground and excited <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> projections. In the optimal case of spin relaxation occurring by an &#x0201c;over-the-barrier&#x0201d; Orbach mechanism, the value of <italic>U</italic> will be proportional to the energy gap of the ground and higher excited <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> states.<sup><xref rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr">19,20</xref></sup> Molecular symmetry also has direct bearing on the probability of QTM between resonating <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> projections. In some ligand field geometries transverse anisotropy terms will be included in the crystal-field Hamiltonian, thereby resulting in rapid QTM.<sup><xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></p><p>With this in mind, understanding how various coordination geometries affect the magnetic anisotropy a Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion is crucial in the continued development of high-performance SMMs. Many of the early examples of Ln-based SMMs featured multi-dentate oxygen and/or nitrogen-based donor ligands which naturally resulted in SMMs with high coordination numbers.<sup><xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22&#x02013;24</xref></sup> Of the &#x0201c;classical&#x0201d; Ln-SMM geometries, those featuring axially elongated square antiprismatic (<italic>D</italic><sub>4d</sub>),<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11,25&#x02013;27</xref></sup> axially compressed square antiprismatic (<italic>D</italic><sub>4d</sub>),<sup><xref rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr">28,29</xref></sup> or compressed pentagonal bipyramidal (<italic>D</italic><sub>5h</sub>)<sup><xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8,10,30,31</xref></sup> geometries have been some of the most thoroughly investigated. More recently, unique and lower coordinate structural motifs for Ln<sup>3+</sup> compounds have been achieved by incorporating organic based ligand scaffolds in SMM design.<sup><xref rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr">32&#x02013;35</xref></sup> Modern organometallic lanthanide chemistry has led to structurally and magnetically important molecules such as the C<sub>8</sub> symmetric lanthanide bis-cyclooctatetraene, [Ln(COT)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>,<sup><xref rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr">32&#x02013;35</xref></sup> and the aforementioned pseudo and strictly linear lanthanide metallocenium, [Ln(Cp<sup>R</sup>)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+1/0</sup>, complexes.</p><p>Lanthanide-based SMMs featuring six-coordinate ligand field geometries have been relatively unexplored in terms of relating molecular geometry to the magnetic behavior of various Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions.<sup><xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9,36&#x02013;40</xref></sup> This is most likely due to the relatively low number of six-coordinate lanthanide complexes reported in the literature as compared to those having higher coordination numbers. Of the cubic and trigonal coordination environments for six-coordinate lanthanide compounds, a trigonal ligand field is expected to be more suitable for SMM behavior.<sup><xref rid="cit41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> For a Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion residing in an idealized octahedral (<italic>O</italic><sub>h</sub>) environment, slow magnetic relaxation is not expected, as the absence of the second-order uniaxial anisotropy parameter, <italic>B</italic><sup>0</sup><sub>2</sub>, from the crystal-field Hamiltonian should exclude the possibility of easy-axis magnetic anisotropy.<sup><xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr">37,42,43</xref></sup> In contrast, an ideal trigonal prismatic ligand field (<italic>D</italic><sub>3h</sub>) is predicted to stabilize a highly axial &#x000b1;<italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> ground state which could result in dynamic SMM behavior. Indeed, recent reports have shown that a trigonal prismatic geometry can support SMM behavior of Dy<sup>3+</sup> and Tb<sup>3+</sup> ions.<sup><xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36,37,39,40,44,45</xref></sup></p><p>Recently, our group utilized the organometallic chemistry of the 1,1'- diferrocenyl (Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) metallo-ligand to synthesize the first Ln-[1]ferrocenophane molecules, [DyFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and [TbFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, which feature a rare trigonal prismatic arrangement of the six C1 carbons of the three dianionic Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligands.<sup><xref rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr">44,45</xref></sup> [DyFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and [TbFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> both exhibit zero applied field SMM behavior, with magnetic anisotropy energy barriers of <italic>U</italic> = 110 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and <italic>U</italic> = 274 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. It is important to note that, to the best of our knowledge, [TbFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> features the largest zero-field magnetization energy barrier for a Ln&#x02013;SMM with trigonal prismatic geometry. We recognized the [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> structural motif as an ideal template for investigating the relationship between trigonal prismatic molecular geometry and the magnetic anisotropy of the rest of the late Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions. The homoleptic coordination environment of [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> leads to higher symmetry compared to many of the previously reported trigonal prismatic SMMs which contain hetero-ligand donor atoms.</p><p>Herein, we report the synthesis, structural, and magnetic characterization of the late Ln-[1]ferrocenophane complexes, [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (Ln = Gd (<bold>1</bold>), Ho (<bold>2</bold>), Er (<bold>3</bold>), Tm (<bold>4</bold>), Yb (<bold>5</bold>), Lu (<bold>6</bold>)). Of the compounds reported, the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane compound [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> exhibits slow magnetic relaxation in the absence of externally applied dc fields which renders it a rare example of a non-Kramers Ho<sup>3+</sup> SMM. Furthermore, we show how small distortions in the trigonal prismatic ligand field can lead to dramatic differences in magnetization dynamics of the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane structural motif by synthesizing and magnetically characterizing the pyridine (py) and 2-methyl THF (THF*) solvent adducts, [Li(py)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-py</bold>) and [Li(THF*)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF*)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-THF*</bold>), respectively. Compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> were also investigated by <italic>ab initio</italic> computational methods which provided further insight into the electronic structure of the Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions residing in a trigonal prismatic ligand field geometry and their observed static and dynamic magnetic properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Synthesis</title><p>The late Ln-[1]ferrocenophane compounds [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][LnFc<sub>3</sub>Li(THF)<sub>2</sub>] (Ln = Gd (<bold>1</bold>), Ho (<bold>2</bold>), Er (<bold>3</bold>), Tm (<bold>4</bold>), Yb (<bold>5</bold>), or Lu (<bold>6</bold>)) were prepared using a previously reported protocol <italic>via</italic> the salt elimination reaction of anhydrous LnCl<sub>3</sub> with excess Li<sub>6</sub>Fc<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (TMEDA = tetramethylethylenediamine) in THF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr">44,45</xref></sup> Crude <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> are moderately soluble in Et<sub>2</sub>O which allows for their facile separation from insoluble unreacted starting materials and/or biproducts. Following an Et<sub>2</sub>O extraction, crude <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> are recrystallized by slow diffusion of pentane into their concentrated THF solutions, forming highly air and moisture sensitive plate crystals of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> in yields between 21&#x02013;91% (based on Ln). The relatively high yield of the Tm-[1]ferrocenophane compound <bold>4</bold> (91%), is an outlier and could be a result of the Tm<sup>3+</sup> six-coordinate ionic radii (0.880 &#x000c5;) being the optimal size for the [LnFc<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3&#x02212;</sup> coordination environment. Compound <bold>1</bold> can also be synthesized using anhydrous GdI<sub>3</sub> but in lower yields due to difficult separation of (THF)<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>LiI or [(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub>LiI]<sub>2</sub> salt biproducts. Furthermore, depending on the crystallinity of the LnCl<sub>3</sub> salt, higher yields are obtained for compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> by forming the LnCl<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub><italic>x</italic></sub> solvate prior to addition to Li<sub>6</sub>Fc<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub>.</p><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>(Top) Preparation of late Ln-[1]ferrocenophane compounds. (Bottom) <sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz, THF-d<sub>8</sub>) of the Lu-[1]ferrocenophane compound <bold>6</bold>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f1"/></fig><p>The low temperature crystallization of the heaviest Yb- and Lu-[1]ferrocenophane complexes <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> resulted in a mixture of crystals with two habits: crystals of plate and rod-like shapes could easily be identified. Analysis of both morphologies <italic>via</italic> single-crystal X-ray diffraction (<italic>vide infra</italic>) determined the rod-shaped crystals to contain structurally unique solvate of the [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> anion (hereon denoted as <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold>) whereas the plate crystals are isostructural to <bold>1&#x02013;4</bold>. The crystalline structure of <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> differs from <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> by means of an extra THF solvate molecule located in the crystal lattice. The formation of multiple solvates is unique to the preparation of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> and could be a consequence of the ionic radii of Yb<sup>3+</sup> and Lu<sup>3+</sup> being the smallest of the 4f series.</p><p>The diamagnetic nature of the 4f<sup><xref rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> electron configuration of the Lu<sup>3+</sup> ion allows for facile analysis of the solution phase structure of <bold>6</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectroscopy. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of a mixture of <bold>6</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> in THF-d<sub>8</sub> shows nearly identical chemical shifts as the previously reported [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][YFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] compound, with two downfield resonances at 4.05 ppm and 4.09 ppm corresponding to the two sets magnetically inequivalent protons of the diferrocenyl ligands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The presence of only two resonances corresponding to the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligand protons suggest the solution phase structures of <bold>6</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> are similar on the NMR measurement timescale.</p><p>Once crystalized, compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> are highly insoluble in nonpolar alkanes and ethers such as pentane, diethyl ether, and 1,4-dioxane as well as weakly or non-coordinating polar solvents, such as difluorobenzene. In contrast, <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> are highly soluble in polar coordinating solvents such as THF, 2-methyl THF (THF*) and pyridine (py). The solubility properties of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> suggest that dissolution could involve coordination of the polar coordinating solvent to the Li<sup>+</sup> ions within the lattice of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>. Therefore, we hypothesized that various solvent adducts of the general formula [Li(sol)<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>][LnFc<sub>3</sub>(sol)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>], where sol is a polar coordinating solvent, could be synthesized. Indeed, the synthesis of the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane solvent adducts, [Li(py)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-py</bold>) and [Li(THF*)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF*)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-THF*</bold>), was achieved by slow diffusion of pentanes into pyridine and 2-methyl THF solutions of [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>], respectively. Single crystal X-ray diffraction studies of <bold>2-py</bold> and <bold>2-THF*</bold> (<italic>vide infra</italic>) reveal that for <bold>2-py</bold> all coordinated THF molecules have been replaced by pyridine molecules. On the other hand, the structure of <bold>2-THF*</bold> indicates significant disorder in the THF* solvate molecules which could suggest a statistical mixture of [Li&#x02013;THF]<sup>+</sup> and [Li&#x02013;THF*]<sup>+</sup> units within the same crystal lattice.</p></sec><sec><title>Solid state structural determination</title><sec><title>Solid state structures of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, <bold>5Iso</bold>, and <bold>6Iso</bold></title><p>The solid-state structures of compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> were determined <italic>via</italic> single-crystal X-ray diffraction and are isostructural to the previously reported Tb<sup>3+</sup> and Dy<sup>3+</sup> congeners. All six compounds crystalize in the monoclinic space group <italic>P</italic>2<sub>1</sub>/<italic>c</italic> inside a highly anisotropic unit cell (<italic>a</italic>,<italic>c</italic> &#x0003c; 15 &#x000c5; and <italic>b</italic> &#x0003e; 60 &#x000c5;). The molecular structure of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> features a single Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion accommodated by three dianionic ferrocenyl ligands (Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) that are arranged in a distorted C<sub>3</sub> fashion around the central Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). The six-coordinate geometry of each Ln-[1]ferrocenophane molecule is most accurately described as distorted trigonal prismatic with the principal C<sub>3</sub> axis passing through the centroids of the three diferrocenyl C1-carbons, forming a tri-anionic &#x0201c;pocket&#x0201d; above and below the equatorial plane of the molecule. Each charged ligand &#x0201c;pocket&#x0201d; is stabilized by a [Li&#x02013;THF]<sup>+</sup> moiety which completes the inner-sphere, [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, monoanionic complex. The molecular charge is balanced by a [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> unit residing in the outer-sphere.</p><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Molecular structure of the two crystallographically unique [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> complexes of <bold>2</bold>. Hydrogen atoms and [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> counter cations removed for clarity. Pink = Ho, orange = Fe, blue = Li, red = O, grey = C.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f2"/></fig><p>The unit cells of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> contain two structurally unique Ln-[1]ferrocenophane molecules per asymmetric unit (<bold>Ln(1)</bold> and <bold>Ln(2)</bold>), each having similar bonding parameters (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Across the series the average Ln&#x02013;C bond distances decrease from 2.572[8] &#x000c5; and 2.569[8] &#x000c5; for 1 (<bold>Gd(1)</bold> and <bold>Gd(2)</bold>, respectively) to 2.501[11] &#x000c5; and 2.497[11] &#x000c5; for compound <bold>6</bold> (<bold>Lu(1)</bold> and <bold>Lu(2)</bold>, respectively). The observed decrease in Ln&#x02013;C bond distance with increase in atomic number is most likely due to the increased Lewis acidity and/or the smaller ionic radii of the heaviest Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions. The intramolecular Ln&#x022ef;Fe distances show a more subtle change across the period decreasing from 3.2281[12] &#x000c5; and 3.2300[12] &#x000c5; for <bold>1</bold> (<bold>Gd(1)</bold> and <bold>Gd(2)</bold>, respectively) to 3.2108[16] &#x000c5; and 3.2068[16] &#x000c5; for <bold>6</bold> (<bold>Lu(1)</bold> and <bold>Lu(2)</bold>, respectively). The average Ln&#x022ef;Fe distances between 3.2300[12] to 3.2068[16] &#x000c5; are some of the closest reported for any heterometallic Ln&#x02013;Fe species, but lie just outside the sum of the covalent radii of the Fe<sup>2+</sup> and Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions.<sup><xref rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></p><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Selected average interatomic distances and angles for compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 (Gd)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2 (Ho)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3 (Er)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4 (Tm)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5 (Yb)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6 (Lu)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(1)</bold>&#x02013;C, &#x000c5;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.572[8]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.532[13]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.521[9]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.520[5]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.499[17]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.501[11]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(2)</bold>&#x02013;C, &#x000c5;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.569[8]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.539[12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.522[9]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.517[5]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.503[16]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.497[11]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(1)</bold>&#x022ef;Fe, &#x000c5;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2281[12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.229[8]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2196[14]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.214[8]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.213[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2108[16]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(2)</bold>&#x022ef;Fe, &#x000c5;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2300[12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.221[13]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2172[14]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.212[8]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.209[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2068[16]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(1)</bold> C1&#x02013;Fe&#x02013;C1, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.3[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.5[5]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.9[4]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.1[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.1[7]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.2[4]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(2)</bold> C1&#x02013;Fe&#x02013;C1, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.9[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.8[5]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.1[4]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.0[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.3[7]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.1[1]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&#x02013;<bold>Ln(1)</bold>&#x02013;C, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.9[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3[4]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.9[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0[6]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.8[4]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&#x02013;<bold>Ln(2)</bold>&#x02013;C, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3[4]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.8[3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0[2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.1[6]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.1[4]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(1)</bold>, Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ln(2)</bold>, Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist, &#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.56</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Despite miniscule differences in the average bonding parameters between the distinct <bold>Ln(1)</bold> and <bold>Ln(2)</bold> molecules within each unit cell of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, each molecule shows significant differences of the average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligand twist angle. Here, the ligand twist angle is defined by the torsion of the two C1 donor atoms of a single diferrocenyl ligand with respect to the centroids (previously described) of the trianionic pockets located above and below equatorial plane of the molecule (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref> left inset). A ligand twist angle greater than 0&#x000b0; would indicate distortion of the molecular geometry away from ideal trigonal prismatic geometry. For the <bold>Ho(1)</bold> and <bold>Ho(2)</bold> molecules of compound <bold>2</bold>, the average ligand twist angles are 10.67&#x000b0; and 12.67&#x000b0;, respectively. It is important to note here that such small differences in the ligand field geometry can greatly influence the spectroscopic and magnetic characteristics of a Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion.<sup><xref rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr">47,48</xref></sup> Considering the <bold>Ln(2)</bold> molecules across the heavy lanthanide series, the average diferrocenyl twist angle has an inversely proportional relationship to the 6-coordinate ionic radius of the Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion, increasing from 9.64&#x000b0; for <bold>Gd(2)</bold> (<italic>r</italic><sub>Gd<sup>3+</sup></sub> = 0.938 &#x000c5;) to 18.56&#x000b0; for <bold>Lu(2)</bold> (<italic>r</italic><sub>Lu<sup>3+</sup></sub> = 0.861 &#x000c5;). The <bold>Ln(1)</bold> molecules across the period show an identical trend. This inverse relationship between twist angle and ionic radius can be explained by the increased steric hindrance of the [Fc<sub>3</sub>]<sup>6&#x02212;</sup> ligand field as the Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radius decreases and the needed &#x02018;twist&#x02019; of the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligands to stabilize the smaller Ln<sup>3+</sup> center.</p><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>(Left) Ligand twist angle dependence on Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radius of <bold>Ln(2)</bold> molecules of [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and selected previously reported trigonal prismatic lanthanide complexes. (Right) Dependence of average ligand donor distance, d (defined in right inset), on the Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radius. Triangles = <bold>Ln(2)</bold> of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> ([YFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> included from <xref rid="cit51" ref-type="bibr">ref. 51</xref>), squares = [Ln(L)<sub>3</sub>], circles = [(L<sup>CO</sup>)Ln(N(SiMe<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>], crosses = Ln(Bc<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub>, lines = Ln(Bp<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub>, and X = Ln(Bp<sup>2Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub> (Y<sup>3+</sup> compounds included for selected examples).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f3"/></fig><p>For the trigonal prismatic geometry, comparison of the distance, <italic>d</italic>, between eclipsed ligand donor atoms or pseudo eclipsed donors (in the case of a ligand twist angle &#x0003e; 0) for a series of similar complexes can indicate the degree of ligand rigidity as well as the axiality trigonal ligand field of the central Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion. In the case of [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, <italic>d</italic> would be the distance between the two C1 donors of a single Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligand (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref> right inset) and is proportional to the C&#x02013;Ln&#x02013;C bite angle. For the <bold>Ln(2)</bold> molecules of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, the largest average <italic>d</italic> value of the three Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligands is 3.336 &#x000c5; for <bold>1</bold> which features the largest Gd<sup>3+</sup> ion. Upon moving across the row, the average C1&#x022ef;C1 distance of the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligand decreases to a value of 3.249 &#x000c5; for <bold>6</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref> right). The decrease in average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> C1&#x022ef;C1 distance with decrease in Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radii is accompanied by a decrease in the average C1&#x02013;Fe&#x02013;C1 angle of the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligand from 104.9&#x000b0;[3] for the <bold>Gd(2)</bold> in <bold>1</bold> to 102.1&#x000b0;[1] for <bold>Lu(2)</bold> in <bold>6</bold>.</p><p>In order to gain a more comprehensive picture of the geometric trends in trigonal prismatic lanthanide compounds, we compared the average ligand twist angle and <italic>d</italic> values of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> with the same parameters of selected previously reported trigonal prismatic lanthanide complexes [(L<sup>CO</sup>)Ln(N(SiMe<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>] (HL<sup>CO</sup> = {<italic>N</italic>-[(2-MeO)&#x02013;C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>]}N<private-char name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash"><!-- PBM data was replaced with SVG by xgml2pxml:
<glyph-data id="z.dbd" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="8" y-size="10" xml:space="preserve">
00000000
00000000
00000000
00000000
11111111
00000000
11111111
00000000
00000000
00000000
</glyph-data>
-->
<glyph-data id="z.dbd" format="SVG" resolution="300" x-size="8" y-size="10" xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA[
<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" version="1.0" width="13.200000pt" height="16.000000pt" viewBox="0 0 13.200000 16.000000" preserveAspectRatio="xMidYMid meet"><metadata>
Created by potrace 1.16, written by Peter Selinger 2001-2019
</metadata><g transform="translate(1.000000,15.000000) scale(0.017500,-0.017500)" fill="currentColor" stroke="none"><path d="M0 440 l0 -40 320 0 320 0 0 40 0 40 -320 0 -320 0 0 -40z M0 280 l0 -40 320 0 320 0 0 40 0 40 -320 0 -320 0 0 -40z"/></g></svg>
]]>
</glyph-data></private-char>C(Me)CH<private-char name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash"><glyph-ref glyph-data="z.dbd"/></private-char>C(Me)N(H){N'-[(2-MeO)C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>]}; Ln = Nd<sup>3+</sup>, Dy<sup>3+</sup>, or Y<sup>3+</sup>),<sup><xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr">37,49</xref></sup>, [Ln(L)<sub>3</sub>] (HL = 2-(((2,6-diisopropylphenyl)imino)methyl)-phenol; Ln = Dy<sup>3+</sup> or Er<sup>3+</sup>),<sup><xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> Ln(Bp<sup>Me<sub>2</sub></sup>)<sub>3</sub> ([Bp<sup>Me<sub>2</sub></sup>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> = dihydrobis(dimethylpyrazole)borate; Ln = Sm<sup>3+</sup>, Dy<sup>3+</sup>, or Y<sup>3+</sup>),<sup><xref rid="cit39" ref-type="bibr">39,50</xref></sup> Ln(Bp<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub> ([Bp<sup>Me</sup>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> = dihydrobis(methylpyrazole)borate; Ln = Tb<sup>3+</sup>, Dy<sup>3+</sup>, Y<sup>3+</sup>, Ho<sup>3+</sup>, or Er<sup>3+</sup>), and Ln(Bc<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub> ([Bc<sup>Me</sup>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> = dihydrobis(methylimidazolyl)borate; Ln = Tb<sup>3+</sup>, Dy<sup>3+</sup>, Y<sup>3+</sup>, Ho<sup>3+</sup>, or Er<sup>3+</sup>)<sup><xref rid="cit40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Of the compared complexes, <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, Ln(Bp<sup>Me<sub>2</sub></sup>)<sub>3</sub>, Ln(Bp<sup>Me</sup>), and Ln(Bc<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub> feature a homo-ligand donor environment around the central Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions. To this end, for the tris-pyrazolyl and tris-imidazolyl borate complexes, the possibility of HB&#x02013;H&#x022ef;Ln agostic interactions complicate a complete structural comparison with these compounds. Upon inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref> (Left), it is apparent that the Ln-[1]ferrocenophane complexes, <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, feature the greatest susceptibility of ligand twist angle with a change in ionic radius. Furthermore, in contrast to the Ln-[1]ferrocenophane series, [(L<sup>CO</sup>)Ln(N(SiMe<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>], [Ln(L)<sub>3</sub>], Ln(Bp<sup>Me<sub>2</sub></sup>)<sub>3</sub>, Ln(Bp<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub>, and Ln(Bc<sup>Me</sup>)<sub>3</sub> feature an increase of the average ligand twist angle with Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radius or do not show a significant correlation at all (in the case of the tris&#x02013;borate complexes).</p><p>In general, all five sets of compared trigonal prismatic lanthanide complexes exhibit an increase in the average eclipsed/pseudo eclipsed ligand donor distanced, with an increase in Ln<sup>3+</sup> ionic radii (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>, right). Despite this similar trend, the Ln-[1]ferrocenophane complexes, <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, feature the largest average <italic>d</italic> values of the compared complexes. This distinction is significant and could suggest the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> donor ligands of <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold> might interact more strongly with f-orbitals of <italic>z</italic>-character, which in turn would have a significant influence of the magnetism of these compounds.</p><p>The single-crystal X-ray structures for the Yb<sup>3+</sup> and Lu<sup>3+</sup> solvates, <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold>, were solved in the monoclinic space group <italic>I</italic><sub>a</sub> and <italic>Cc</italic>, respectively, inside a unit cell with lengths between 20&#x02013;33 &#x000c5;. Though solved in different space groups, <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> are most likely isostructural given the almost identical unit cell volumes of 16&#x02009;344(3) &#x000c5;<sup>3</sup> (for <bold>5Iso</bold>) and 16&#x02009;419(4) &#x000c5;<sup>3</sup> (for <bold>6Iso</bold>) (see ESI<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref> for details). Both <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> contain three structurally unique [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] molecules per unit cell along with an uncoordinated THF lattice solvate per Ln-[1]ferrocenophane molecule which is not present in compounds <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The average Ln&#x02013;C and Ln&#x022ef;Fe distances for the three independent molecules of <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold> are close to the corresponding distances for the two independent molecules of compound <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold>, respectively (Table S12<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). To this end, the average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angles vary significantly between corresponding solvates. The most distorted molecules of the THF solvated molecules, <bold>5Iso</bold> and <bold>6Iso</bold>, exhibit a 3.3&#x000b0; and a 2.4&#x000b0; increase in twist angle when compared to the most highly distorted molecules of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold>, respectively. This result is significant as it highlights how crystal packing effects can greatly influence the geometry of the inner coordination sphere of the individual molecules in the solid state.</p><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Molecular structure of the three crystallographically unique [YbFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> complexes of <bold>5Iso</bold> and THF solvate molecules. Hydrogen atoms and [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> counter cations removed for clarity. Yellow = Yb, orange = Fe, blue = Li, red = O, grey = C.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Solid state structures of <bold>2-THF*</bold> and <bold>2-py</bold></title><p>The single crystal X-ray structures of the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane THF* and pyridine adducts, <bold>2-THF*</bold> and <bold>2-py</bold>, were solved in the monoclinic and orthorhombic space group <italic>P</italic>2<sub>1</sub>/<italic>n</italic> and <italic>P</italic>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>, respectively. Both <bold>2-THF*</bold> and <bold>2-py</bold> feature a [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(sol)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> core similar to that of compound <bold>2</bold> except with displaced THF molecules of the [Li&#x02013;THF]<sup>+</sup> units with THF* (for <bold>2-THF*</bold>) or pyridine (for <bold>2-py</bold>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). Substitution of inner sphere THF molecules with THF* or pyridine do not significantly change the Ho&#x02013;C bond distances which are within error equal to those of compound <bold>2</bold> (Table S13<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). To this end, the Ho&#x022ef;Fe distances decrease from 3.229[8] and 3.221[13] for <bold>Ho(1)</bold> and <bold>Ho(2)</bold> in <bold>2</bold> to 3.2098[13] &#x000c5; for <bold>2-THF*</bold> to 3.1970[15] &#x000c5; and 3.1617[16] &#x000c5; for <bold>Ho(1)-py</bold> and <bold>Ho(2)-py</bold> in <bold>2-py</bold>. In contrast to compound <bold>2</bold>, the unit cell of <bold>2-THF*</bold> contains only a single structurally unique Ho<sup>3+</sup> site. Significant disorder of the THF* molecules was observed in the X-ray structure <bold>2-THF*</bold> which is likely a result of multiple orientations of the coordinated THF* molecule. It should also be noted that the observed disorder could also suggest incomplete displacement of the THF molecules upon dissolution of compound <bold>2</bold> in THF*. To this end, the atoms of the [HoFc<sub>3</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> core do not show signs of disorder which might have been expected considering the differing donor strengths of the THF and THF*. Similar to <bold>2</bold>, the unit cell of <bold>2-py</bold> features two structurally unique Ho<sup>3+</sup> sites. Only positional disorder of the inner sphere pyridine solvate molecules of the [Li&#x02013;py]<sup>+</sup> unit is observed in the X-ray structure which suggest full displacement of the THF molecules upon dissolution of <bold>2</bold> in pyridine.</p><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Molecular structure of <bold>2-THF*</bold> (a) and the two crystallographically unique [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> complexes of <bold>2-py</bold> (b). Hydrogen atoms and [Li(sol)<sub>4</sub>]<sup>+</sup> counter cations removed for clarity. Pink = Ho, orange = Fe, blue = Li, red = O, dark blue = N, grey = C.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f5"/></fig><p>Though little variation is observed in the interatomic Ho&#x02013;C distances between <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold>, the average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angle varies significantly upon changing the identity of the axial [Li-sol]<sup>+</sup> moiety. Considering the most highly distorted molecule within each of the unit cells, the average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angle increases from 12.67&#x000b0; (for <bold>2</bold>), to 16.52&#x000b0; (for <bold>2-THF*</bold>), to 23.69&#x000b0; (for <bold>2-py</bold>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). The average Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angle for <bold>2-py</bold> represents the largest of any of the Ln-[1]ferrocenophane compounds reported herein. As shown previously with the structural variation between the corresponding solvates of the Yb- and Lu-[1]ferrocenophane complexes, crystal packing can greatly influence the geometry of the [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> inner coordination sphere. The variation in the crystal packing for <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> is also emphasized by the changes in the closest intermolecular distances between Ho<sup>3+</sup> sites of 10.586 &#x000c5; (for <bold>2</bold>), 11.069 &#x000c5; (for <bold>2-THF*</bold>), and 8.941 &#x000c5; (for <bold>2-py</bold>) (Table S14<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). The varying electronic donor strengths of the solvent molecules likely plays an additional role in the geometric variation between <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> though similar Li&#x02013;C and Li&#x022ef;Ho interatomic distance between the molecules precludes any further discussion here.</p><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Comparison of the average twist angle of the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> ligands in <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> viewed down the Li&#x02013;Ho&#x02013;Li axis. Coordinated THF, THF*, and pyridine molecules removed for clarity.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Magnetic properties</title><sec><title>Static magnetic properties of [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>1&#x02013;5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold>)</title><p>The static magnetic properties of compounds <bold>1&#x02013;5</bold> were investigated by measuring the temperature dependence of the molar magnetic susceptibility under an external 0.1 T magnetic field across the 300&#x02013;2 K temperature range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). The <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> (300 K) values for <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold> are 14.39 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<bold>2</bold>), 11.71 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<bold>3</bold>), 7.00 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<bold>4</bold>), and 2.50 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<bold>5</bold>) and correspond nicely to the expected values of 14.07 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 11.48 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 7.15 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and 2.57 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for a single non-interacting Ho<sup>3+</sup> (<sup>5</sup>I<sub>8</sub>; <italic>S</italic> = 2, <italic>L</italic> = 6; <italic>g</italic><sub>J</sub> = 5/4), Er<sup>3+</sup> (<sup>4</sup>I<sub>15/2</sub>; <italic>S</italic> = 3/2, <italic>L</italic> = 6; <italic>g</italic><sub>J</sub> = 6/5), Tm<sup>3+</sup> (<sup>3</sup>H<sub>6</sub>; <italic>S</italic> = 1, <italic>L</italic> = 5; <italic>g</italic><sub>J</sub> = 7/6), and Yb<sup>3+</sup> (<sup>2</sup>F<sub>7/2</sub>; <italic>S</italic> = 1/2, <italic>L</italic> = 3; <italic>g</italic><sub>J</sub> = 8/7) ions, respectively. The <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> (300 K) value of 1 is 8.84 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and is slightly higher than the expected value of 7.88 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for a non-interacting Gd<sup>3+</sup> ion (<sup>8</sup>S<sub>7/2</sub>; <italic>S</italic> = 7/2, <italic>L</italic> = 0; <italic>g</italic><sub>J</sub> = 2). This discrepancy could be due to small weighing errors or a preferred orientation of the Gd-[1]ferrocenophane plate crystallites aligning with the external field, resulting in a slight increase of the magnetic moment. Upon cooling, the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> of <bold>1</bold> remains constant across the entire temperature range suggesting an isolated <italic>S</italic> = 7/2 ground state and weak intermolecular magnetic interactions between neighboring molecules in the crystal lattice. In contrast, deviation from typical Curie&#x02013;Weiss behavior is observed for <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold>. For the Ho<sup>3+</sup> and Yb<sup>3+</sup> compounds <bold>2</bold> and <bold>5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold>, the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> value remains nearly constant until <italic>ca.</italic> 100 K where a gradual decrease is observed to minimum values of 9.77 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (for <bold>2</bold>) and 0.63 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (for <bold>5</bold>) at 2.5 K and 2 K, respectively. A steeper <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> decline at low temperatures is observed for <bold>3</bold>, where a drop from 11.08 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 5.86 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> occurs between 100&#x02013;2 K. The most pronounced temperature dependent behavior is observed for the Tm<sup>3+</sup> compound <bold>4</bold> which exhibits a nearly linear decrease of <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> with temperature beginning at 30 K to a minimum value of 0.23 emu K mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 2 K. The low temperature decline of the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> value observed for <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold> is typical for mono-metallic species containing a single anisotropic Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion and is commonly attributed to the depopulation of the crystal field states, very weak intermolecular antiferromagnetic interactions, and/or blocking of the magnetization. However, the precipitous drop of the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> value of <bold>4</bold> suggest population of a non-magnetic ground state at the lowest temperatures. This observation is further supported by <italic>ab initio</italic> calculations which predicts a stabilization of a <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = 0 ground state of the Tm<sup>3+</sup> ion within the crystal field sublevels (<italic>vide infra</italic>).</p><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Temperature dependence of the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub>M</sub><italic>T</italic> of <bold>1&#x02013;5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold> (<italic>H</italic> = 0.1 <italic>T</italic>, <italic>T</italic> = 2&#x02013;300 K).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f7"/></fig><p>The static magnetic behavior of <bold>1&#x02013;5</bold> was further investigated by measuring the field dependence of the magnetization between 2&#x02013;8 K (Fig. S12<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). For compounds <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold>, the 2 K magnetization values at the 7 T field limit are 5.11 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for <bold>2</bold>), 6.16 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for <bold>3</bold>), 1.28 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for <bold>4</bold>), and 1.36 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for <bold>5</bold>), respectively, and are much lower than the expected single ion <italic>M</italic><sub>s</sub> values of 10 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for Ho<sup>3+</sup>), 9 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for Er<sup>3+</sup>), 7 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for Tm<sup>3+</sup>), and 4 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> (for Yb<sup>3+</sup>). This discrepancy suggests anisotropy of the lowest energy J multiplets of the respective Ln<sup>3+</sup> ion which results in non-degenerate <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> microstates. The inherent magnetic anisotropy of <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold> is further supported by the non-superposition of the <italic>M vs. H</italic>/<italic>T</italic> curves between 2&#x02013;8 K (Fig. S13<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). For compound <bold>1</bold>, the 2 K magnetization curve reaches a maximum value of 7.78 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> at 7 <italic>T</italic> which corresponds nicely to the expected value of 7 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sub>B</sub> for a single Gd<sup>3+</sup> ion. This data along with the superposition of the <italic>M vs. H</italic>/<italic>T</italic> curves between 2&#x02013;8 K supports the isotropic nature of an isolated <italic>S</italic> = 7/2 ground state in <bold>1</bold>.</p></sec><sec><title>Dynamic magnetic properties of [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2</bold>)</title><p>Examples of mononuclear Ho-based molecules that display dynamic magnetic behavior are relatively sparse in the literature.<sup><xref rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr">28,52&#x02013;57</xref></sup> Even rarer are holmium SMMs which are supported by purely organic based ligand field environments.<sup><xref rid="cit58" ref-type="bibr">58,59</xref></sup> The rarity of Ho-based SMMs is likely due to Ho<sup>3+</sup> being a non-Kramers ion, which does not necessitate a degenerate magnetic ground state as in Dy<sup>3+</sup>, Er<sup>3+</sup>, or Yb<sup>3+</sup> based molecules. Furthermore, the 100% natural abundance of the <italic>I</italic> = 7/2 <sup>165</sup>Ho nuclei facilitates strong nuclear hyperfine interactions which can cause fast QTM.<sup><xref rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup></p><p>A common characteristic among the few reported Ho-based SMMs is a highly symmetric axial ligand field environment which stabilizes a suitably anisotropic <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> ground state of the oblate Ho<sup>3+</sup> ion. Previous <italic>ab initio</italic> studies of the Dy- and Tb-[1]ferrocenophane compounds suggest the three diferrocenyl ligands of [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> promote a largely axial ligand field that stabilizes large <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> ground states in the oblate Dy<sup>3+</sup> and Tb<sup>3+</sup> ions. Based on these results, we hypothesized that the trigonal prismatic [Fc<sub>3</sub>]<sup>6&#x02212;</sup> ligand field could be suitable to promote a highly anisotropic ground state in the oblate Ho<sup>3+</sup> ion resulting in SMM behavior in the [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> complex. In order to probe the SMM behavior in <bold>2</bold>, the variable temperature alternating current (ac) magnetic susceptibility was measured in the absence of an external magnetic field. The presence of a broad temperature dependent signal in the molar out-of-phase component <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t1.jpg" id="ugt1"/> of the ac magnetic susceptibility <italic>versus</italic> frequency plot indicates <bold>2</bold> is indeed a rare example of zero applied field Ho<sup>3+</sup> SMM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8a</xref>). Between 2&#x02013;5 K, the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t2.jpg" id="ugt2"/> signal maximum is slightly temperature dependent, shifting to higher frequencies upon increasing the temperature. This slight variation of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t3.jpg" id="ugt3"/> maximum with temperature is significant as it suggests contributions to the spin relaxation from thermally assisted Raman and/or Orbach mechanisms even at the lowest temperatures. Increasing the temperature above 5 K, the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t4.jpg" id="ugt4"/> maximum becomes increasingly temperature dependent, moving outside the 1000 Hz frequency limit at 11 K.</p><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>(a&#x02013;c) Temperature dependence of the out-of-phase component of the molar ac magnetic susceptibility <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t27.jpg" id="ugt27"/> of <bold>2</bold> (a) and the corresponding resolved slow (b) and fast (c) relaxation processes. (d&#x02013;f) Temperature dependence of the out-of-phase component of the molar ac susceptibility <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t28.jpg" id="ugt28"/> of <bold>2-dilute</bold> and the corresponding resolved slow (e) and fast (f) relaxation processes (<italic>H</italic> = 0 <italic>T</italic>, <italic>T</italic> = 2&#x02013;11 K). Lines represent fits to the experimental data (circles) or resolved <bold>SR</bold> and <bold>FR</bold> data.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f8"/></fig><p>The exceptionally broad nature of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t5.jpg" id="ugt5"/> signal of <bold>2</bold> indicates multiple spin relaxation processes are occurring at similar ac frequencies.<sup><xref rid="cit61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> It is likely that this observation is predominately a result of the two structurally unique <bold>Ho(1)</bold> and <bold>Ho(2)</bold> sites in the solid state structure of <bold>2</bold> having slightly different magnetization dynamics. However, the complexity of the spin dynamics of Ln&#x02013;SMMs has recently been emphasized and the simultaneous contribution from Raman, Orbach, and QTM processes to the spin relaxation of a single Ho<sup>3+</sup> ion cannot be excluded.<sup><xref rid="cit62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> The molar in-phase <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t6.jpg" id="ugt6"/> and the out-of-phase <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t7.jpg" id="ugt7"/> components of the ac magnetic susceptibility of <bold>2</bold> were used to construct Cole&#x02013;Cole plots <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t8.jpg" id="ugt8"/> at each temperature which were subsequently fit with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn1">eqn (1)</xref>:<disp-formula id="eqn1"><label>1</label><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t9.jpg" id="ugt9" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula></p><p>(Cole&#x02013;Cole parameters defined in ESI<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn1">Eqn (1)</xref> represents the sum of two modified Debye functions and describes two magnetic relaxation processes each having a characteristic magnetic relaxation time, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>2</sub>, at each temperature.</p><p>Using the extracted Cole&#x02013;Cole parameters at each temperature, a &#x0201c;slow&#x0201d; (<bold>SR</bold>) and a &#x0201c;fast&#x0201d; (<bold>FR</bold>) relaxation process could be resolved in the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t10.jpg" id="ugt10"/><italic>versus</italic> frequency plot of <bold>2</bold>, where the 2 K <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t11.jpg" id="ugt11"/> signal maxima of <bold>SR</bold> and <bold>FR</bold> appear at 11.6 and 262.5 Hz, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8b and c</xref>). For <bold>FR</bold>, the shorter 2 K magnetic relaxation time of <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>2</sub> = 0.00058 s (as compared to <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.014 s for <bold>SR</bold>) and the temperature independence of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t12.jpg" id="ugt12"/> signal maximum suggests significant contribution of QTM to the spin relaxation. The origin of the increased QTM contribution for <bold>FR</bold> is most likely due to transverse fields arising from intermolecular interactions between neighboring spin centers or nuclear hyperfine interactions.</p><p>To further investigate the origin of QTM in <bold>2</bold>, the magnetically dilute species, [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][Y<sub>0.94</sub>Ho<sub>0.06</sub>Fc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-dilute</bold>), was prepared and magnetically characterized. Similar to <bold>2</bold>, the zero-field ac magnetic susceptibility data of <bold>2-dilute</bold> provides evidence of multiple spin relaxation processes, with two distinct maxima appearing at 1.2 Hz and 107.8 Hz in the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t13.jpg" id="ugt13"/><italic>vs.</italic> Frequency plot at 2 K (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8d</xref>). As previously described, a <bold>FR</bold> and <bold>SR</bold> process were resolved by fitting the ac magnetic susceptibility of <bold>2-dilute</bold> with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn1">eqn (1)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8e amd f</xref>). The 2 K magnetic relaxation times of <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.14 s (for <bold>SR</bold>) and <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>2</sub> = 0.0011 s (for <bold>FR</bold>) are at least half of an order of magnitude longer than the corresponding <bold>SR</bold> and <bold>FR</bold> processes for non-dilute <bold>2</bold> at the same temperature. This result is significant as it suggests that intermolecular magnetic interactions are playing a non-negligible role in the low temperature magnetization dynamics of compound <bold>2</bold>. To this end, the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t14.jpg" id="ugt14"/> maximum of the <bold>SR</bold> processes of <bold>2-dilute</bold> at low temperatures is still only marginally temperature dependent which might indicate intramolecular phenomenon such as nuclear hyperfine interactions are contributing to the QTM of <bold>2</bold>.</p><p>QTM pathways can also be mitigated by creating a field bias upon the application of an external magnetic field which breaks the degeneracy of the &#x000b1;<italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> crystal field states thereby lowering the probability of spin relaxation through tunneling mechanisms. The temperature dependence of the ac magnetic susceptibility of compound <bold>2</bold> was measured under an optimal 0.35 <italic>T</italic> magnetic field (Fig. S31<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>) from 1.8&#x02013;11 K. In an external field, the 2 K <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t15.jpg" id="ugt15"/> signal of <bold>2@0.35T</bold> remains broad but shows a significant shift of the maximum to lower frequencies suggesting an increase in the magnetic relaxation time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Heating the sample to 5 K results in a high frequency shift of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t16.jpg" id="ugt16"/> maximum as well as an increase in the magnitude of the signal. Interestingly, heating past 5 K results in an increase in symmetry of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t17.jpg" id="ugt17"/> signal and indicates the spin dynamics of <bold>2@0.35T</bold> is shifting towards a single relaxation process at higher temperatures. The <bold>2@0.35T</bold> magnetic relaxation time for the <bold>SR</bold> process at 2 K of <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0.13 s (determined using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn1">eqn (1)</xref>) is close to the corresponding <bold>SR</bold> process relaxation time for <bold>2-dilute</bold> at the same temperature. This observation suggests application of an external field and magnetic dilution have similar effects on the magnetization dynamics of <bold>2</bold>, at least when considering only the <bold>SR</bold> process.</p><fig id="fig9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><title>Temperature dependence of the out-of-phase component of the molar ac magnetic susceptibility <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t29.jpg" id="ugt29"/> of <bold>2@0.35T</bold> (<italic>H</italic> = 0.35 <italic>T</italic>, <italic>T</italic> = 2&#x02013;11 K). Lines represent fits to the experimental data (circles).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f9"/></fig><p>The magnetic relaxation times extracted using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn1">eqn (1)</xref> were used to construct Arrhenius plots (ln(<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>) <italic>vs.</italic> 1/<italic>T</italic>) for each of the <bold>SR</bold> and <bold>FR</bold> processes of <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-dilute</bold>, and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>). Each Arrhenius plot was fit using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn2">eqn (2)</xref>, which accounts for spin relaxation through direct, QTM, Raman, and Orbach relaxation processes.<sup><xref rid="cit63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn2"><label>2</label><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t18.jpg" id="ugt18" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula></p><fig id="fig10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><title>Arrhenius plots of the magnetic relaxation times of the of the &#x0201c;Slow&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Fast&#x0201d; magnetic relaxation processes of <bold>2</bold> (a), <bold>2-dilute</bold> (b), and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> (c). Solid blue circle in (a) represents point not included in Arrhenius fitting procedure.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f10"/></fig><p>In the case of <bold>2</bold> and <bold>2-dilute</bold> where <italic>H</italic> = 0 <italic>T</italic>, the direct term <italic>AH</italic><sup><italic>n</italic>1</sup><italic>T</italic> becomes zero and was therefore disregarded. For <bold>2@0.35T</bold>, the direct term <italic>A</italic> = 114 S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was determined by fitting the field dependence of the magnetic relaxation time (Fig. S31<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). Due to the complicated nature of the <bold>2@0.35T</bold> ac magnetic susceptibility, the low temperature regime (1.8&#x02013;2.5 K) could not be fit accurately and only the higher temperature regime (3&#x02013;11 K) of the <bold>SR</bold> process was considered in the Arrhenius fitting procedure. The best fit parameters obtained using this fitting procedure for <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-dilute</bold>, and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> are given in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. It is important to note that the fitting parameters for the <bold>FR</bold> process of <bold>2</bold> and <bold>2-dilute</bold> should only be considered as rough estimates, as the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t19.jpg" id="ugt19"/> maximum of the resolved signal lies outside of the measured frequency range at higher temperatures. For all fits, the obtained Raman coefficients (<italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub>) are close to the expected range of <italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub> = 5&#x02013;7 for a non-Kramers ion.<sup><xref rid="cit63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> For the <bold>FR</bold> and <bold>SR</bold> processes of <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-dilute</bold>, and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> energy barrier values between <italic>U</italic> = 110&#x02013;131 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were obtained.</p><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Arrhenius parameters of <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-dilute</bold>, and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> extracted using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn2">eqn (2)</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2@0.35T</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2-dilute</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Relaxation process 1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>A</italic> (S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>
<sub>QTM</sub> (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>C</italic> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;<italic>n</italic></sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00432</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>
<sub>o</sub> (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>U</italic> (cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Relaxation process 2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>A</italic> (S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>
<sub>QTM</sub> (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000593</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000755</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>C</italic> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;<italic>n</italic></sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00679</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c4;</italic>
<sub>o</sub> (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>U</italic> (cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Dynamic magnetic properties of [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<bold>2-py</bold>) and [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF*)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<bold>2-THF*</bold>)</title><p>Small perturbations in the crystal-field environment can greatly influence the electronic structure and thus the magnetization dynamics of lanthanide-based molecules. In order to explore how small distortions in the trigonal prismatic [Fc<sub>3</sub>]<sup>6&#x02212;</sup> ligand field effects the SMM properties of the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane compound, [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, the static and dynamic magnetic properties of the pyridine solvated complex, [HoFc<sub>3</sub>(py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<bold>2-py</bold>) were explored.</p><p>The static magnetic behavior of <bold>2-py</bold> is nearly identical to that of compound <bold>2</bold> (Fig. S11<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). Interestingly, the dynamic magnetic properties of <bold>2-py</bold> are markedly different from that of compound <bold>2</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Fig. 11</xref>). Compound <bold>2-py</bold> features extremely broad signals in the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t20.jpg" id="ugt20"/><italic>vs.</italic> frequency plot but does not feature any discernable signal maxima within the measured 1&#x02013;1000 Hz frequency range. This qualitative observation readily suggests that the magnetic relaxation times for the more geometrically distorted Ho-[1]ferrocenophane molecules in <bold>2-py</bold>, are much faster than the magnetic relaxation times observed for the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane molecules in <bold>2</bold>, which features a low frequency <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t21.jpg" id="ugt21"/> signal maximum at 18.2 Hz at 2 K. Upon increasing the temperature above 2 K, the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t22.jpg" id="ugt22"/> signal of <bold>2-py</bold> moves out of the high frequency limit and almost completely disappears at 10 K. Out-of-phase signals at only the highest frequencies without signal maxima within the frequency range could suggest QTM is a major contributor to the spin relaxation in <bold>2-py</bold>. Although the magnetic relaxation of <bold>2-py</bold> is too fast to allow the extraction of an energy barrier of magnetization reversal, the presented data suggests that the deviation from idealized trigonal prismatic geometry (increase in torsion angle) increases relaxation times.</p><fig id="fig11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><title>Temperature dependence of the out-of-phase component of the molar ac magnetic susceptibility <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t30.jpg" id="ugt30"/> of <bold>2-py</bold> (<italic>H</italic> = 0 <italic>T</italic>, <italic>T</italic> = 2&#x02013;10 K).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f11"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Dynamic magnetic properties of [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (Ln = Er<sup>3+</sup> (<bold>3</bold>), Tm<sup>3+</sup> (<bold>4</bold>), and Yb<sup>3+</sup> (<bold>5</bold>))</title><p>For the Er<sup>3+</sup>, Tm<sup>3+</sup>, and Yb<sup>3+</sup> compounds <bold>3</bold>, <bold>4</bold>, and <bold>5</bold> respectively, no appreciable signal is observed in the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t23.jpg" id="ugt23"/><italic>vs.</italic> Frequency plot in the absence of an external magnetic field. This result is not surprising as the axial [LnFc<sub>3</sub>]<sup>3&#x02212;</sup> ligand field likely destabilizes the largest <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = &#x000b1;15/2, &#x000b1;6, and &#x000b1;7/2 projections of the prolate Er<sup>3+</sup>, Tm<sup>3+</sup>, and Yb<sup>3+</sup> ions, respectively. These results are also consistent with dc magnetization data for the Tm<sup>3+</sup> compounds, <bold>4</bold>, which suggest the lowest energy <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = 0 ground state for <bold>4</bold>.</p><p>For the Yb<sup>3+</sup> compound <bold>5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold>, application of an optimal 0.2 T external magnetic field results in slow magnetic relaxation behavior as evidenced by a narrow temperature dependent signal in <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t24.jpg" id="ugt24"/><italic>vs.</italic> Frequency plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12">Fig. 12a</xref>). Between 1.8&#x02013;2 K, the magnitude of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t25.jpg" id="ugt25"/> signal increases which could suggest that the spin relaxation is occurring through multiple relaxation mechanisms at the lowest temperatures and subsequently shifting towards a single mechanism upon heating. Heating results in an increased temperature dependence of the <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t26.jpg" id="ugt26"/> single maximum which eventually moves outside of the measured frequency range at 3.5 K.</p><fig id="fig12" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><title>(a) Temperature dependence of the out-of-phase component of the molar ac magnetic susceptibility <inline-graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-t31.jpg" id="ugt31"/> of <bold>5</bold>. (<italic>H</italic> = 0.2 <italic>T</italic>, <italic>T</italic> = 1.8&#x02013;3.9 K). (b) Arrhenius plot of the magnetic relaxation time of <bold>5</bold>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f12"/></fig><p>Using the ac magnetic susceptibility of compound <bold>5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold>, Cole&#x02013;Cole curves were constructed and were fitted using general Debye equation which considers only one spin relaxation process. The extracted magnetic relaxation times were then used to construct an Arrhenius plot between 1.8&#x02013;3.5 K (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12">Fig. 12b</xref>). Analyzing the Arrhenius plot for compound <bold>5</bold> shows the magnetic relaxation times for <bold>5</bold> are temperature dependent across the full temperature range suggesting low contribution from quantum tunneling processes. Between 2.5&#x02013;3.5 K, the magnetic relaxation times become increasingly temperature dependent but never become fully linear on the logarithmic scale. This indicates significant contributions to the spin relaxation from second-order Raman and/or direct processes even at the highest temperature regime. Similar behavior has been observed in the trigonal Yb<sup>3+</sup> SMM, Yb[trensal], where it was reported that considering solely an Orbach relaxation mechanism was insufficient in describing the anisotropy energy barrier of the system.<sup><xref rid="cit64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup> As previously described, the Arrhenius plot for <bold>5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold> was fit using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn2">eqn (2)</xref>. The direct exponent, <italic>n</italic><sub>1</sub>, was held constant at <italic>n</italic><sub>1</sub> = 4 and the direct term, <italic>A</italic>, was allowed to freely refine along with the other Arrhenius parameters due to the inability in acquiring a reasonable fit of the <italic>&#x003c4; vs.</italic> H plot for compound <bold>5</bold>/<bold>5Iso</bold> (Fig. S49<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>). Using this fitting procedure, values of Arrhenius parameters of <italic>A</italic> = 0.304 S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>QTM</sub> = 0.00269 s, <italic>C</italic> = 0.00812 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>,<sup><xref rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup><italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub> = 4.25, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>o</sub> = 9.04 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> s, and <italic>U</italic> = 6 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were obtained.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Electronic structure determination of compounds <bold>1&#x02013;5</bold></title><p>To further investigate the electronic structure of the late lanthanide ions in the trigonal prismatic geometry and the observed magnetic properties of <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold>, multi-configurational <italic>ab initio</italic> calculations were performed using the Molcas 8.2 package within the CASSCF/SO-RASSI and XMS-CASPT2/SO-RASSI level of theory.<sup><xref rid="cit65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup> For the two independent <bold>Ln(1)</bold> and <bold>Ln(2)</bold> molecules of <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold>, there are only small differences of the energies of the spin&#x02013;orbit states and corresponding <italic>g</italic>-tensors, therefore only the results obtained for <bold>Ln(1)</bold> within the XMS-CASPT2 level of theory will be discussed here (Tables S21&#x02013;S27<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref>) (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Energies (cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of the lowest energy doublets of <bold>Ln(1)</bold> in <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Compound</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3575</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.9322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.7001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.0824</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.0082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.6344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475.9593</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.1925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.2557</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">348.8809</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1208.0192</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227.7217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372.2061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359.4642</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x02009;479.2524</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228.2524</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.3370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">614.8964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x02009;636.9361</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389.3542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">603.7203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628.4261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#x02009;490.9949</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390.5907</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">793.9510</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">424.9725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">794.4556</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.2938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">912.2663</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447.0406</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">912.3256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">504.8665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1196.5839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516.2164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1196.5971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">522.8741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6103.0014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">537.9741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6106.8661</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540.7899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">565.8972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The ground state electronic structures for <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold> are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13">Fig. 13</xref>. The axial nature of the trigonal prismatic ligand field is expected to be least suitable for stabilizing the largest <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> projections in the latest prolate lanthanide ions (Er<sup>3+</sup>, Tm<sup>3+</sup>, and Yb<sup>3+</sup>). The Er-[1]ferrocenophane compound, <bold>3</bold>, shows highly mixed ground doublets containing <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = &#x000b1;1/2 (24%), &#x000b1;5/2 (23%), and &#x000b1;7/2 (18.7%) character. The first and second excited <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> states for <bold>3</bold> reside only 28 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 52 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> above the ground doublets which contributes to the highly mixed <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> composition and large transverse <italic>g</italic>-tensors (<italic>g</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub>) of <bold>3</bold> (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). These factors contribute to the lack of axial magnetic anisotropy of the ground state and explain the lack of SMM behavior for <bold>3</bold>. For compound <bold>4</bold>, a non-magnetic, <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = 0, ground state is observed and therefore it does not exhibit any magnetic anisotropy. This corresponds well with the direct current magnetic susceptibility data in which the molar magnetic susceptibility temperature product drops to near zero at 2 K. The composition of the ground doublet of the Yb-[1]ferrocenophane compound, <bold>5</bold>, is mostly <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = &#x000b1;7/2 (51%) and &#x000b1;3/2 (11%) character and exhibits large transversal <italic>g</italic>-tensors which leads to a magnetic anisotropy axis which is nearly perpendicular to the principal C<sub>3</sub> axis of the [LnFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> motif. Therefore, the lack of SMM behavior of <bold>5</bold> in the absence of an external magnetic field is not surprising as fast spin relaxation through QTM processes is expected. To this end, the observed slow relaxation under an applied magnetic field suggests that the ground <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = &#x000b1;7/2 doublet becomes purer under an applied field and therefore QTM is at least partially shut down. For <bold>5</bold>, the first excited <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> state lies 121 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> above the ground doublet, therefore if the spin relaxation of <bold>5</bold> under an applied field proceeds <italic>via</italic> an Orbach mechanism through the first excited state, and energy barrier &#x0223c;120 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is likely to be observed under an applied magnetic field. The experimentally extracted spin reversal barrier of 6 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is significantly lower than the energy gap between the ground and first excited state and suggest that spin relaxation proceeds mainly through a second-order Raman and/or direct mechanism.</p><fig id="fig13" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><title>(a) Ground state electronic structure of compounds [TbFc<sub>3</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, [DyFc<sub>3</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, and <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold>. (b) Depiction of the magnetic anisotropy axis of [TbFc<sub>3</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, [DyFc<sub>3</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, <bold>2</bold>, <bold>3</bold>, and <bold>5</bold>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f13"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>The g-tensor of the lowest four doublets of <bold>Ln(1)</bold> in <bold>2&#x02013;5</bold></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2">Doublet</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Compound</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.847</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>y</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.645</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.920</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>y</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.736</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.893</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>y</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.382</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.774</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.736</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.298</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.797</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>y</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.514</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>g</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.797</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.987</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>For the Ho-[1]ferrocenophane compound, <bold>2</bold>, an almost pure <italic>m</italic><sub>j</sub> = &#x000b1;7 ground state is observed and is well stabilized from the first and second excited states by 137 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 228 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. The highly anisotropic ground state leads to an axial magnetic moment vector that resides along the principal {LnFc<sub>3</sub>} C<sub>3</sub> axis explaining the observed SMM behavior of <bold>2</bold>. The magnetic blocking barrier of the <bold>Ho(2)</bold> molecule of <bold>2</bold> was further investigated by following the methodology described in <xref rid="cit66" ref-type="bibr">ref. 66</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14">Fig. 14</xref>). The tunneling gaps between the ground doublets are small which suggests ground state QTM is minimal. Spin relaxation is expected to proceed through the first excited state given the large tunneling gap of 0.77 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The energy of the first excited state (137 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) corresponds remarkably well with the experimentally extracted energy barriers of <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-dilute</bold>, and <bold>2@0.35T</bold> (110&#x02013;131 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><fig id="fig14" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><title>Calculated barrier for magnetization reversal for <bold>Ho(2)</bold>. The doublet states are arranged according to the values of their magnetic moments. The numbers at each arrow show the corresponding matrix element of the transversal magnetic moment, whereas <italic>&#x00394;</italic><sub>tun</sub> is the intrinsic tunneling gap of the corresponding doublet.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d0sc01197e-f14"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We present a detailed analysis of trends in structure and magnetic properties of the remaining members of the family of late Ln-[1]ferrocenophane complexes which all feature exclusively carbon-donors coordinated to trigonal prismatic lanthanide ions. The observed trend of increasing Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angle with decreasing ionic radii of the Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions can be rationalized by simple geometric arguments and considering the structural rigidity of the Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> units. The Ho<sup>3+</sup> complex <bold>2</bold> exhibits slow magnetic relaxation in the absence of applied dc fields, rendering it a rare example of a Ho<sup>3+</sup>-based SMM. Structural modification of the approximate trigonal prismatic coordination environment can be achieved remotely <italic>via</italic> substitution of coordinating solvent molecules to the terminating Li<sup>+</sup> ions. Specifically, an increase in Fc<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> twist angle and deviation from ideal trigonal prismatic geometry is observed in the series <bold>2</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> which is accompanied by a decrease in magnetic relaxation times at a given temperature for the pyridine solvated molecule <bold>2-py</bold>. Taken together our results emphasize the sensitivity of the magnetic structure of Ln<sup>3+</sup> ions in trigonal prismatic coordination environments to the twist angle and provide design guidelines for six-coordinate SMMs.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental section</title><sec><title>General materials and methods</title><p>All syntheses and magnetic sample preparation were carried out under the rigorous exclusion of air and moisture using an ultra-high purity Ar filled glovebox (Vigor) in which the O<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O levels were generally held under 2 ppm and 0.1 ppm, respectively. Tetrahydrofuran, diethyl ether, hexanes, and <italic>n</italic>-pentane were all dried and deoxygenated using a solvent purification system (JC Meyer or Innovative Technologies SPS) and were stored over molecular sieves (<bold>3a</bold>, 8 to 12 mesh) prior to use. Pyridine was dried by stirring over CaH<sub>2</sub> for 24 hours and deoxygenated using freeze&#x02013;pump&#x02013;thaw methods. Prior to use 2-methyl tetrahydrofuran (THF*) was passed through a basic alumina column to remove the butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) stabilizer. Stabilizer free THF* was deoxygenated by purging N<sub>2</sub> gas through the solvent and was dried by refluxing over Na/benzophenone. Anhydrous THF* and pyridine were stored over molecular sieves (<bold>3a</bold>, 8 to 12 mesh). Anhydrous GdCl<sub>3</sub>, HoCl<sub>3</sub>, and ErCl<sub>3</sub> were received as a generous gift from Dr Timothy Hughbanks. Anhydrous TmCl<sub>3</sub> (Millipore Sigma), YbCl<sub>3</sub> (Alfa Aesar), and LuCl<sub>3</sub> (Alfa Aesar) were purchased from commercial sources and were used as received. Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(&#x003b7;<sup>5</sup>-C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="cit67" ref-type="bibr">ref. 67</xref>) and [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][YFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>]<sup><xref rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> were prepared as previously described. Carbon and hydrogen elemental analysis were performed on compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> by Midwest Microlab Inc.</p></sec><sec><title>X-ray crystallography</title><p>Details regarding the structural determination of compounds <bold>1&#x02013;6</bold>, <bold>5Iso</bold>, <bold>6Iso</bold>, <bold>2-THF*</bold>, and <bold>2-py</bold> can be found in the ESI.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#x02020;</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Magnetic characterization</title><p>Samples used for magnetic characterization were prepared by thoroughly crushing the respective paramagnetic species into a microcrystalline powder and subsequently adding between 20&#x02013;40 mg to the bottom of a high purity glass NMR tube along with solid <italic>n</italic>-eicosane (&#x0223c;27&#x02013;65 mg). The NMR tube containing the paramagnetic species/<italic>n</italic>-eicosane mixture was equipped with a gas line adaptor, removed from the glovebox, and was sealed under vacuum on a Schlenk line. To prevent torqueing of small crystallites under high magnetic fields, the solid <italic>n</italic>-eicosane in the sealed sample was melted by heating the sealed tube between 40&#x02013;43 &#x000b0;C in a hot water bath, forming a solid matrix upon cooling to room temperature.</p><p>Magnetic characterization was carried out using a Quantum Design MPMS 3 SQUID magnetometer. The direct current (dc) magnetic susceptibility was measured under a 0.1 <italic>T</italic> magnetic field between 2&#x02013;300 K. A diamagnetic correction (calculated using Pascal's constants) was included in the calculation of the dc molar magnetic susceptibility and considers the diamagnetic response of eicosane and the complex core electrons.<sup><xref rid="cit68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup> The variable temperature magnetization was measured between 2&#x02013;8 K up to external magnetic field strengths of 7 <italic>T</italic>. The alternating current (ac) magnetic susceptibly was measured using a 0.2 mT alternating field between 1&#x02013;1000 Hz using external field strengths of either 0 T, 0.2 <italic>T</italic>, or 0.35 <italic>T</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Synthesis</title><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][GdFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>1</bold>)</title><p>A 20 mL vial was charged with GdCl<sub>3</sub> (0.1590 g; 0.6032 mmols), THF (2 mL), and a magnetic stir bar. The suspension was heated to 45 &#x000b0;C and stirred vigorously for <italic>ca.</italic> 8 hours. The suspension was then added to a vial containing a suspension of Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.6618 g; 0.8011 mmols) in THF (5&#x02013;10 mL), stirred with a glass coated stir bar, forming a cloudy red suspension. The suspension was let stir for 16&#x02013;18 hours upon which the reaction mixture was filtered through Celite. The dark red filtrate was reduced under dynamic vacuum forming a viscid oil which expanded as a sticky solid upon agitation. The red-orange solid was washed with hexanes (4 &#x000d7; 5 mL) and was subsequently dried under vacuum to yield a light orange powder. The crude product was extracted into several washings of Et<sub>2</sub>O (4 &#x000d7; 5 mL) which were filtered through Celite. The Et<sub>2</sub>O filtrate was reduced to dryness under dynamic vacuum and the resulting orange material was dissolved in THF (3&#x02013;5 mL), filtered through Celite, and placed into a pentane vapor diffusion chamber. Pyrophoric plate crystals of 1 formed overnight at &#x02212;27 &#x000b0;C, which were collected by decantation of the mother liquor, washing with pentane (2 &#x000d7; 2 mL), and allowing the crystals to dry under an Ar atmosphere at ambient temperature and pressure (0.2166 g; yield = 31.96%). *In contrast to compounds <bold>2&#x02013;6</bold> and <bold>2-py</bold>, elemental analysis on crystalline material of <bold>1</bold> using commercial analysis services resulted in low C and H values. This discrepancy could be due to the smaller crystals obtained for <bold>1</bold> and resulting increased propensity for desolvation of THF molecules or product decomposition prior to analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2</bold>)</title><p>To a 20 mL vial containing Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.4559 g; 0.552 mmols) in THF (5&#x02013;10 mL) was added solid HoCl<sub>3</sub> (0.1117 g; 0.412 mmols) and an additional THF wash (4&#x02013;5 mL) forming a red suspension. The suspension was let stir for 16&#x02013;18 hours upon which the reaction mixture was filtered through Celite. The dark red filtrate was reduced under dynamic vacuum forming a viscid oil which expanded as a sticky solid upon agitation. The red-orange solid was washed with hexanes (3 &#x000d7; 5 mL) and was subsequently dried under vacuum to yield a light orange powder. The crude product was extracted into several washings of Et<sub>2</sub>O (4 &#x000d7; 5 mL) which were filtered through Celite. The Et<sub>2</sub>O filtrate was reduced to dryness under dynamic vacuum and the resulting orange material was dissolved in THF (3&#x02013;5 mL), filtered through Celite, and placed into a pentane vapor diffusion chamber. Large pyrophoric plate crystals of <bold>2</bold> formed overnight at &#x02212;27 &#x000b0;C, which were collected by decantation of the mother liquor, washing with pentane (2 &#x000d7; 2 mL), and allowing the crystals to dry under an Ar atmosphere at ambient temperature and pressure (0.2555 g; yield = 40.46%) Anal. calcd for C<sub>54</sub>H<sub>72</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>HoLi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (found): C, 55.41 (55.11); H, 6.20 (5.89).</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(Py)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(Py)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-py</bold>)</title><p>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (0.0475 g; 0.0406 mmols) was dissolved in pyridine (1&#x02013;2 mL) forming an orange solution. The solution was filtered through Celite and placed in a vapor diffusion chamber using pentanes as the volatile. Red plate crystals of <bold>2-py</bold> grew over several days at &#x02212;27 &#x000b0;C and were collected by decanting the mother liquor, washing with pentane (2 &#x000d7; 2 mL), and allowing the crystals to dry under an Ar atmosphere at ambient temperature and pressure (yield: 0.0165 g; 31.7%). Anal. calcd. for C<sub>64.38</sub>H<sub>58.38</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>HoLi<sub>3</sub>N<sub>6.88</sub> (found): C, 60.33 (59.29); H, 4.59 (4.54); N, 7.52 (6.62). Anal. calcd. for C<sub>59.38</sub>H<sub>53.38</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>HoLi<sub>3</sub>N<sub>5.88</sub> (found): C, 59.30 (59.29); H, 4.47 (4.54); N, 6.85 (6.62).</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF*)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF*)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-THF*</bold>)</title><p>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (0.1045 g; 0.08928 mmols) was dissolved in 2-methyl THF (2&#x02013;3 mL) forming an orange solution. The solution was filtered through Celite and placed in a vapor diffusion chamber using pentanes as the volatile. Red plate crystals of <bold>2-THF*</bold> along with small amount of orange plates of different morphology grew over 3&#x02013;4 days at &#x02212;27 &#x000b0;C and were collected by decanting the mother liquor, washing with pentane (2 &#x000d7; 2 mL), and allowing the crystals to dry under an Ar atmosphere at ambient temperature and pressure (yield: 0.0838 g; 74.8%). Due to small amounts of an impurity, apparent <italic>via</italic> X-ray crystallography, elemental analysis was not attempted for <bold>2-THF*</bold>.</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][Ho<sub>0.06</sub>Y<sub>0.94</sub>Fc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>2-dilute</bold>)</title><p>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (0.0025 g; 0.0021 mmols) and [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][YFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (0.0353 g; 0.0323 mmols) were weighed in separate vials. [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][YFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] was completely dissolved in THF (2 mL) and the resulting solution was added to solid [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] along with an additional THF wash (1 mL). Upon complete dissolution of [Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][HoFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>], the solution was placed in a pentane 2-dilute grew overnight. The crystals were collected by decantation of the mother liquor, washing with pentane (2 &#x000d7; 2 mL), and allowing the crystals to dry under an Ar atmosphere ambient temperature and pressure (0.0245 g; yield = 65%). Unit cell (110 K): <italic>a</italic> = 11.40 &#x000c5;; <italic>b</italic> = 63.59 &#x000c5;; <italic>c</italic> = 13.74 &#x000c5;; <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 90.00&#x000b0;; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> = 92.26&#x000b0;; <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 90.00&#x000b0;; volume = 9951 &#x000c5;<sup>3</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][ErFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>3</bold>)</title><p>Synthesis analogous to preparation of <bold>2</bold> using ErCl<sub>3</sub> (0.101 g; 0.370 mmols) and Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.407 g; 0.492 mmols) (0.1957 g; yield = 50.07%). Anal. calcd for C<sub>54</sub>H<sub>72</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>ErLi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (found): C, 55.30 (55.03); H, 6.19 (6.06).</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][TmFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>4</bold>)</title><p>Synthesis analogous to preparation of <bold>1</bold> using TmCl<sub>3</sub> (0.0930 g; 0.338 mmols) and Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.3719 g; 0.04502 mmols) (0.2227 g; yield = 91.47%). Anal. calcd for C<sub>54</sub>H<sub>72</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>TmLi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (found): C, 55.22 (55.19); H, 6.18 (6.33).</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][YbFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>5</bold>, <bold>5Iso</bold>)</title><p>Synthesis analogous to preparation of <bold>1</bold> using YbCl<sub>3</sub> (0.1416 g; 0.5068 mmols) and Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.5565 g; 0.6736 mmol). Large plate crystals of <bold>5</bold> along with a smaller amount of brown rod crystals of <bold>5Iso</bold> apparent in product mixture (0.124 g; yield = 20.7% using theoretical yield for pure 5) Anal. calcd for C<sub>54</sub>H<sub>72</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>YbLi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (found): C, 55.03 (54.90); H, 6.16 (6.19).</p></sec><sec><title>[Li(THF)<sub>4</sub>][LuFc<sub>3</sub>(THF)<sub>2</sub>Li<sub>2</sub>] (<bold>6</bold>, <bold>6Iso</bold>)</title><p>Synthesis analogous to preparation of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>5Iso</bold> using LuCl<sub>3</sub> (0.1311 g; 0.4660 mmols) and Li<sub>6</sub>(Fe(C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(TMEDA)<sub>2</sub> (0.5132 g; 0.6212 mmols) (0.1496 g; yield = 27.20% using theoretical yield for pure 6) <sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz, THF-d<sub>8</sub>): <italic>&#x003b4;</italic>(ppm) 4.05 (s, 4H, C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>) 4.09 (s, 4H, C<sub>5</sub>H<sub>4</sub>) Anal. calcd for C<sub>54</sub>H<sub>72</sub>Fe<sub>3</sub>LuLi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (found): C, 54.94 (55.39); H, 6.15 (6.02).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts to declare.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SC-011-D0SC01197E-s001"><label>SC-011-D0SC01197E-s001</label><media xlink:href="SC-011-D0SC01197E-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d24e4719" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SC-011-D0SC01197E-s002"><label>SC-011-D0SC01197E-s002</label><media xlink:href="SC-011-D0SC01197E-s002.cif" orientation="portrait" id="d24e4722" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>M. N. is grateful for support of this project by the National Science Foundation (CHE-1753014) and general financial support through The Welch Foundation (A-1880). V. V. acknowledges the postdoctoral fellowships from the Fonds Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek Vlaanderen (FWO, Flemish Science Foundation). A. U. is grateful to SERB/IUSSTF (India) for a postdoctoral fellowship. We thank Dr Timothy Hughbanks for the generous gift of anhydrous lanthanide salt starting materials.</p></ack><ref-list><title>Notes and references</title><ref id="cit1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gatteschi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessoli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villain</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Molecular Nanomagnets</source>, <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press.</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pineider</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danieli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Totti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorace</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sainctavit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arrio</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cezar</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessoli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>468</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09478</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20981008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20981008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pineider</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sainctavit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danieli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sciancalepore</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talarico</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arrio</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gatteschi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessoli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Mater.</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat2374</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19182788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19182788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunting</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atanasov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damgaard-M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perfetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crassee</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orlita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Slageren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>eaat7319</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aat7319</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30442763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30442763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.6b11043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27936686?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27936686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zadrozny</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atanasov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grandjean</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchem.1630</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23787747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23787747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harriman</surname><given-names>K. L. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brosmer</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungur</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaconescu</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murugesu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>1420</fpage><lpage>1423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.6b12374</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28075128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28075128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winpenny</surname><given-names>R. E. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>16071</fpage><lpage>16074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201609685</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27874236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27874236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ariciu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuna</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>I. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collison</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>E. J. L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winpenny</surname><given-names>R. E. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5SC03111G</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29861976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29861976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungur</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2016</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>2829</fpage><lpage>2837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.5b13584</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26883386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26883386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaizu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2003</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>8694</fpage><lpage>8695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja029629n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12862442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12862442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>G. F. S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>19935</fpage><lpage>19940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.9b11515</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31751131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31751131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClain</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groshens</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furche</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>12967</fpage><lpage>12973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.9b05816</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31375028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClain</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakarawet</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teat</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groshens</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>8492</fpage><lpage>8503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8SC03907K</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30568773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30568773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansikkamaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>1400</fpage><lpage>1403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aav0652</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30337456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Acc. Chem. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1880</fpage><lpage>1889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.accounts.8b00270</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30091896?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30091896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>C. A. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>548</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23447</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28836589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28836589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansikkamaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>11445</fpage><lpage>11449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201705426</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28586163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28586163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winpenny</surname><given-names>R. E. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2013</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>5110</fpage><lpage>5148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr400018q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23550940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23550940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C1SC00513H</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gatteschi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessoli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.200390099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12548682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12548682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guennic</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>3632</fpage><lpage>3639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5SC04510J</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30008995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30008995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajiwara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem.&#x02013;Eur. J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>7428</fpage><lpage>7432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201003538</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21618295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21618295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>7448</fpage><lpage>7451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201004027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20803599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20803599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>13889</fpage><lpage>13896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.7b02010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29111697?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29111697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganivet</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balleseros</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de la Torre</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Juan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem.&#x02013;Eur. J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201202600</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23197446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23197446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takamatsu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>7250</fpage><lpage>7252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic700954t</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17691726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17691726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AlDaman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardonna-Serra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Juan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaita-Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;-Gastaldo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>3467</fpage><lpage>3479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic801630z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19361246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19361246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AlDaman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Juan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;-Gastaldo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaita-Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>8874</fpage><lpage>8875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja801659m</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18558687?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18558687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajeshkumar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajaraman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murugavel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5181</fpage><lpage>5191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6SC00279J</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30155168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30155168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieru</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungur</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernsdorfer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2016</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>5441</fpage><lpage>5450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.6b02638</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27054904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27054904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T. Q.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>X. B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem. Front.</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6QI00028B</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Roy</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korobkov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murugesu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Commun<bold>.</bold></source><year>2014</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1602</fpage><lpage>1604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C3CC48557A</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24419176?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24419176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miehaus</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>17952</fpage><lpage>17957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja4094814</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24188004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24188004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>4730</fpage><lpage>4733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja200198v</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21401130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21401130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorganics</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/inorganics6010016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>7320</fpage><lpage>7323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.7b00952</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28636343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem.&#x02013;Eur. J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>15975</fpage><lpage>15980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201404573</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25297951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25297951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miehaus</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2011</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>8484</fpage><lpage>8489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic201078r</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21834501?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21834501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miehaus</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minasian</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukens Jr</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozimor</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuh</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tyliszczak</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2014</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>6056</fpage><lpage>6068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja501569t</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24650296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24650296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungur</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>10043</fpage><lpage>10056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.6b01353</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27508399?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27508399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit42"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murugesu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Lanthanides and Actinides in Molecular Magnetism</source>, <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Weinheim, Germany</publisher-loc>, <year>2015</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldov&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardonna-Serra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Juan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaita-Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palii</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>12565</fpage><lpage>12574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic302068c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23102271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23102271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latendresse</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuvanesh</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nippe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>8058</fpage><lpage>8061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.7b01499</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28590123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28590123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latendresse</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieru</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>B. O.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuvanesh</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibortaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nippe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2018</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>8164</fpage><lpage>8169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201804075</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29734485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. A: Cryst. Phys., Diffr., Theor. Gen. Crystallogr.</source><year>1976</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0567739476001551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiddiq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komijani</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaita-Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>531</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature16984</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26983539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26983539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>2097</fpage><lpage>2099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.5b00089</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25668635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25668635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olejn&#x000ed;k</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pad&#x0011b;lkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridrichov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hor&#x000e1;&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merna</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x0016f;&#x0017e;i&#x0010d;ka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Organomet. Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>759</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jorganchem.2014.02.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caralho</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domingos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaspar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piresde Matos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Polyhedron</source><year>1992</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1481</fpage><lpage>1488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-5387(00)83141-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit51"><note><p>Unpublished results</p></note></ref><ref id="cit52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernsdorfer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>4996</fpage><lpage>5000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201701480</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28295930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28295930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreiser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westerstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunsch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000e4;mer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decurtins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greber</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem.&#x02013;Eur. J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>13536</fpage><lpage>13540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201403042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25164532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25164532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardona-Serra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Juan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaita-Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cam&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evangelisti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ses&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>14982</fpage><lpage>14990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja305163t</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22894703?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22894703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>14236</fpage><lpage>14239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja206286h</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21838285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21838285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blagg</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuna</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>E. J. L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winpenny</surname><given-names>R. E. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Commun.</source><year>2011</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>10587</fpage><lpage>10589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C1CC14186D</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21881647?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isikawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernsdorfer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2005</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>3650</fpage><lpage>3651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja0428661</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15771471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>C. A. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>18714</fpage><lpage>18724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.7b11535</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29182861?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29182861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>3079</fpage><lpage>3087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic202511n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22356450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22356450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pointillart</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cador</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Guennic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouahab</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Coord. Chem. Rev.</source><year>2017</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2016.12.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Dalton Trans.</source><year>2011</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>9953</fpage><lpage>9963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C1DT10474H</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21829790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>L. T. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Phys. Rev. B: Condens. Matter Mater. Phys.</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>104422</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.104422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Slageren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>6655</fpage><lpage>6669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5CS00222B</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26158197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreiser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weihe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibille</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johannesen</surname><given-names>H. V.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigrist</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rols</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendix</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piligkos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>7600</fpage><lpage>7606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.5b01209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26201004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26201004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galv&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>I. F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angeli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilante</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Autschbach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bokarev</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogdanov</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>et al.</italic>, OpenMolcas: From Source Code to Insight</article-title><source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5925</fpage><lpage>5964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jctc.9b00532</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31509407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31509407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungur</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thewissen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costes</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernsdorfer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chibotaru</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>6328</fpage><lpage>6337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic302568x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23692474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23692474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katcher</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenberg</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Organomet. Chem.</source><year>1971</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-328X(00)80571-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Chem. Educ.</source><year>2008</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ed085p532</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>