<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7202028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179621</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_400993</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.119.400993</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Investigations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Epigenetic Regulation of ABA-Induced Transcriptional Responses in Maize</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6612-3570</contrib-id><name><surname>Vendramin</surname><given-names>Stefania</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4416-7983</contrib-id><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Ji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3655-0130</contrib-id><name><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>Peter A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7114-8454</contrib-id><name><surname>Madzima</surname><given-names>Thelma F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9564-8146</contrib-id><name><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>Karen M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>Department of Biological Science, Florida State University, Tallahassee, Florida 32306</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department of Plant and Microbial Biology, University of Minnesota, St Paul, Minnesota, 55108</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x02021;</label>Division of Biological Sciences, School of STEM, University of Washington Bothell, Bothell, Washington, 98011</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>2</label>Corresponding authors: Division of Biological Sciences, School of STEM, University of Washington Bothell, Bothell, WA 98011. E-mail: <email>madzima@uw.edu</email>. Department of Biological Science, Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL 32306. E-mail: <email>mcginnis@bio.fsu.edu</email></corresp><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>1</label><p>Present address: Center for Genomics and Systems Biology, Department of Biology, New York University, New York NY 10003.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1727</fpage><lpage>1743</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Vendramin <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="1727.pdf"/><abstract><p>Plants are subjected to extreme environmental conditions and must adapt rapidly. The phytohormone abscisic acid (ABA) accumulates during abiotic stress, signaling transcriptional changes that trigger physiological responses. Epigenetic modifications often facilitate transcription, particularly at genes exhibiting temporal, tissue-specific and environmentally-induced expression. In maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>), MEDIATOR OF PARAMUTATION 1 (MOP1) is required for progression of an RNA-dependent epigenetic pathway that regulates transcriptional silencing of loci genomewide. MOP1 function has been previously correlated with genomic regions adjoining particular types of transposable elements and genic regions, suggesting that this regulatory pathway functions to maintain distinct transcriptional activities within genomic spaces, and that loss of MOP1 may modify the responsiveness of some loci to other regulatory pathways. As critical regulators of gene expression, MOP1 and ABA pathways each regulate specific genes. To determine whether loss of MOP1 impacts ABA-responsive gene expression in maize, <italic>mop1-1</italic> and <italic>Mop1</italic> homozygous seedlings were subjected to exogenous ABA and RNA-sequencing. A total of 3,242 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified in four pairwise comparisons. Overall, ABA-induced changes in gene expression were enhanced in <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants. The highest number of DEGs were identified in ABA-induced <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants, including many transcription factors; this suggests combinatorial regulatory scenarios including direct and indirect transcriptional responses to genetic disruption (<italic>mop1-1</italic>) and/or stimulus-induction of a hierarchical, cascading network of responsive genes. Additionally, a modest increase in CHH methylation at putative MOP1-RdDM loci in response to ABA was observed in some genotypes, suggesting that epigenetic variation might influence environmentally-induced transcriptional responses in maize.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Abscisic acid (ABA)</kwd><kwd><italic>Mediator of paramutation1 (Mop1)</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Zea mays</italic></kwd><kwd>epigenetics</kwd><kwd>siRNAs</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="100"/><page-count count="17"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>As sessile organisms, plants must adapt rapidly to fluctuating and often extreme abiotic stress conditions that negatively impact crop productivity and yield, such as water deprivation/drought, high salinity, nutrient deficiency and extreme temperatures. In addition to its role in plant development, the phytohormone abscisic acid (ABA) serves as a critical regulator of plant responses to specific abiotic stresses. ABA responses to environmental stress stimuli result in physiological changes primarily directed to minimize water loss, such as stomatal closure and growth inhibition (reviewed by <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Fujita <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Sah <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Kuromori <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>).</p><p>The signaling events and molecular mechanisms of ABA-mediated responses have been extensively characterized in the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis). Briefly, under specific abiotic stress, ABA binds to a PYRABACTIN RESISTANCE (PYR)/PYR1-LIKE (PYL)/REGULATORY COMPONENT OF ABA RECEPTOR (RCAR) (PYR/PYL/RCAR) receptor complex which inactivates the negative signaling PHOSPHATASE TYPE 2C (PP2C) protein. Receptor binding by ABA and inactivation of PP2C in turn allows for the positive regulator SNF1-RELATED PROTEIN KINASE 2 (SnRK2) to phosphorylate and activate ABSCISIC ACID RESPONSIVE ELEMENT BINDING PROTEIN/BINDING FACTOR (AREB/ABF) transcription factors (TFs) (reviewed by <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). ABA-induced transcription factors regulate many primary target genes by recognizing and binding to specific ABA-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-elements in their promoters. The promoters of ABA-responsive genes are expected to contain two or more copies of a sequence known as an ABA-Responsive Element (ABRE) (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Marcotte <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>) or one ABRE that works in conjunction with a Coupling Element (CE) (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Shen and Ho 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Shen <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>) that function as TF binding sites. TFs that contain these regulatory elements can be transcriptionally induced by ABA and trigger the regulation of primary or secondary ABA target genes. Therefore, transcription factor activation, promoter recognition, and DNA-binding activities are critical downstream ABA-mediated physiological responses to abiotic stress.</p><p>Transcription factor families that mediate plant responses to abiotic stresses include the APETALA2/ethylene-responsive element-binding proteins (AP2/EREBPs), basic leucine zipper (bZIP), Myeloblastosis (MYB), WRKY and No apical meristem, ATAF1 and CUC cup-shaped cotyledon (NAC) proteins (reviewed by <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Hoang <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>). In several documented examples, transgenic plants overexpressing these regulatory proteins exhibit increased stress tolerance phenotypes (reviewed by <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Fujita <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Todaka <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Joshi <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Hoang <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>), demonstrating the utility of manipulating regulatory factors to increase agricultural productivity under extreme environmental conditions.</p><p>Transcription factor binding and transcriptional activation of some abiotic stress-responsive genes relies on alterations to chromatin structure and epigenetic modifications. The relationship between transcription and chromatin remodeling in response to abiotic stress and ABA signaling has recently begun to be appreciated (reviewed by <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Asensi-Fabado <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000e4;mke and B&#x000e4;urle 2017</xref>).</p><p>In plants, RNA-dependent DNA methylation (RdDM) is a specific transcriptional gene-silencing pathway that functions to direct changes in epigenetic modifications and gene expression at target loci (reviewed by <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Matzke <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). The RdDM pathway is reliant on the biogenesis of and response to small non-coding RNAs (sRNAs) through the activity of several proteins, which include two plant-specific DNA-dependent RNA polymerases (Pol IV and Pol V), an RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RDR), a Dicer-like protein, an Argonaute-complex, DNA modifying enzymes to induce cytosine methylation, ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling complexes, and other accessory proteins (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Matzke and Mosher 2014</xref>).</p><p>In maize, MEDIATOR OF PARAMUTATION 1 (MOP1), an ortholog of the Arabidopsis RDR2 (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Dorweiler <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Alleman <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), interacts with Pol IV (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Haag <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) and is required for Pol IV-dependent sRNA biogenesis and progression of the RdDM pathway. A Pol IV-MOP1-dependent pathway maintains chromatin boundaries between protein-coding genes and gene-proximal transposable elements (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2015a</xref>). The <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutation results in a reduction of 24-nt siRNAs and a loss in DNA methylation at certain loci, particularly in the CHH context (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Lisch <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">Woodhouse <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Nobuta <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>); this mutant stock has proven to be a valuable genetic resource and has been used extensively to characterize Pol IV-mediated RdDM activities across the maize genome (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Nobuta <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2015a</xref>). Nonetheless, the identification of MOP1 and RdDM targets is not a straight-forward task, because multiple factors contribute to MOP1 target specificity and loss of gene silencing, which initiates a cascade of transcriptional and epigenetic changes that complicate the distinction between MOP1 direct and indirect targets.</p><p>Cytosine DNA methylation is important in many biological processes including regulation of transposon silencing and expression of endogenous genes, plant development, and environmental-stress responses (<xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). In plants, this conserved epigenetic mark occurs in symmetric (CG, CHG) and asymmetric contexts (CHH); in which H can be A,T, or C) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Henderson and Jacobsen 2007</xref>). CG and CHG methylation is maintained throughout DNA replication by METHYLTRANSFERASE 1 (MET1) and CHROMOMETHYLASE 3 (CMT3) respectively (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Niederhuth and Schmitz 2017</xref>). Asymmetric methylation can be established by DOMAINS REARRANGED METHYLASE 1/2 (DRM1/2) through the RdDM pathway (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Law and Jacobsen 2010</xref>).</p><p>The majority of the maize genome is composed of transposons (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Schnable <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), which are mostly methylated in a symmetrical context (<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">West <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). On a genome-wide scale, methylated CHH sites are observed at significantly lower levels than methylated CG and CHG sites, however, regions of elevated CHH methylation are observed upstream of the transcription start sites of genes (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). These RdDM-dependent CHH methylation sites coincide with the presence of specific classes of transposons found within 1 kb of many maize genes (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Regulski <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2015a</xref>).</p><p>In Arabidopsis, four glycosylases have been characterized as functioning in active DNA demethylation by initiating removal of methylated cytosines from DNA via base excision repair: REPRESSOR OF SILENCING 1 (ROS1), DEMETER (DME), DME-like 2 (DML2) and DML3 (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Choi <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agius <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gehring <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Morales-Ruiz <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Penterman <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). ROS1 has been shown to act through an auto-regulatory, coordinated RdDM-demethylation based response (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Lei <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). At some loci, maintenance of transcription appears to be dependent on RdDM activity, which challenges the canonical model of RdDM-mediated transcriptional repression. ROS1 was also recently shown to be required for transcriptional activation of specific ABA-inducible genes in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2019</xref>). The maize DNG103 is highly similar to Arabidopsis ROS1. As reported with <italic>Ros1</italic> in Arabidopsis RdDM mutants (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Huettel <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), <italic>Dng103</italic> is downregulated in maize RdDM mutants (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Erhard <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Transcriptional repression of <italic>Dng103</italic> in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants likely induces other expression changes that cannot be directly attributed to loss of MOP1 activity.</p><p>Plant responses to abiotic stress are multifaceted, integrating multiple environmental cues and biological response mechanisms. These complex mechanisms must be understood to maximize stress tolerance in plants. As both MOP1 and ABA signaling networks act as key regulators of gene expression, characterizing these responses and identifying overlap between the two processes will provide a wealth of information about the mechanisms of stress response in crop plants and candidate pathways to enhance stress response under different agricultural conditions. In this study, we use RNA- and sequence-capture bisulfite sequencing of ABA-induced <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant and wildtype <italic>Mop1</italic> seedlings to identify MOP1-dependent, ABA-induced genes.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) plants were grown in 2.8 cu. ft potting soil (10-gal coarse sand:400 ml 18.6.12 slow release fertilizer) in greenhouse conditions (16 h light period, 25&#x000b0;, 50% humidity) until they reached the V3 stage (RNA-seq) or ten-day old seedlings (methylation). The <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutation was from genetic stocks from J. Dorweiler of the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutation introgressed into the B73 reference genome and backcrossed for seven generations (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). For this study, progeny resulting from the self-pollination of an ear of a heterozygous plant was used. Only homozygous wildtype and homozygous mutant siblings were used.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Plant genotyping</title><p>The <italic>Mop1/mop1-1</italic> segregating family was genotyped under the following PCR conditions: 94&#x000b0; for 5 min (1x&#x0223c;; 95&#x000b0; for 30 s, 56&#x000b0; for 45 s, 72&#x000b0; for 45 s (30x); 72&#x000b0; for 10 min (1x); hold for 4&#x000b0; (as needed); using the following primers as previously described (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima, Huang, &#x00026; Mcginnis 2014</xref>):</p><p>KM384: (5&#x02032;-TCTCCACCGCCCACTTGAT-3&#x02032;);</p><p>KM385: (5&#x02032;-CCCAAGAGCT GTCTCGTATCCGT-3&#x02032;);</p><p>KM386: (5&#x02032; -CTTCATCTCGAAGTAGCGCTTGTTGTCC-3&#x02032;).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Abscisic acid treatment in seedlings</title><p>ABA concentrations used in maize seedling studies range from 1 to 150 &#x000b5;M, and 50 &#x000b5;M is commonly used in stage V3 seedlings (&#x0223c;2 weeks old) (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fan <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Phillips and Ludidi 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Belda-Palazon <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">He <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">He <italic>et al.</italic> 2019</xref>). Maize seedlings at the V3 stage were removed from the soil, roots were rinsed in water, dried, and then submerged in a 1 L beaker with 250 mL of liquid Murashige and Skoog (MS) media (Sigma Aldrich, M6899) with 50 &#x003bc;M ABA (ABA; (Sigma Aldrich, (+/&#x02212;) Abscisic Acid, A1049)) or without ABA (MS) for 7 and 8 hr (methylation and RNA-seq, respectively) in greenhouse conditions (16 h light period, 25&#x000b0;, 50% humidity). After the incubation period, roots where removed and seedlings were immediately flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80&#x000b0; until use. Homozygous wildtype (<italic>Mop1</italic> WT) and homozygous <italic>mop1</italic> mutant (<italic>mop1-1</italic>) individuals were used.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Total RNA isolation</title><p>Frozen seedling tissue was finely ground into powder in liquid nitrogen and homogenized before total RNA extraction was performed using TRI reagent according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Molecular Research Center, 18080-051). RNA samples were DNase treated (RQ1 RNase-Free DNase, Promega, M6101) and purified using RNA clean &#x00026; concentrator 25 (Zymo Research, R1018). The integrity and quality of the total RNA was checked by a NanoDrop 1000 spectrophotometer and by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>RNA library preparation, RNA-sequencing and read alignment</title><p>Three biological replicates were used for all RNA-seq experiments for each treatment and genotype, for a total of 12 samples. The final sample concentration was quantified by Qubit. RNA library preparation (NEBNext Ultra II kit, NEB, E7760) and Illumina paired-end 150 bp (PE 150) sequencing were performed by Novogene Corporation (Sacramento, California). More than 20 million reads were obtained per library, FASTQ adapters were trimmed by Cutadapt 1.8.1 (<xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Martin 2011</xref>) and quality control was performed using FASTQC v0.11.2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>). Reads were mapped to the B73 maize genome (AGP B73v4) (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Jiao <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>) by HISAT2 v2.04 (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Pertea <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). Transcripts were assembled <italic>de novo</italic> to allow for inclusion of transcripts that are not included in the reference genome annotation and quantified using StringTie v1.3.4d (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Pertea <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). Gene count matrices were generated from this data using the prepDE.py python script available in the StringTie website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/index.shtml?t=manual">http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/index.shtml?t=manual</ext-link>). These matrices were used by the Bioconductor package edgeR 3.20.9 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>) in R for differential expression analysis in order to identify upregulated and downregulated genes for the four different genotypes under two treatments. Low-abundance counts of &#x0003c; 0.58 cpm were removed using the DESeq2 filtering method (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="statquest.org/2017/05/16/statquest-filtering-genes-with-low-read-counts/">statquest.org/2017/05/16/statquest-filtering-genes-with-low-read-counts/</ext-link>); (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Love <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) incorporated into the edgeR pipeline, and genes with an adjusted p-value of &#x02264; 0.05 and an absolute log<sub>2</sub> fold change (FC) value of &#x02265; 0.95 were considered as differentially expressed for both upregulated and downregulated genes.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Reverse Transcription Quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) analysis of transcript abundance</title><p>Reverse Transcription Quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) was performed for all 12 RNA samples to confirm an induction of ABA treatment by measuring the expression of <italic>Responsive to ABA</italic> 17 (<italic>Rab17)</italic> (<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Vilardell <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>) in maize seedlings. The well characterized ABA and stress-responsive maize gene <italic>Viviparous1</italic> (<italic>Vp1</italic>) (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Cao <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) was used as a negative control, since it is only ABA-responsive in maize embryos, and <italic>Ubiquitin conjugase</italic> was used as a control. <italic>Rab17</italic> qPCR primers KM1634 (5&#x02032;-TCCTTGATTCCCTTCTTCCTC-3&#x02032;) and KM1635 (5&#x02032;-GAGGGAGGAGCACAAGACC-3&#x02032;), <italic>Vp1</italic> qPCR primers KM1465 (5&#x02032;- CCGATGTCAAGTCGGGCAAATATC-3&#x02032;) and KM1466 (5&#x02032;-TGGAACCACTGCCTTGCTCTTG-3&#x02032;), and <italic>Ubiquitin conjugase</italic> KM633 (5&#x02032;- GACTACACGATGGAGAACATCCTAACCC-3&#x02032;) and KM634 (5&#x02032;- GAAGAATGTCCCTTCTGGAGGCTGC-3&#x02032;) were used.</p><p>RT-qPCR was performed for 11 of the 12 RNA samples (excluding a wild type control that had atypical expression patterns and was therefore excluded as an outlier) to measure gene expression of <italic>Dng101</italic> (Zm000010a020199), <italic>Dng103</italic> (Zm00001d038302), and <italic>Dng105</italic> (Zm00001d016521). The following qPCR primers were used for <italic>Dng101</italic>, KM1656 (5&#x02032;-CTTCTGCTCTTGCTGCTCCA-3&#x02032;) and KM1657 (5&#x02032;-CGACTGAAGAGATA CAACGATGC-3&#x02032;), <italic>Dng103</italic> KM1467 (5&#x02032;- ACCATGCTGTGACCCTCAAATGG-3&#x02032;) and KM1468 (5&#x02032;- CATAGCTGTTCGACAAGGAACCAG-3&#x02032;), and <italic>Dng105</italic> KM1658 (5&#x02032;-GGCAAGATATACAGGAATGCTTGA-3&#x02032;) and KM1659 (5&#x02032;- CGATGTCCTAGTCCGCTTCA -3&#x02032;). <italic>Ubiquitin conjugase</italic> was used as a control amplified by primers KM63 5&#x02032;- GACTACACGATGGAGAACATCCTAACCC-3&#x02032;) and KM634 (5&#x02032;- GAAGAATGTCCCTTCTGGAGGCTGC-3&#x02032;).</p><p>First-strand cDNA synthesis and RT-qPCR were performed by Florida State University&#x02019;s Biology Molecular Core Facility. First-strand cDNA synthesis was performed by reverse transcribing 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA with Oligo(dT)<sub>20</sub> primers according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (SuperScriptTM III Reverse Transcriptase, Invitrogen, 18080-051). Reverse transcriptase quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) was performed using an Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System and SYBR Green reagents (Thermofisher Scientific). The generation of specific PCR products was confirmed by melting curve analysis. Primers were designed using MaizeGDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="maizegdb.org">maizegdb.org</ext-link>) and Net Primer Analysis Software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="premierbiosoft.com/netprimer/">premierbiosoft.com/netprimer/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>DNA methylation library construction, sequencing, and analysis</title><p>High molecular weight genomic DNA was isolated from above ground tissue of maize 10-day old seedlings using a standard CTAB protocol. Sequence capture library construction used 0.5-1 &#x003bc;g of genomic DNA as previously described by (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2015b</xref>). Adapters were trimmed using Trim Galore! (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</ext-link>). Reads were aligned to maize genome version 4 (AGPv4) using <italic>BSMAP-2.90</italic> (-v 5 -q 20) (<xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Xi &#x00026; Li 2009</xref>) and uniquely mapped reads were processed as described previously (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Han <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>) The unmethylated chloroplast genome was used to determine cytosine conversion rate. The methylation ratio (number of reads that were methylated and unmethylated) was determined for each methylation context by the weighted DNA methylation method (#C / (#C + #T)) using <italic>BSMAP</italic> tools. BEDTools and overlapping reads were used to determine read coverage for target regions.</p><p>Genome-wide methylation changes were determined by assessing regions with a minimum of 5x coverage and 2 methylation sites, and methylation levels of 10% for CG and CHG contexts and 1% for the CHH context. Methylation % difference was calculated by the equation: ((Genotype/Treatment 1 mC% - Genotype/Treatment 2 mC%) / (Genotype/Treatment 2)).</p><p>Promoter regions of DEGs were defined as the 2 kb region upstream from the transcription start site. This 2000 bp region was divided into 100 bp tiles for further methylation analysis. Tiles with no data were removed and not counted for the final average mC level. Coverage was calculated using DNA methylation data in 100 bp tiles. Methylation percentage was defined as [treatment &#x02013; control] x100. For average methylation % in the promoter region of DEGs, a minimum of 2x coverage, 2 methylation sites, 10% methylation for CG/CHG and 1% for CHH was used.</p><p>Pairwise comparisons for <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA <italic>vs.</italic>
<italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS (Figure 6, comparison A) and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant MS <italic>vs.</italic>
<italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS (Figure 6, comparison D) were correlated with genes in Group I and II, and Groups III, IV, V and VI from RNA-Seq results, respectively. Differentially methylated promoters were identified by comparisons where there was an absolute methylation difference (Genotype/Treatment 1 mC% - Genotype/Treatment mC 2%) of &#x02265; 40% in the CG/CHG context; in the CHH context where one Genotype/Treatment sample showed a methylation level of &#x02264; 5% and between comparisons a methylation % difference higher than &#x02265;15%. A region with &#x02265;10% methylation increase in the CG context was defined as having CG hypermethylation.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Gene ontology analysis</title><p>Gene ontology (GO) (Plant GO Slim) analysis was conducted using the web-based tool agriGO v2.0 (<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Tian <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>), incorporating AGOv4 IDs into a Single Enrichment Analysis (SEA) using the Fisher&#x02019;s statistical test, Hochberg (FDR) multi-test adjustment method with a significance level of &#x0003c; 0.05 and minimum number of mapping entries of 10 genes per GO-term. The GO term enrichment was generated by hierarchically clustering the log10 of the total GO term percentage of a set of genes that were upregulated or downregulated in wildtype or mutant in response to ABA (Table S4).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Alignment and overlap of 24 nt siRNA and promoter proximal regions of DEGs</title><p>Using publicly available data from NCBI&#x02019;s Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO, GSE68510; (<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>)) from (<italic>Mop1</italic>/<italic>mop1-1</italic>) wildtype and mutant (<italic>mop1-1</italic>/<italic>mop1-1</italic>) maize young cob small RNA raw reads were processed for 24-nt siRNA alignment and comparison. The TruSeq Small RNA 3&#x02032; adapter (RA3) sequences were removed from the raw reads using Cutadapt (<xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Martin 2011</xref>) and quality of the reads was assessed before and after the trimming using FASTQC v0.11.2 (bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/). Alignment of the reads was performed by ShortStack v3 (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>) using default parameters. Using the (.bam) alignment files generated by ShortStack v3 and the chromosomal location of the 2 kb region upstream of the transcription start site (TSS) (downloaded using biomart ensembl plants) (ShortStack specified parameter:&#x02013;loci) of all protein coding genes in <italic>Zea mays</italic> (B73 RefGen_v4), the promoter proximal regions of these genes were assessed for the presence of 24 nt siRNAs. Differential 24 nt siRNA targeting between <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant in this 2 Kb region upstream of TSS was calculated with edgeR 3.20.9 (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Robinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Mccarthy <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) after removal of low-abundance regions and library normalization. Further normalization was performed to the foldchange of 2.2 (log<sub>2</sub> of 1.13), calculated using the abundances of the undisturbed expression of high-confidence maize miRNAs from miRbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/cgi-bin/mirna_summary.pl?org=zma">http://www.mirbase.org/cgi-bin/mirna_summary.pl?org=zma</ext-link>; B73_RefGen_v4) in the mutant and wildtype (miRNA abundances in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant/miRNA abundances in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype; Table S4, File S6).</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>ABA-response transcription factor network</title><p>Based on the Arabidopsis ABA-responsive transcription factor hierarchical network built using chromatin immunoprecipitated (ChIP) data (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>) maize orthologs for the genes present in the network were identified using a list generated by blasting maize proteins against TAIR 10 protein sequences using standalone BLASTP version 2.2.28+ 581 (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) (File S3). Gene targets for transcription factors located in every level or tier were predicted using a tissue-specific gene regulatory network in seed, SAM, root and leaf maize tissues (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bio.fsu.edu/mcginnislab/mgrn/">https://www.bio.fsu.edu/mcginnislab/mgrn/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>) and were represented as edges. Nodes represent the log<sub>2</sub>FC of these genes in our dataset (Figure S5).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Motif discovery and enrichment analysis</title><p>The Multiple Expectation Maximization (EM) for Motif Elicitation (MEME) tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme-suite.org">http://meme-suite.org</ext-link>) version 5.0.4 was used to search for the presence of any conserved domains among the ABA-response transcription factor network built from our dataset. The promoter sequences of 47 genes were used with the following parameters: -dna -mod anr -revcomp -minw 5 -maxw 10 -nmotifs 10 -evt 0.05. A motif highly similar to the maize ABRE was found in 66% of these genes. Find Individual Motif Occurrences (FIMO) version 5.0.5 was used to identify ABA-responsive genes in other sets of DEGs. Motif enrichment was performed using the previously-found putative ABRE motif (CACG[TC]G[TG]C[GC]) as input. Primary ABA targets were defined as genes that were differentially expressed in response to ABA and that contained at least two ABRE sites in their promoter or one ABRE site and a coupling element (CE).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Transposable element enrichment analysis</title><p>Bedtools &#x02018;closest&#x02019; tool was used to identify enriched TEs adjacent to the 2 kb upstream or 2 kb downstream DNA region of DEGs from groups V and VI (File S10). Gene annotations from the differentially expressed genes of interest were extracted from the B73 Refgen_v4 genome assembly (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Jiao <italic>Et Al</italic>., 2017</xref>) using EnsemblPlants BioMart (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="plants.ensembl.org/biomart/">plants.ensembl.org/biomart/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Kinsella <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The transposable element (TE) annotation file used was downloaded from github (B73.structuralTEv2.2018.12.20.filteredTE.gff3.gz; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SNAnderson/maizeTE_variation">https://github.com/SNAnderson/maizeTE_variation</ext-link>). The percentage distribution of transposable element families in the B73 genome was calculated using from data from previously published studies (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s14"><title>Data availability</title><p>All RNA-sequencing and Bisulfite-Sequencing data are available at the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Gene Expression Omnibus (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Edgar <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>) through GEO Series accession number GSE132167.</p><p>Figure S1: Rab17 RT-qPCR</p><p>Figure S2: MDS clustering</p><p>Figure S3: DNG RT-qPCR</p><p>Figure S4: <italic>Mop1</italic> WT and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant promoter methylation for DEGs and non-DEGs</p><p>Figure S5: Heatmap (Log2 FC) of TF Network DEGs</p><p>Table S1: DEGs no. for DE analysis using different biological replicates no.</p><p>Table S2: Maize protein phosphatases class A (<italic>PP2C</italic>-A)</p><p>Table S3: Number of GO terms found for DEGs in four groups</p><p>Table S4: High-confidence miRNAs</p><p>File S1: Groups I-VII log2FC</p><p>File S2: GO term enrichment per DEG group</p><p>File S3: Homologous TFs</p><p>File S4: Tiers and Downstream genes</p><p>File S5: Group model parameters per gene</p><p>File S6: Genome-wide siRNA changes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</p><p>File S7: SeqCap DNA methylation ratios in all sequence contexts</p><p>File S8: Promoter DNA methylation for <italic>Mop1</italic> Wildtype ABA-responsive DEGs</p><p>File S9: MOP1-ABA targets with a loss of siRNA and DNA methylation at ABRE sites</p><p>File S10: TE enrichment in a subset of genes in Groups V and VI.</p><p>Supplemental material available at figshare: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25387/g3.9626636">https://doi.org/10.25387/g3.9626636</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s15"><title>Results</title><sec id="s16"><title>Canonical abiotic stress associated genes are transcriptionally responsive to ABA in wildtype and mop1-1 maize seedlings</title><p>To determine the combined effects of MOP1 and ABA on gene expression in maize, homozygous wildtype (<italic>Mop1</italic>) and mutant (<italic>mop1-1)</italic> individuals from a segregating family of seedlings at vegetative stage 3 (V3) from a self-pollinated <italic>Mop1/mop1-1</italic> ear were subjected to treatment with ABA. Induction was confirmed by measuring the expression of the <italic>Responsive to ABA 17 (Rab17)</italic> gene (Figure S1), which encodes a putative dehydrin protein and has been the subject of study for ABA- and osmotic stress-responsiveness. Upregulation of <italic>Rab17</italic> expression is well-documented in several transcriptomic studies measuring responses to ABA and drought in maize embryos (<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Vilardell <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Goday <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>) and vegetative tissues (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Vilardell <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Busk and Pages 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) as well as in drought studies in sorghum leaves at the seedling stage (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Reverse transcription and quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) of <italic>Rab17</italic> confirmed that the ABA-treatment of V3 seedlings was sufficient to induce changes in gene expression (Figure S1).</p><p>RNA from these ABA-induced and control genotypes was subjected to cDNA library preparation, RNA-sequencing and transcriptome analysis. An average of &#x0223c;23 million 150 bp paired end raw reads were obtained per sample and mapped to the B73 reference genome (AGP B73v4) (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Jiao <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>). Mapped reads were used in subsequent analysis (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Multidimensional scaling (MDS) was performed to determine the relationship between genotype and treatment for the 12 homozygous <italic>Mop1</italic> and <italic>mop1-1</italic> samples, with the majority clustering according to genotype and treatment (Figure S2). One biological replicate of a <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype sample that was not treated with ABA clustered with the wildtype ABA-treated samples. This suggests non-experimental endogenous induction of ABA in this seedling, perhaps related to a stress response induced in this individual under control treatment conditions. Due to evidence of an ABA-induced response, this sample was removed from further analysis and only two replicates for the wildtype control were used. The removal of wt_m1_ms_3 did not affect the proportion of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) found in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant in response to ABA when compared to <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype (Table S1).</p><table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Summary of RNA-seq libraries per genotype and treatment</title></caption><table frame="void" rules="groups"><col width="10.59%" span="1"/><col width="11.43%" span="1"/><col width="10.3%" span="1"/><col width="10.3%" span="1"/><col width="10.3%" span="1"/><col width="10.3%" span="1"/><col width="11.77%" span="1"/><col width="10.3%" span="1"/><col width="14.71%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Replicate</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total raw reads</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clean reads</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mapped reads</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Mapped reads</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniquely mapped reads</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Uniquely mapped reads</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22307497</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22181351</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19983179</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.09</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17478905</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22220268</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22103764</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19606039</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.70</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17123786</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25460004</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25345274</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22656140</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.39</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20020232</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22263417</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22135607</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19700690</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.00</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17356529</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23131739</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23008377</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20776564</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.30</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18613777</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21771139</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21657574</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19680237</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.87</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17650923</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24469219</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24316810</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21753818</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.46</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19001155</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24142476</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23989219</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22240405</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.71</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20196523</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">control</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23023844</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22878557</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19890617</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.94</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17579883</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21775951</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21606778</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19832862</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.79</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18099998</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22373108</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22282587</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20183567</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.58</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17919656</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABA</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21583557</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21464462</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19414606</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.45</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17055662</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.46</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1n1"><label>a</label><p>Removed from analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Significant DEGs were identified in four pairwise comparisons as genes with a twofold expression change (log<sub>2</sub> FC &#x02265; 0.95, FDR &#x0003c; 0.05) (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The DEGs in the four comparisons were further sub-divided into eight analysis groups based on gene expression patterns identified by making direct comparisons between genotypes and treatments (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; File S1). For example, by comparing expression in wildtype plants in the presence and absence of ABA treatment, ABA-induced (Group I) and ABA-repressed (Group II) genes were detected. The total number of DEGs identified in all eight groups was 3,242 genes; however, 1,681 genes were found to be common to more than one analysis group, resulting in 1,561 DEGs unique to an individual analysis group (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><italic>)</italic>. Analysis of the individual groups of unique DEGs revealed relationships between ABA-responsiveness and MOP1-mediated effects on transcriptional regulation in maize (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Differentially expressed gene categories and analysis groups</title></caption><table frame="void" rules="groups"><col width="11.85%" span="1"/><col width="9.21%" span="1"/><col width="13.15%" span="1"/><col width="14.79%" span="1"/><col width="12.76%" span="1"/><col width="12.31%" span="1"/><col width="12.15%" span="1"/><col width="13.78%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pair-wise comparison</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis group</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression pattern</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref> DEGs</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2FC Significant <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref> DEGs</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Significant <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref> DEGs</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total 2FC Significant <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref> DEGs</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA / <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">606</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">506</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">1028</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">858</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1">ABA response in wildtype</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">downregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">422</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">352</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant MS / <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">173</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">173</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1">Response to loss of RdDM</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">downregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant ABA / <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant MS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1511</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">965</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">3118</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">1959</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1">ABA response in RdDM deficient mutant</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">VI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">downregulated</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1607</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">994</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant ABA / <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VII</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="char" char="." colspan="1">252</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1">Differential ABA-response in RdDM deficient mutant compared to wildtype</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">VIII</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">downregulated</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="5" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Total DEGs</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4575</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="5" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Number of DEGs in more than one analysis group</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2091</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="5" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Number of DEGs in only one analysis group</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2484</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1561</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2n1"><label>a</label><p>Significant genes are DEGs with a p-value and FDR &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Genome-wide differential gene expression with log<sub>2</sub> FC &#x02265; 0.95, FDR &#x0003c; 0.05. (a) Venn Diagram showing the overlap of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) specifying upregulated (black, italics), contra-regulated or genes that have diverse regulation polarity (red), and downregulated (black, underlined) genes in four pair-wise-comparisons. The Venn Diagram was generated using Vennplex (<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Cai <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). (b) Distribution of significant differential gene expression log2 fold change (FC) in four comparisons. Boxes encompass the upper and lower quartile log2 FC, the middle line depicts the median, the cross represents the mean, the whiskers show the maximum and minimum log2 FC values, and the dots outside the whiskers show the outliers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1727f1"/></fig><p>In summary, several well-documented, abiotic-stress-associated responses were found to be ABA responsive in wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants (Groups I and V; File S1). In addition to <italic>Rab17</italic>, notable examples include twelve of the twenty maize <italic>Protein Phosphatase 2C-like class</italic>, <italic>group A (PP2C-A)</italic> genes (Table S2) that are known to act as negative regulators of ABA signaling in Arabidopsis and other plant species (reviewed by <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>Many of the DEGs identified in untreated <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants relative to untreated <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype (Groups III and IV) are comparable to published <italic>mop1-1</italic> expression datasets (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) in spite of tissue-specific expression differences that likely exist between these studies. The maize <italic>Dng103</italic> (Zm00001d038302) gene, an ortholog of the Arabidopsis DNA glycosylase gene <italic>Repressor of silencing1</italic> (<italic>Ros1</italic>) (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Morales-Ruiz <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), has been shown to be downregulated in <italic>mop1-1</italic> shoot apical meristems (SAMs) (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), immature ears (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and leaves (<xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Based on our expression criteria for DEGs, <italic>Dng103</italic> did not appear in Group IV as was expected, however, downregulation of <italic>Dng103</italic> in <italic>mop1-1</italic> seedlings was confirmed by RT-qPCR (Figure S3). Interestingly, <italic>Dng103</italic> expression was highly variable across biological replicates, and the gene appears to be upregulated in response to exogenous ABA application in wildtype but not <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants (Figure S3).</p><p>Genes identified in Groups I and II (ABA-responsive in WT) and Groups III and IV (MOP1-dependent) are similar to previously reported transcriptomic studies of ABA in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Seki <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Matsui <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>) and MOP1 in maize (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>)]. Therefore, we focus herein on the novel findings of their combined regulation, identified predominantly through analysis of Groups V-VIII DEGs (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Loss of MOP1 amplifies ABA transcriptional responses in maize seedlings</title><p>The largest numbers of DEGs from all eight analysis groups were observed in Groups V and VI (representing 60% of all DEGs), which were identified by comparing expression in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants exposed to exogenous ABA relative to untreated mutant siblings. Groups V and VI include 965 and 994 up- and downregulated genes, respectively (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Of the 1959 DEGs, one-third of these (658 genes) were also differentially expressed in wildtype plants in response to exogenous ABA (Groups I and II) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), suggesting that these are ABA-dependent genes. When comparing the magnitude of effect of ABA exposure on gene expression, both genotypes exhibit a similar average and distribution of fold-change in response to ABA treatment (Groups I, II, V, and VI; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). However, a much larger number of genes meet the significance and fold-change thresholds established for these analysis groups in <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants compared to wildtype. This results in &#x0223c;2x more upregulated genes and &#x0223c;3x more downregulated genes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant plants when compared to <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype plants (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that the loss of MOP1 amplifies genome-wide ABA-induced changes in gene expression in maize.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>In the absence of MOP1, ABA induces differential expression of a unique subset of genes and distinct functional categories</title><p>A direct comparison of the ABA response in homozygous <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants <italic>vs.</italic> wildtype allows for the identification of 252 genes that are differentially expressed between these two genotypes in the presence of exogenous ABA (Groups VII and VIII; <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Specifically, there were 194 up- and 58 downregulated DEGs in ABA-treated <italic>mop1-1</italic> compared to wildtype. Of these 252 genes, 128 were also included in Groups III and IV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), indicating that these genes were differentially expressed in <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants in a similar manner with or without ABA treatment.</p><p>Of the 252 genes, one third (88 genes) were uniquely differentially expressed in these groups and not detected by other comparisons. These 88 genes would not have been identified as differentially expressed if gene expression had not been analyzed in the absence of MOP1 and the presence of ABA simultaneously. Genes in this category include specific members of the abiotic stress-responsive LATE EMBRYOGENESIS ABUNDANT (LEA), dehydrins, Glucosyltransferase/Rab-like GTPase activator/Myotubularin (GRAM) and VQ gene families that were uniquely upregulated in response to ABA in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The unique expression patterns of genes with predicted physiological and developmental roles suggests that plants experiencing a loss of MOP1 together with the induction of ABA responses may have biological consequences. To explore this further, the identity and predicted function of DEGs across the different analysis groups were characterized.</p><table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Abiotic stress-responsive LEA, Dehydrins, GRAM and VQ genes uniquely upregulated in response to ABA in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</title></caption><table frame="border" rules="groups"><col width="26.92%" span="1"/><col width="29.83%" span="1"/><col width="22.13%" span="1"/><col width="21.12%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="4" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> Mutant Unique</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Family</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub>FC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Late Embryogenesis Abundant (LEA)</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryonic protein DC-8</td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d002360</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEA5-D-like</td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d040659</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative desiccation-related protein <italic>LEA14</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d009700</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032620</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Dehydrins</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dhn3</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d051420</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>COR410</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017547</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">GRAM</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d023664</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032636</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">VQ</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ZmVQ13</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d00208</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ZmVQ29</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d015397</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ZmVQ53</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d046961</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ZmVQ58</italic></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d023269</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Gene ontology (GO) analysis was used to predict the biological processes (BP) of annotated genes in each of the 8 analysis groups. Only genes from Groups I, II, V, and VI met the enrichment criteria for GO analysis (see Methods). More than 85% of the genes were annotated in these groups, resulting in 17 GO terms for Group I, 11 for Group II, 22 for Group V and 28 for Group VI (Table S4).</p><p>Consistent with response to ABA induction, the most prevalent GO term present across all four groups was &#x02018;response to stimulus&#x02019; (GO:0050896; FDR &#x02264; 7E-05; File S2). Noteably, Group VI genes, which are downregulated in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous seedlings treated with ABA, were enriched with unique diverse GO terms such as growth, development, and reproduction, when compared to the other three groups (FDR &#x02264; 0.049; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). The enrichment of development-related genes that are differentially expressed between mutants and wildtype may be related to the pleiotropic developmental defective phenotypes observed in <italic>mop1-1</italic> and the many genes mis-regulated as a consequence of the loss of MOP1 activity (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Dorweiler <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Jia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Enriched biological process Gene Ontology (GO) terms in differentially expressed genes (DEGs) (File S2). Comparisons were made between analysis Groups I, II, V, and VI (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Hierarchical clustering of log<sub>10</sub> (% genes) of significant GO terms enriched in each expression comparison (FDR &#x0003c; 0.05, minimum of 10 genes per GO term). No color (white) shows no particular GO term enrichment in the dataset.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1727f2"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Hierarchically organized transcription factors are uniquely differentially expressed in response to ABA in the mop1-1 genotype</title><p>The amplified response to ABA observed in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants might be due to the combined consequences of direct and indirect effects. MOP1 and ABA treatment might each directly induce a subset of transcriptional changes that in turn activate a cascade of additional responses in maize. Transcription factors (TFs) are key regulators of the transcriptional activity of genes involved in networks that are fundamental for plant growth and development, as well as responses to stress stimuli, and might therefore induce secondary effects in such a cascade.</p><p>In response to ABA, a total of 90 transcription factors were induced in both the <italic>Mop1</italic> and <italic>mop1-1</italic> genotypes, or unique to one genotype (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), including genes corresponding to the Zinc-finger (ZF), APETALA2/Ethylene-Responsive Element Binding Protein (AP2/EREBP), Basic Leucine Zipper (bZIP), Myeloblastosis (MYB), Homeobox (HB), and Heat Shock Factor (HSFTF) families of TFs (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). For example, the AP2/EREBP superfamily is one of the largest known to play a critical role in abiotic stress responses in plants (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Mizoi <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Of the AP2/EREBP TFs identified in this study, most are upregulated in response to ABA (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Of these 90 TFs, 32 were found to be upregulated in response to ABA in both mutant and wildtype genotypes, whereas 51 TFs were upregulated in response to ABA only in <italic>mop1-1</italic> (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Other members of the same families of TFs were identified as downregulated in response to ABA treatment (72 TFs, <xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The majority of these (50 genes) were uniquely downregulated in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant (<xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), presumably through negative regulation directed by ABA-responsive and MOP1-silenced TFs. Another noteable observation from this analysis was that members of the NAC family of TFs, known to be responsive to ABA and dehydration (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Nakashima <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), were exclusively differentially expressed in response to ABA in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant (<xref rid="t4" ref-type="table">Tables 4</xref> and <xref rid="t5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Transcription factor (TF) families upregulated in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant in response to ABA (Groups I, V)</title></caption><table frame="border" rules="groups"><col width="16.48%" span="1"/><col width="9.31%" span="1"/><col width="17.69%" span="1"/><col width="9.64%" span="1"/><col width="19.04%" span="1"/><col width="10.15%" span="1"/><col width="17.69%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>Mop1</italic> Wildtype Unique</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Common in WT and Mutant</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> Mutant Unique</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TF Family</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="11" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Ethylene-Responsive Element Binding (EREB): AP2/ERF, DREB/CBF, and RAV subfamily</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb60</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032144</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb13</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d052152</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb106</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d048991</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb34</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039077</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb111</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d053195</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb69</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d037941</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb122</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d045204</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb126</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043782</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb147</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043205</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb133</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d038320</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb156</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026447</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb162</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d038907</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb186</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008872</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb179</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027924</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dhn1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d037894</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb202</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d005798</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dbf1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032295</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Abi13</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d011639</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Abi35</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">No apical meristem, ATAF1 and Cup-shaped cotyledon (NAC)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf25</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d023294</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf30</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d016950</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf40</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d050893</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf60</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d013003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf118</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008399</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="11" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Myeloblastosis (MYB)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glk16</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d001936</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb26</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017383</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb22</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008528</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic>Myb153</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d019712</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb112</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d046632</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb50</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d015614</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb159</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d020408</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb1066</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d037334</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb162</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d020457</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb132</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d025864</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb158</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d036768</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb166</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d051267</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mybr24</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008808</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mybr55</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d012285</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mybr58</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d051480</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glk25</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d010634</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fdl1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d022227</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">basic Leucine Zipper Domain (bZIP)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip45</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d030577</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043992</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip9</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d020025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip4</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d018178</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip10</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d023507</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip49</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d031790</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip27</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d002143</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip95</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d042721</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip29</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d034571</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip102</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043117</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip76</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d036736</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gbf1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039065</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip107</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d024160</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d042899</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">WRKY</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky38</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d005622</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky32</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d028962</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky80</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008793</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky81</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043060</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">basic Helix-Loop-Helix (BHLH)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh41</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d007311</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh144</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d004095</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh20</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d005841</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh160</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027987</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh132</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d042482</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh165</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d049870</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh152</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d016873</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d048901</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Homeobox (HB)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb41</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017422</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb5</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027991</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb52</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008869</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d002782</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb62</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d047995</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb70</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d025964</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb78</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d029934</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Heat Shock Factor TF (HSFTF)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hsftf18</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d016255</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hsftf3</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d044259</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hsftf28</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d046299</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Squamosa-promoter Binding Protein (SBP)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sbp29</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d021573</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sbp7</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d052905</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sbp18</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d012015</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear Factor Y (NF-Y)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cadtfr6</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d006813</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ca2p1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d013501</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene-Insensitive-Like (EIL)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eil8</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d016924</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin/IAA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iaa44</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026480</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Other TFs</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tcptf24</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d008919</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arftf29</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1">Zm00001d036533</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzr9</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027587</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mads45</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d035053</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Platz11</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017682</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="t5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Transcription factor (TF) families downregulated in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant (Groups II, VI)</title></caption><table frame="border" rules="groups"><col width="8.66%" span="1"/><col width="9.92%" span="1"/><col width="17.69%" span="1"/><col width="11.01%" span="1"/><col width="17.69%" span="1"/><col width="10.68%" span="1"/><col width="24.35%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TF Family</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>Mop1</italic> WT Unique</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Common in WT and Mutant</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> Mutant Unique</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene id</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">EREB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb190</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026486</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb46</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d015759</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ereb143</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d020540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">NAC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf62</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d034984</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf92</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d050039</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf103</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d002934</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nactf121</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d021424</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">MYB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb154</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d047671</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glk52</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026542</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb11</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d022628</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb42</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d053220</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb23</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d022259</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb63</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d052804</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb27</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d044538</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb38</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032024</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mybr78</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017782</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb109</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d023932</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb131</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039496</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Myb164</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d031270</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">bZIP</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip20</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d012719</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip53</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043420</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip84</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d053988</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip61</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d015743</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bzip89</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d016154</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">WRKY</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky20</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d009698</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wrky100</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d038761</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">BHLH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh47</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d034298</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh25</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d044242</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh173</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d031665</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh30</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d018056</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh33</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d005939</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh97</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d048309</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bhlh143</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d047878</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">HB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glk53</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d015407</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb21</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d046223</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hb122</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026537</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d049000</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSFTF</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hsftf25</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d011406</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hsftf13</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027757</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NF-Y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ca5p15</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039581</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eil2</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d007188</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iaa3</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d033319</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Other TF</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crr2</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d026594</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gbptf21</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d040254</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Irl1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d040173</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ptac12</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043325</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rack1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d038923</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="16" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Zinc-Fingers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d035195</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dbb2</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d002806</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C3h3</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"/><td rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Zm00001d037023</td><td rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d004439</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C3h21</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d044074</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Zm00001d049625</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Col4</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d045661</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Zm00001d048214</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Col10</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d037327</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Zm00001d049525</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Id1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d032922</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Zm00001d016721</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gata13</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d012757</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Zm00001d006879</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d052883</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d052918</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d017871</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d027684</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d037974</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d039579</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"/><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zm00001d043422</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Zm00001d043728</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Zm00001d045454</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Zm00001d046289</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A recent analysis of transcriptional responses to ABA and TF binding events in Arabidopsis suggests a hierarchical model of regulation, with three tiers of TFs and a set of target genes thought to directly impact physiological responses (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). An implication of this model would be that a higher tier TF might induce a substantial cascade of effects by modulating expression of many genes in downstream tiers.</p><p>To see if this hierarchical model could be adapted to MOP1- and ABA-mediated transcriptional responses, maize genes homologous to the TFs in the <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref> model were identified in <italic>Mop1</italic> and <italic>mop1-1</italic> up- and downregulated genes using a list of maize orthologs of Arabidopsis genes generated in an earlier study (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>) (File S3). Of the ten Tier 1 TF families in the Arabidopsis study, six were represented in our maize seedling dataset with one or more homologous genes (| log<sub>2</sub> FC | &#x02265; 0.8, FDR &#x0003c; 0.05; File S3). Three of the six Tier 2 TFs and two of the five Tier 3 TFs had one or more homologs that were differentially expressed in maize seedlings exposed to ABA (| log<sub>2</sub> FC | &#x02265; 0.91, FDR &#x0003c; 0.05; File S3). A total of 30 maize genes were identified as differentially expressed in maize seedlings and shared homology with the target genes identified by the hierarchical model (| log<sub>2</sub> FC | &#x02265; 0.75, FDR &#x0003c; 0.05; File S3). A previously constructed gene regulatory network (GRN) (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>) was used to predict the regulatory relationships between these maize genes in seed, shoot apical meristem, root, and leaf tissues (File S4). The connectivity of this network supports the idea that these genes are part of a regulatory network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>), and the gene expression responses observed in this study may result from several scenarios ranging from primary and secondary transcriptional responses to disruption or stimulus in a hierarchical network.</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Model of maize transcription factor hierarchical network. Maize genes orthologous to Arabidopsis genes in a hierarchical, ABA-responsive network (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>) were identified among ABA-responsive DEGs in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants. Transcription Factors are separated in three levels based on the Arabidopsis hierarchical regulatory model (TF level 1, 2, and 3). Target genes are clustered by function (Transport, Metabolism, Receptors, Phosphatases, Kinases, and E3 ligases). Node color corresponds to log<sub>2</sub>FC. Nodes that lack a border are differentially expressed in both wildtype and mutant in response to ABA; nodes with a dotted border are differentially expressed only in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant; and nodes with solid borders are differentially expressed only in wildtype.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1727f3"/></fig></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Mop1 wildtype plants exhibit context-dependent ABA-induced cytosine methylation at specific loci, including particular families of transposons</title><p>The canonical model for MOP1-activity is based on a predicted role for MOP1 in RdDM-mediated gene silencing in which <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants display a (1) reduction in 24-nt siRNAs (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Nobuta <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) and (2) reduced CHH methylation (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>To profile MOP1-dependent 24-nt siRNAs, we used publicly available datasets (<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>) to determine if upregulated genes were more likely to have hallmarks of direct regulation by MOP1 than downregulated genes. Genes that are differentially expressed in response to ABA in wildtype but not <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants might be examples of regulatory events that are ABA-responsive and MOP1-dependent. Two hundred (200) genes are uniquely differentially expressed in wildtype in response to ABA. These 200 genes include 105 upregulated and 95 downregulated ABA-responsive genes in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype that are not detected as differentially expressed in ABA-induced <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants; identified from a comparison of Groups I and II <italic>vs.</italic> Groups V and VI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Eighty-six percent (86%; 171 genes) of the MOP1-dependent ABA-responsive genes had a known gene identifier. Of these 171 genes, 26.08% (24/92 upregulated genes, Group I) and 26.58% (21/79 downregulated genes, Group II) showed a depletion of MOP1-dependent 24-nt siRNAs in their promoter regions in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant when compared to <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype, respectively (<xref rid="t6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Although potentially limited by tissue-specific differences between the siRNA datasets and expression analysis in this study, there was no apparent relationship between MOP1-dependent siRNAs and upregulation in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants.</p><table-wrap id="t6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>24-nt siRNA depletion percentage in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant in the 5&#x02032; proximal promoter region (2 kb upstream of TSS) of differentially expressed genes</title></caption><table frame="border" rules="groups"><col width="19.79%" span="1"/><col width="11.34%" span="1"/><col width="16.48%" span="1"/><col width="16.62%" span="1"/><col width="16.44%" span="1"/><col width="19.33%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pair-wise comparison</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of total genes with gene model in group/subgroup</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of genes with siRNA in 5&#x02032; proximal promoter</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% siRNA depleted genes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA / wildtype MS</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">470</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.98</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to WT</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row">II</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to WT</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant MS /<italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">IV</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant ABA / mutant MS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">894</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to <italic>mop1-1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">516</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row">VI</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">893</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to <italic>mop1-1</italic></td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">668</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant ABA /<italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VII</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.89</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">VIII</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Upregulated genes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III, V, VII</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">977</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to <italic>mop1-1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">596</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" scope="row" colspan="1">Downregulated genes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV, VI, VIII</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All genes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">938</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique to <italic>mop1-1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">712</td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genome-wide</bold></td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>All genes</bold></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>44,301</bold></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7,844</bold></td><td valign="middle" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17.71</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To profile cytosine methylation changes, <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant seedlings subjected to ABA treatment or MS control were also used in a sequence-capture bisulfite sequencing approach (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). This experiment allowed us to survey ABA-induced cytosine methylation in maize, as well as to explore the role of MOP1-mediated RdDM in ABA-induced epigenetic responses. The captured regions were selected based on several criteria as previously described (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Han <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>) and included a total of 21,822 loci with a mean length of &#x0223c;285 bp, representing &#x0223c;15 Mb (&#x0003c;1% of the B73 maize genome), and were aligned to the B73v4 reference genome (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Jiao <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>).</p><p>Consistent with the previously described loss of RdDM activity in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), the biggest difference in cytosine methylation in our control samples was observed in the CHH context (68% CHH reduction in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants relative to wildtype; compared to 14% CHG and 3% CG) (comparison D, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Interestingly, a slight increase in methylation in response to ABA treatment was observed in the CHG and CHH sequence contexts (1.6% and 11.1% respectively; comparison A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>) in a unique manner in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype plants, suggesting ABA-induced cytosine methylation at specific loci. It is worth noting that <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype plants introgressed into the B73 genome had lower than average CHH methylation compared to B73 plants treated with MS or ABA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>) and the methylated CHH (mCHH) increase in the <italic>Mop1</italic> WT promoter region in response to ABA is similar to the untreated B73 methylation level. An ABA-dependent increase in CHH methylation was not observed for B73 plants in this experiment. Therefore, further experiments would be needed to separate the effects of pedigree-related epigenetic differences that may stem from a genomic exposure to <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous conditions and may take multiple generations to recover from.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>DNA methylation in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype and <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant seedlings in response to abscisic acid. (A) Genome-wide methylation % difference in all sequence contexts (CG, CHG, and CHH) was calculated using the following equation ((Genotype/Treatment mC% - Genotype/Treatment control mC%) / Genotype/Treatment control mC%) for all regions in the genome. (B) Cytosine methylation % of the 2 Kb upstream region from the transcription start site (TSS) for three genotypes, B73 (blue), <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype (yellow), <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant (red) for two treatments, ABA (continuous) and MS (dotted). The mean methylation percentage (%) was calculated per genotype/treatment combination and context for all genes. (C) Methylation % difference in CG, CHG, and CHH context for <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA-upregulated (Group I) and ABA-downregulated (Group II) genes in three different promoter regions (2 Kb from TSS, 1 Kb from TSS, and a 0.5 Kb region including -0.25 to -0.75 Kb). Methylation % difference was calculated using the following equation (<italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype ABA mC% - <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype MS mC%).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1727f4"/></fig><p>A promoter analysis of genotype/treatment combinations in all three cytosine methylation sequence contexts shows an increase in DNA methylation in the CHH context in ABA-treated <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype when compared to MS-treated wildtype plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). An additional promoter analysis correlating the methylation percentage in this region for ABA-responsive DEGs and non-DEGs was performed (Figure S4). We observed that wildtype plants had higher CHH methylation within the first 1000 bp upstream from the TSS of ABA-responsive DEGs (Groups I, II, V and VI). This ABA-induced DNA methylation change is not observed as a response to this hormone in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant, which suggests that MOP1 might be necessary for an epigenetic environmental response in maize seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>, Figure S4). The percent differences in DNA methylation for comparison A were measured in the promoter region of wildtype ABA-responsive DEGs (Groups I and II). Regions of 2 kb (0 to -2.0 Kb), 1 kb (0 to -1.0 Kb), and 500 bp (-0.25 to -0.75 Kb) upstream of TSS were assayed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>, File S9). The average methylation differences between ABA-up (Group I) and downregulated (Group II) genes becomes more apparent in the smaller promoter region (500 bp), closer to the TSS in the CHH context, suggesting a dynamic transient methylation change as a response to ABA levels that are correlated with gene expression regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). A GO term analysis of Group II genes that show an increase in CHH methylation in their promoter region identified four biological process GO terms related to response to endogenous stimulus (GO:0009719, FDR 6.1 e-5; GO:0009725, FDR 6.1 e-5; GO:0010033; FDR 0.0007, GO:0042221, FDR 0.02) and four molecular function GO terms related to hydrolase and transferase activity of glycosyl compounds (GO:0004553, FDR 0.0011; GO:0016798, FDR 0.0015; GO:0016758, FDR 0.016; GO:0016757, FDR 0.024). The increase in CHH methylation of this group of genes during ABA treatment suggests the transcriptional epigenetic regulatory machinery in maize seedlings during environmental stimuli tends to direct gene silencing toward mechanisms involved in metabolism in order to efficiently activate processes of stress response and recovery.</p><p>MOP1 function has been previously correlated with genomic regions adjoining particular types of transposable elements and genic regions (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Madzima <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2015a</xref>), suggesting that this regulatory pathway functions to maintain distinct transcriptional activities within genomic spaces, and that loss of MOP1 may modify the responsiveness of some loci to other regulatory pathways. We analyzed the enrichment of individual TE families in regions adjacent to ABA-regulated genes in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant that contain ABA-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements (ABREs) (177 and 67 DEGs from Groups V and VI, respectively). Approximately 50% of the TEs found within 2 kb upstream of the transcription start sites (TSS) or 2 kb downstream of the transcription termination sites (TTS) of genes predicted to be common MOP1-ABA regulatory gene targets belong to the Pif/Harbinger (DTH) and Tc1/Mariner (DTT) superfamilies of the class II DNA TIR transposons. This is consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gent <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and shows a considerable change in the number of DTH and DTT transposons at these loci when compared to the B73 genome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, File S10). In our study, the DTH superfamily of TEs was 12% and 15% more abundant near upregulated and downregulated genes, respectively, compared to the distribution of this TE category across the B73 genome. Additionally, the DTT elements were half as abundant near ABRE-containing ABA-downregulated genes in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant than near ABA-upregulated genes or across the B73 genome. These findings suggest that loss of MOP1 may modify how responsive these genes are to other regulatory pathways like ABA, due to changes in TE transcriptional maintenance at these loci.</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Percentage of transposable elements (TEs) within each TE superfamily. TEs detected within 2 kb upstream or downstream of genes with ABREs or CEs that were upregulated (white) or downregulated (stripes) in <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant plants treated with ABA represented multiple TE categories. The TEs analyzed include Class I of LTR retrotransposons Copia (RLC), Gypsy (RLG), and unclassified (RLX), LINES L1 (RIL) and RTE (RIT), and SINES (RST) as well as class II of DNA TIR transposons hAT (DTA), CACTA (DTC), Pif/Harbinger (DTH), Mutator (DTM), Tc1/Mariner (DTT), and unclassified TIR (DTX), and the Helitron superfamily (DHH). The abundance of the same TE families across the B73 genome (black; 338,224 TEs) was used as a comparison against <italic>mop1-1</italic> ABREs/CEs-containing ABA-upregulated (103 TEs) and downregulated (42 TEs) genes. Bars depict the percentage (y-axis) of the TE categories (x-axis) in each subset that belong to each TE family.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1727f5"/></fig></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Gene expression responses to ABA involve coordination of cis-elements, CHH methylation, and MOP1-mediated effects</title><p>Genes directly induced or repressed by ABA are expected to have canonical ABA <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory sequences that are recognized by ABA-phosphorylated TFs. To predict primary transcriptional targets of ABA, we searched for ABRE and CE <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements within the putative promoters of DEGs in ABA-treated wildtype (Groups I and II) and mutant (Groups V and VI) samples.</p><p>Out of the total 858 genes in Groups I and II, this analysis was limited to 774 genes with a named gene model in the annotated maize genome version 40 (Zea_mays.AGPv4.40.gtf, EnsemblPlants; (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Kersey <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>)) (File S5). One hunded thirteen (113) genes were identified as ABA primary targets: 94 were identified to have potential ABRE and CE sites within the 2 kb sequence upstream of the transcription start sites (TSS) using the MEME-suite (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bailey <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>) (File S5) and the remaining 19 genes were identified through a literature search of genes empirically demonstrated to be directly regulated by ABA in previous published studies (File S5). Based on the GRN (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>), 23 of these 113 genes are predicted to regulate the expression of a collective group of 501 genes. These 23 genes are TFs (14 genes) and Prh/PP2CA (8 genes), with one of unknown category. Within these 501 genes, 75 were also predicted to contain ABA-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements and be directly regulated by ABA, while 426 genes were exclusively predicted to be secondary targets (File S5).</p><p>We identified a negative correlation between transcription and CHH methylation specifically in downregulated ABRE/CE containing genes (ABA-primary targets) in ABA-treated <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype seedlings. Of 113 ABA-primary targets, 92 were upregulated and 21 were downregulated in ABA-treated wildtype plants. Of the 21 downregulated ABA-primary targets, 14 exhibited an increased in CHH methylation, in contrast to the upregulated primary ABA-induced genes, where no change in CHH methylation was observed for any of the 92 genes. In <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants, 5 of these 14 genes are not downregulated nor do they exhibit CHH methylation in the ABRE proximal regions. This suggests that a subset of genes may be methylated and downregulated by a MOP1-dependent pathway in response to ABA. Induction of ABA-dependent MOP1-mediated methylation is also revealed by the increase in CHH methylation around TSS in response to ABA in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype, but not <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>A total of 244 DEGs in ABA-treated <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants were predicted to be ABA primary response genes based on the performed motif enrichment analysis and previously published experiments (File S5). Using these primary targets as predicted regulators in the GRN (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>), differential expression of secondary targets by these primary targets could explain the change in expression of the 1,362 out of 1,542 genes that were not predicted to be primary response genes (File S5). Collectively, primary responses and their predicted secondary targets account for 90% of ABA-induced changes in gene expression in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant, suggesting that a cascade of regulatory effects largely explains the combined effects of a loss of MOP1 and exposure to ABA.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s22"><title>Discussion</title><p>In response to changing and potentially growth-limiting environmental conditions, plants have evolved adaptive physiological mechanisms that are often linked to activation or repression of gene expression. Extensive research in the field has uncovered an increasingly complex network of regulation that includes cross talk between many different types of stressors, phytohormones, and regulatory mechanisms (reviewed by <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">kundu and Gantait 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Dangi <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). Important components of the regulation of gene expression in plants include epigenetic and ABA-induced transcriptional regulation (reviewed by <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Vishwakarma <italic>et al.</italic> 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Annacondia <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). Plant responses to stress are often non-additive, and simultaneous exposures to multiple stimuli have been documented to induce changes in gene expression that are distinct from either stimulus individually (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Mittler 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Atkinson and Urwin 2012</xref>). Recent evidence suggests a particular importance of siRNA-mediated responses to stress-induced changes in gene expression (reviewed by <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Khraiwesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Chekanova 2016</xref>). Therefore, this study sought to understand how <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants, known to have reduced 24-nt siRNA levels in maize (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Nobuta <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), would respond to ABA at the level of gene expression. The patterns of gene expression observed in this study support a hierarchical model of gene expression similar to that proposed to explain environmental stress responses in the model plant Arabidopsis, which includes 3 interconnected tiers of transcriptional regulators that, directly and indirectly, regulate the expression of many ABA-responsive target genes (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). The work reported herein also supports the integration of MOP1-mediated regulation into these hierarchical plant responses and coordinate epigenetic and stimulus-driven regulation.</p><p>Our analysis of gene expression in V3 maize seedlings in the presence and absence of exogenous ABA treatment uncovered genome-wide changes in gene expression. Many of these changes were genotype independent and included many known examples of ABA-responsive genes in plants. Consistent with known pleiotropic phenotypes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants, the analysis also revealed that <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutants did not respond to ABA treatment in an identical manner to their wildtype siblings. These differences could be explained by the disruption of a hierarchical regulatory pathway, with a cascade of effects on gene expression, MOP1-dependent responses to ABA in maize, and combined direct and indirect effects of MOP1 and ABA response acting in synergy to create non-additive gene expression profiles across the genome. The largest number of differentially expressed genes was detected in <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants that had been exposed to exogenous ABA. This suggests that some distinct genes become more responsive to ABA in the absence of MOP1, while some ABA-responsive genes are unresponsive to ABA in the absence of MOP1. These relationships may be evidence of coordination between ABA-mediated and MOP1-mediated regulatory pathways and reinforce the idea that epigenetic regulation is crucial to plant response and adaptation to abiotic stress. These results also support the idea of the presence of epigenetically silenced genes that are &#x0201c;hidden&#x0201d; from ABA-responsiveness in <italic>Mop1</italic> wildtype. This cryptic variation is epigenetically &#x0201c;uncovered&#x0201d; in the <italic>mop1-1</italic> mutant in response to ABA as differentially expressed epi-alelles.</p><p>To estimate direct and indirect MOP1-mediated effects, we explored the distribution of MOP1-dependent siRNAs in the predicted promoter regions of DEGs. The genes that are downregulated in <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants are often regarded as indirect targets of a loss of MOP1 because of the canonically accepted silencing activity of MOP1 dependent pathways. However, these genes also appear to be enriched for 5&#x02032; proximal MOP1-dependent siRNAs; one potential explanation for this would be the coordinated activity of RdDM and ROS1-dependent demethylation to maintain gene activity, as has been described in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Lei <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Some of the RdDM targets are promoter regions that can be actively demethylated by ROS1 (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agius, Kapoor, &#x00026; Zhu 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Morales-Ruiz <italic>Et Al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Penterman, Zilberman, <italic>Et Al</italic>., 2007</xref>). RDR2 is an essential component of RdDM and is the MOP1 homolog in Arabidopsis. In the <italic>rdr2</italic> background, CG hypermethylation was found in the promoter region of downregulated ROS1 target genes, suggesting ROS1 demethylation is associated with RDR2 (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Penterman <italic>Et Al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Many stress-responsive genes are also downregulated in a triple DNA demethylase mutant (<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Le <italic>Et Al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Consistently, ROS1 is required for transcriptional activation via demethylation of specific ABA-inducible genes (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2019</xref>). These genes contain TEs and show DNA methylation changes in their promoters, suggesting that RdDM might mediate regulation of stress-responsive genes in a manner that involves DNA demethylation (<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Le <italic>Et Al</italic>. 2014</xref>).</p><p>There are multiple genes in the maize genome with amino acid sequence similarity to Arabidopsis ROS1 (reviewed by <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">LMadzima, Sloan <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and at least one of them appears to be downregulated and not responsive to ABA induction of expression in <italic>mop1-1</italic> seedlings. It is therefore possible that some of the genes identified in this analysis are additional examples of coordinate regulation by RdDM-gene silencing and demethylation-associated transcriptional activation, and that disruption of this coordinated regulation relates to some of the phenotypes exhibited by <italic>mop1-1</italic> homozygous plants.</p><p>It is possible that the upregulated genes in <italic>mop1-1</italic> plants for which MOP1-dependent siRNAs were not identified are indirect targets of MOP1, or that siRNAs exist but were not detected in the datasets used for this analysis because of tissue-specific differences in siRNA populations or incompletely annotated gene models. Based upon the diverse and diffuse gene expression phenotypes observed, it is likely that there are different explanations for the responses of different groups of genes.</p><p>The sequence-capture methylation analysis allowed us to identify a handful of examples in which there is an overlap between ABA and RdDM regulatory mechanisms. Previous studies have reported an increase in non-CG methylation (CHG and CHH) in intergenic TE sequences in response to osmotic stress, which induces ABA biosynthesis and is associated with a transient epigenetic adaptation to environmental cues (<xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Wibowo <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). This is consistent with the fact that CHH methylation is not stochastic and has been observed to change as a response to abiotic stress in plant species (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dubin <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Secco <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Wibowo <italic>et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). The role of ABA in DNA methylation/demethylation and gene expression processes in maize is not yet understood.</p><p>Interpreting the complexity of plant responses to the environment is essential to a complete understanding of plant growth, development and physiology, with particular regard to crop yield and agricultural challenges. By perturbing phytohormone levels and an essential component of epigenetic regulation, some unique plant responses were observed. These results shed some insight onto the nature of combinatorial, and potentially synergistic, regulation of gene expression in maize.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to Nathan Springer for providing the SeqCap DNA methylation data. This work was funded by the National Science Foundation funds to K.M.M (CMB-035919) and start-up funds from the University of Washington Bothell School of STEM to T.F.M. P.A.C. was supported by a grant from NSF (IOS-1802848).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental material available at figshare: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25387/g3.9626636">https://doi.org/10.25387/g3.9626636</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Communicating editor: M. Estelle</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agius</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Role of the Arabidopsis DNA glycosylase/lyase ROS1 in active DNA demethylation.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>11796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11801</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603563103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alleman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidorenko</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorweiler</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>An RNA-dependent RNA polymerase is required for paramutation in maize.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>442</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stitzer</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brohammer</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noshay</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2019</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transposable elements contribute to dynamic genome content in maize.</article-title>
<source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>1052</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1065</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.14489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31381222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annacondia</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mager&#x000f8;y</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Stress response regulation by epigenetic mechanisms: changing of the guards.</article-title>
<source>Physiol. Plant.</source>
<volume>162</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29080251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asensi-Fabado</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amtmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Plant responses to abiotic stress: The chromatin context of transcriptional regulation.</article-title>
<source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta. Gene Regul. Mech.</source>
<volume>1860</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2016.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27487458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Urwin</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The interaction of plant biotic and abiotic stresses: from genes to the field.</article-title>
<source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>3523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3543</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22467407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The MEME Suite.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>W39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25953851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belda-Palazon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Garcia</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano-Juste</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coego</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antoni</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>PYL8 mediates ABA perception in the root through non-cell-autonomous and ligand-stabilization-based mechanisms.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>115</volume>: <fpage>E11857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E11863</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1815410115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busk</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pages</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Regulation of abscisic acid-induced transcription.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006058700720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9617810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications.</article-title>
<source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>VennPlex-A Novel Venn Diagram Program for Comparing and Visualizing Datasets with Differentially Regulated Datapoints.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biderre-Petit</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kbhaya</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic acid and stress signals induce Viviparous1 expression in seed and vegetative tissues of maize.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>731</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.091454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17208960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lun</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>From reads to genes to pathways: differential expression analysis of RNA-Seq experiments using Rsubread and the edgeR quasi-likelihood pipeline.</article-title>
<source>F1000 Res.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1438</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DEMETER, a DNA glycosylase domain protein, is required for endosperm gene imprinting and seed viability in arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(02)00807-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dangi</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khangwal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Combinatorial Interactions of Biotic and Abiotic Stresses in Plants and Their Molecular Mechanisms: Systems Biology Approach.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>636</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>650</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12033-018-0100-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29943149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorweiler</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollick</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kermicle</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title>mediator of paramutation1 is required for establishment and maintenance of paramutation at multiple maize loci.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.11.2101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubin</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Remigereau</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DNA methylation in Arabidopsis has a genetic basis and shows evidence of local adaptation.</article-title>
<source>eLife</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e05255</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.05255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25939354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domrachev</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erhard</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McClish</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollick</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Nascent transcription affected by RNA polymerase IV in Zea mays.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>199</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.115.174714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25653306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W. Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S. X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Contrasting transcriptional responses of PYR1/PYL/RCAR ABA receptors to ABA or dehydration stress between maize seedling leaves and roots.</article-title>
<source>BMC Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0764-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27101806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>ABA-mediated transcriptional regulation in response to osmotic stress in plants.</article-title>
<source>J. Plant Res.</source>
<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>525</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10265-011-0412-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21416314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penterman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DEMETER DNA glycosylase establishes MEDEA polycomb gene self-imprinting by allele-specific demethylation.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.12.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gent</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harkess</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>CHH islands: de novo DNA methylation in near-gene chromatin regulation in maize.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>637</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.146985.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gent</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madzima</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Accessible DNA and relative depletion of H3K9me2 at maize loci undergoing RNA-directed DNA methylation.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4917</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.130427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25465407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goday</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Culianez-Macia</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mar Alba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Figueras</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1994</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The maize abscisic acid-responsive protein Rab17 is located in the nucleus and interacts with nuclear localization signals.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8180497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brower-Toland</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidorenko</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicora</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Functional diversification of maize RNA polymerase IV and V subtypes via alternative catalytic subunits.</article-title>
<source>Cell Rep.</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.08.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25284785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stelpflug</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaeppler</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Heritable Epigenomic Changes to the Maize Methylome Resulting from Tissue Culture.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>209</volume>: <fpage>983</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>995</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.118.300987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29848487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2019</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The Maize Clade A PP2C Phosphatases Play Critical Roles in Multiple Abiotic Stress Responses.</article-title>
<source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20143573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terzaghi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The Maize ABA Receptors ZmPYL8, 9, and 12 Facilitate Plant Drought Resistance.</article-title>
<source>Front Plant Sci</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29670640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Epigenetic inheritance in plants.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>447</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>424</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17522675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>X. L. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nhi</surname><given-names>D. N. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thu</surname><given-names>N. B. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thao</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcription Factors and Their Roles in Signal Transduction in Plants under Abiotic Stresses.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Genomics</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>497</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389202918666170227150057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29204078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendramin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Construction and Optimization of a Large Gene Coexpression Network in Maize Using RNA-Seq Data.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>583</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Distinct tissue-specific transcriptional regulation revealed by gene regulatory networks in maize.</article-title>
<source>BMC Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1329-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huettel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daxinger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aufsatz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Endogenous targets of RNA-directed DNA methylation and Pol IV in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2836</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16724114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisch</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohtsu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nettleton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Loss of RNA-dependent RNA polymerase 2 (RDR2) function causes widespread and unexpected changes in the expression of transposons, genes, and 24-nt small RNAs.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000737</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stitzer</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Improved maize reference genome with single-molecule technologies.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>546</volume>: <fpage>524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28605751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coruh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Improved Placement of Multi-mapping Small RNAs.</article-title>
<source>G3 (Bethesda)</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.030452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27175019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finkler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slabas</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of Sorghum bicolor responding to combined heat and drought stress.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24916767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>Z. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcription Factors and Plants Response to Drought Stress: Current Understanding and Future Directions.</article-title>
<source>Front Plant Sci</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1029</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27471513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kersey</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allot</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boddu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Ensembl Genomes 2018: an integrated omics infrastructure for non-vertebrate species.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>D802</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D808</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29092050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khraiwesh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Role of miRNAs and siRNAs in biotic and abiotic stress responses of plants.</article-title>
<source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1819</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sako</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Chromatin changes in response to drought, salinity, heat, and cold stresses in plants.</article-title>
<source>Front Plant Sci</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25784920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2019</year>&#x02003;<article-title>ROS1-Dependent DNA Demethylation Is Required for ABA-Inducible NIC3 Expression.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>1810</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1821</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.18.01471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Ensembl BioMarts: a hub for data retrieval across taxonomic space.</article-title>
<source>Database (Oxford)</source>
<volume>2011</volume>: <fpage>bar030</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/bar030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21785142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic acid signal crosstalk during abiotic stress response.</article-title>
<source>Plant Gene</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plgene.2017.04.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuromori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>ABA Transport and Plant Water Stress Responses.</article-title>
<source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2018.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29731225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000e4;mke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000e4;urle</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Epigenetic and chromatin-based mechanisms in environmental stress adaptation and stress memory in plants.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>124</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1263-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28655328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Establishing, maintaining and modifying DNA methylation patterns in plants and animals.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Au Khang</surname></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DNA demethylases target promoter transposable elements to positively regulate stress responsive genes in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biology</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0458-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Regulatory link between DNA methylation and active demethylation in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>112</volume>: <fpage>3553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3557</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1502279112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25733903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eichten</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermanson</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaunbrecher</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetic perturbation of the maize methylome.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4602</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4616</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.133140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gent</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zynda</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makarevitch</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year><comment>a</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>RNA-directed DNA methylation enforces boundaries between heterochromatin and euchromatin in the maize genome.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>112</volume>: <fpage>14728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14733</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1514680112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eichten</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year><comment>b</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Post-conversion targeted capture of modified cytosines in mammalian and plant genomes.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>e81</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25813045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Antisilencing role of the RNA-directed DNA methylation pathway and a histone acetyltransferase in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>11425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11430</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1208557109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22733760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorweiler</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A mutation that prevents paramutation in maize also reverses Mutator transposon methylation and silencing.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>6130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.052152199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Network analysis of ABA-dependent and ABA-independent drought responsive genes in Arabidopsis thaliana.</article-title>
<source>Genet. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>624</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>637</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-4685-gmb-2017-0229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30044467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>550</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madzima</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Chromatin structure and gene expression changes associated with loss of MOP1 activity in Zea mays.</article-title>
<source>Epigenetics</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1059</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/epi.29022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24786611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madzima</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stroud</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>&#x02018;Epigenomics&#x02019;</article-title> in <source>Genetics, Genomics and Breeding of Maize</source>. <comment>R. Wusirika, M. Bohn, J. Lai, C. Kole Eds. CRC Press.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcotte</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Quatrano</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1989</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic acid-responsive sequences from the em gene of wheat.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>976</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2562556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads.</article-title>
<source>EMBnet.Jour.</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14806/ej.17.1.200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morosawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaminuma</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Arabidopsis transcriptome analysis under drought, cold, high-salinity and ABA treatment conditions using a tiling array.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcn101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18625610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RNA-Directed DNA Methylation: The Evolution of a Complex Epigenetic Pathway in Flowering Plants.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-043014-114633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25494460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosher</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RNA-directed DNA methylation: an epigenetic pathway of increasing complexity.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24805120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Differential expression analysis of multifactor RNA-Seq experiments with respect to biological variation.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>4288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22287627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhalothia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basantani</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic acid and abiotic stress tolerance - different tiers of regulation.</article-title>
<source>J. Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>171</volume>: <fpage>486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2013.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24655384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abiotic stress, the field environment and stress combination.</article-title>
<source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2005.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16359910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizoi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>AP2/ERF family transcription factors in plant abiotic stress responses.</article-title>
<source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1819</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21867785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-Ruiz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega-Galisteo</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponferrada-Marin</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Macias</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ariza</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DEMETER and REPRESSOR OF SILENCING 1 encode 5-methylcytosine DNA glycosylases.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>6853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6858</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0601109103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16624880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcriptional regulatory networks in response to abiotic stresses in Arabidopsis and grasses.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>149</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.129791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederhuth</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Putting DNA methylation in context: from genomes to gene expression in plants.</article-title>
<source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta. Gene Regul. Mech.</source>
<volume>1860</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2016.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27590871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobuta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Paoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Distinct size distribution of endogeneous siRNAs in maize: Evidence from deep sequencing in the mop1&#x02013;1 mutant.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>14958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14963</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0808066105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penterman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzawa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetic interactions between DNA demethylation and methylation in arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1557</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.107730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penterman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballinger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DNA demethylation in the Arabidopsis genome.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>6752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6757</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0701861104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17409185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT, StringTie and Ballgown.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1667</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludidi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Drought and exogenous abscisic acid alter hydrogen peroxide accumulation and differentially regulate the expression of two maize RD22-like genes.</article-title>
<source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>8821</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-08976-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28821770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regulski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The maize methylome influences mRNA splice sites and reveals widespread paramutation-like switches guided by small RNA.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1662</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.153510.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic Acid and Abiotic Stress Tolerance in Crop Plants.</article-title>
<source>Front Plant Sci</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27200044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The B73 maize genome: complexity, diversity, and dynamics.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>326</volume>: <fpage>1112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1115</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1178534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19965430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Secco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiarenza</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Stress induced gene expression drives transient DNA methylation changes at adjacent repetitive elements.</article-title>
<source>eLife</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.09343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nanjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Monitoring the expression pattern of around 7,000 Arabidopsis genes under ABA treatments using a full-length cDNA microarray.</article-title>
<source>Funct. Integr. Genomics</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10142-002-0070-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12444421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1995</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Functional dissection of an abscisic acid (ABA)-inducible gene reveals two independent ABA-responsive complexes each containing a G-box and a novel cis-acting element.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7734964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1996</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Modular nature of abscisic acid (ABA) response complexes: composite promoter units that are necessary and sufficient for ABA induction of gene expression in barley.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1119</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8768371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castanon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nery</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A transcription factor hierarchy defines an environmental stress response network.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>354</volume>: <fpage>6312</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag1550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>agriGO v2.0: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural community, 2017 update.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>W122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Todaka</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Recent advances in the dissection of drought-stress regulatory networks and strategies for development of drought-tolerant transgenic rice plants.</article-title>
<source>Front Plant Sci</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilardell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goday</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torrent</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1990</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Gene sequence, developmental expression, and protein phosphorylation of RAB-17 in maize.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00028778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2151715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilardell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Zapater</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goday</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pages</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1994</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Regulation of the rab17 gene promoter in transgenic Arabidopsis wild-type, ABA-deficient and ABA-insensitive mutants.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>569</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00023554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8155877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishwakarma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Abscisic Acid Signaling and Abiotic Stress Tolerance in Plants: A Review on Current Knowledge and Future Prospects.</article-title>
<source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28265276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chekanova</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Small RNAs: essential regulators of gene expression and defenses against environmental stresses in plants.</article-title>
<source>Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. RNA</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>381</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wrna.1340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26924473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmeyer</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2017</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Overlapping RdDM and non-RdDM mechanisms work together to maintain somatic repression of a paramutagenic epiallele of maize pericarp color1.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>e0187157</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29112965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Interaction network of core ABA signaling components in maize.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>263</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-017-0692-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29344831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eichten</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genomic distribution of H3K9me2 and DNA methylation in a maize genome.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e105267</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25122127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wibowo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marconi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Correction: Hyperosmotic stress memory in Arabidopsis is mediated by distinct epigenetically labile sites in the genome and is restricted in the male germline by DNA glycosylase activity.</article-title>
<source>eLife</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pignatta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Methylation-sensitive expression of a DNA demethylase gene serves as an epigenetic rheostat.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e1005142</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25826366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodhouse</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Initiation, establishment, and maintenance of heritable MuDR transposon silencing in maize are mediated by distinct factors.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e339</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>BSMAP: Whole genome bisulfite sequence MAPping program.</article-title>
<source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Dynamics and function of DNA methylation in plants.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-018-0016-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29784956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2004</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Isolation and analysis of water stress induced genes in maize seedlings by subtractive PCR and cDNA macroarray.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>823</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-1969-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>