<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AMB Express</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AMB Express</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AMB Express</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2191-0855</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6170517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">680</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-018-0680-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metagenome sequencing to analyze the impacts of thiamine supplementation on ruminal fungi in dairy cows fed high-concentrate diets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Fuguang</given-names></name><address><email>xuefuguang123@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>Xuemei</given-names></name><address><email>xuemeinan@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Fuyu</given-names></name><address><email>sfycaas@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Xiaohua</given-names></name><address><email>panxiaohuacaas@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Yuming</given-names></name><address><email>guoyum@cau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Linshu</given-names></name><address><phone>+86-10-80798101</phone><email>jls@bac.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Benhai</given-names></name><address><phone>+86-10-62811680</phone><email>xiongbenhai@caas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0526 1937</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410727.7</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, Institute of Animal Science, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0530 8290</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22935.3f</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, College of Animal Science, </institution><institution>China Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 6793</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411626.6</institution-id><institution>Beijing Key Laboratory for Dairy Cow Nutrition, </institution><institution>Beijing University of Agriculture, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>159</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Ruminal thiamine deficiencies occur when dairy cows are overfed with high-concentrate diet, and thiamine supplementation has been proved to attenuate high-concentrate diet induced SARA. However, there is limited knowledge of the relationship between thiamine supplementation in high-concentrate diets and ruminal fungi. In order to investigate the impacts of thiamine supplementation on ruminal fungi, twelve Chinese Holstein dairy cows were randomly assigned into three treatments: control diet (CON; 20% starch, dry matter basis), high-concentrate diet (HC; 33.2% starch, dry matter basis) and high-concentrate diet supplemented with 180&#x000a0;mg thiamine/kg dry matter intake. Dry matter intake and milk production were recorded during the experimental periods. On day 21, rumen fluid samples were collected at 3&#x000a0;h postfeeding and ruminal pH, thiamine concentration and volatile fatty acids were measured. Metagenome sequencing method was conducted to detect ruminal fungi composition. Feeding HC significantly decreased dry matter intake, milk production, ruminal pH, ruminal acetate and thiamine concentration, however, significantly increased propionate and isovalerate (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). These changes were inversed by thiamine supplementation (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Totally, seven phyla and almost 1050 species of rumen fungi were identified across all samples in which especially, 3 genera and 10 species of strictly anaerobic fungi phylum <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic> was found. Principal coordinate analysis indicated that feeding HC and thiamine supplementation caused a significant inverse in ruminal fungi composition. Feeding HC significantly decreased the abundance of fungi compared with CON (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) while thiamine supplementation significantly increased the abundance of ruminal fungi (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). These results indicated that thiamine supplementation may effectively attenuate rumen metabolic disorder caused by HC diet through buffering the ruminal pH, shifting the rumen fermentation pattern and increasing the abundance of ruminal fungi. The findings in this study could therefore contribute to the further understanding of the mechanism of thiamine&#x02019;s function in dairy cows.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13568-018-0680-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>High-concentrate diet</kwd><kwd>Metagenome</kwd><kwd>Ruminal fungi</kwd><kwd>Thiamine</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Project of National Nature Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>No. 31572435</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Benhai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the National Key Research and Development Plan</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016YFD0700205</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Benhai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Ruminal microbiota is a large systematic microbial ecosystem which is composed by an immense variety of bacteria, protozoa, anaerobic fungi and archaea (Hobson and Stewart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1997</xref>). Functions of this microbial ecosystem are to digest plant materials and convert them into energy and compounds which are absorbable for ruminants (Fernando et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2010</xref>; Mao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2016</xref>; Pitta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2016</xref>). The stability of ruminal microbiota is critical for maintaining the health of ruminants, however, in modern dairy cow production systems, high fermentable carbohydrates are frequently used to obtain higher milk production. The overfeeding of high-concentrate diet decreases ruminal pH, changes ruminal microbiota structure (McCann et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2016</xref>), influences ruminal fermentation characteristics and consequently leads to subacute ruminal acidosis (SARA) (Enemark <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). SARA has been reported as one of the most serious nutritional diseases in high yielding dairy cows which costs a considerable economic loss all over the world each year (Valente et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2017</xref>) and thus many efforts have been paid to prevent its occurrence. Interestingly, our previous study revealed that thiamine supplementation could attenuate high-concentrate diets induced SARA by decreasing ruminal lactate production and increasing ruminal pH value in rumen fluid (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2016</xref>). Moreover, ruminal thiamine content was found to be closely related to <italic>Bacteroides, Ruminococcus 1</italic>, <italic>Ruminobacter</italic> etc. Thiamine supplementation to high-concentrate diet attributed to the increasing abundances of these bacteria (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>). However, these findings mainly focused on ruminal bacterial communities. The information on effect of thiamine supplementation on the composition of other microbial communities including fungi is still limited.</p><p id="Par3">Rumen fungi were first mentioned as a major component of rumen microbiota by a British scientist Colin Orpin (Orpin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1976</xref>), which account for about 5% of the total microbial biomass (Rezaeian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2004</xref>). In ruminal condition, fungi produced a wide range of enzymes which could digest the major structural carbohydrates of plant cell walls, and ferment diet fiber to product absorbable compounds for the host animal (Fliegerova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>; Sekhavati et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2007</xref>). Previous studies about the function of rumen fungi mainly focused on fiber digestion, biogas production (Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;r&#x00131;m et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>) and carbohydrate degradation (Phillips and Gordon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1995</xref>). However, the relationships between thiamine and the rumen fungi are still unclear. Thiamine supplementation shifted the rumen bacterial communities in our previous study (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>), and thiamine exerts beneficial effects in interactions between fungi and bacteria from lamb rumen (Chaucheyras-Durand and Fonty <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2001</xref>). Thus, a hypothesis was proposed that thiamine supplementation may affect the abundance and functions of rumen fungi.</p><p id="Par4">In the past years, several molecular techniques including qPCR, Deformation gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) and 18S rRNA gene sequences were employed for detecting the predominance and diversity of different genera as well as species of rumen fungi. However, 18S rRNA gene sequencing based analysis of fungi have become obsolete because of the highly conserved nature of the 18S rRNA gene (Fliegerova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>). Fortunately, based on the development of high through-put sequencing technology, metagenomic sequencing method provided a new way to reveal details about microbial communities (Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>). Metagenomic sequencing mainly uses next-generation sequencing technology to perform shotgun assays on genomic DNA of all microscopic organisms in samples to analyze the genetic diversity and abundance of microbial populations, and to interpret the genetic composition and functional diversity of microbial populations (Kamke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>; Pitta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2016</xref>). Metagenomics sequencing has been widely applied in detecting the diversity and functions of rumen and gut microbiota in recent years and these findings provided us deeper understandings about the micro-ecosystem (Mao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2016</xref>; Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>). Therefore, metagenomic sequencing method was used in this study to detect the impacts of thiamine supplementation on ruminal fungi in dairy cows fed high-concentrate diets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Animals, experimental design and dietary treatments</title><p id="Par5">Animal care and procedures were in accordance with the Chinese guidelines for animal welfare and approved by Animal Care and Use Committee of the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences. Twelve Chinese Holstein dairy cows (627&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19.9&#x000a0;kg BW; 180&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8 DIM) in second-parity fitted with 10&#x000a0;cm ruminal cannulas (Bar Diamond, Parma, ID) were divided into three treatments. Treatments included a control diet (CON; 20% starch, dry matter basis), a high-concentrate diet (HC; 33.2% starch, dry matter basis) and high-concentrate diet supplemented with 180&#x000a0;mg thiamine/kg dry matter intake (HCT). The diets were formulated according to NRC (2001) to meet or exceed the energy requirements of Holstein dairy cows yielding 20&#x000a0;kg of milk/d with 3.5% milk fat and 3.0% true protein. Details of ingredient analysis and chemical composition of diets were shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1. Cows were fed twice equally at 06:00 and 18:00&#x000a0;h each day, and thiamine (thiamine hydrochloride, purity&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;99%; Wanrong Science and Technology Development Co., Ltd., Wuhan, China) was add via the rumen cannula twice daily after diets were offered for a 21&#x000a0;day period. Throughout the experimental periods, the cows were housed in individual stalls and had free access to fresh water.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Rumen fluid sampling and parameters measurement</title><p id="Par6">During the experimental period, automatic feeding equipments (made by Institute of Animal Science Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, China and NanShang Husbandry Science and Technology Ltd. Henan, China) were used to record dry matter intake. Milking facilities of Afimilk were applied to record milk production of each cow. On day 21, rumen contents were sampled from cranial, caudal, dorsal, and ventral sites of rumen at 3&#x000a0;h after the morning feeding. Collected samples were strained through four layers of cheesecloth to obtain rumen fluid. Rumen fluid was then divided into two parts. One part was processed to analyze the pH value, thiamine content and rumen volatile fatty acid (VFA) content. The other part was put into the liquid nitrogen immediately after adding stabilizer and then stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for DNA extraction. Ruminal pH value was measured using a portable type pH meter (Testo 205, Testo AG, Lenzkirch, Germany) immediately after rumen fluid sample collection. Thiamine concentration in rumen fluid was detected by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) according to Analytical Methods Committee (2000). Individual and total VFA (TVFA) of ruminal fluid were determined by gas chromatograph (GC-2010, Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>DNA extraction, library construction, and metagenomics sequencing</title><p id="Par7">DNA for metagenomics was extracted from the rumen fluid samples by using the QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols. The DNA concentration and purity were quantified with TBS-380 and NanoDrop2000, respectively. DNA quality was examined with the 1% agarose gels electrophoresis system.</p><p id="Par8">DNA was fragmented to an average size of 300&#x000a0;bp using Covaris M220 (Gene Company Limited, China) for paired-end library construction. Paired-end library was prepared by using TruSeqTM DNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). Adapters containing the full complement of sequencing primer hybridization sites were ligated to the Blunt-end fragments. Paired-end sequencing was performed on Illumina HiSeq&#x000a0;4000 platform (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) using HiSeq&#x000a0;3000/4000 PE Cluster Kit and HiSeq&#x000a0;3000/4000 SBS Kits according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.illumina.com">http://www.illumina.com</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Sequence quality control and genome assembly</title><p id="Par9">The quality control methods used the following criteria: 3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032; ends were stripped using SeqPrep (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jstjohn/SeqPrep">https://github.com/jstjohn/SeqPrep</ext-link>) (Aronesty <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>). Low-quality reads (length&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;bp or with a quality value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;20 or having N bases) were removed by Sickle (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>). Sequences that lost their mated reads were considered as single reads and were used in the assembly procedure. Reads were aligned to the cow genome by NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) and any hit associated with the reads and their mated reads were removed. Filtered reads were considered for the next step of the analysis.</p><p id="Par10">Considering that K-mers, varying from 1/3 to &#x02009;2/3 of reads length were used in assembly by SOAP denovo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn">http://soap.genomics.org.cn</ext-link>, Version 1.06), which is based on De Brujin graph construction (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2010</xref>). Scaffolds with a length over 500&#x000a0;bp were retained for statistical tests; we evaluated the quality and quantity of scaffolds generated by each assembly and finally chose the best K-mer which yielded the minimum scaffold number and the maximum value of N50 and N90. Then, scaffolds with a length over 500&#x000a0;bp were extracted and broken into contigs without gaps. Contigs were used for further gene prediction and annotation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Gene prediction and taxonomy</title><p id="Par11">Open reading frames (ORFs) from each sample were predicted using MetaGene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://metagene.cb.k.u-tokyo.ac.jp/">http://metagene.cb.k.u-tokyo.ac.jp/</ext-link>) (Bao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2014</xref>). The predicted ORFs with length being or over 100&#x000a0;bp were retrieved and translated to amino acid sequences using the NCBI translation table (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/taxonomyhome.html/index.cgi%3fchapter%3dtgencodes#SG1">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/taxonomyhome.html/index.cgi?chapter=tgencodes#SG1</ext-link>). All sequences from gene sets with a 95% sequence identity (90% coverage) were clustered as the non-redundant gene catalog by the CD-HIT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.org/cd-hit/">http://www.bioinformatics.org/cd-hit/</ext-link>). Reads after quality control were mapped to the representative genes with 95% identity using SOAP aligner (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn/">http://soap.genomics.org.cn/</ext-link>) and gene abundance in each sample was evaluated (Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>). DIAMOND (Huson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2016</xref>), a new alignment tool for aligning short DNA sequencing reads to a protein reference database was employed for taxonomic annotations by aligning non-redundant gene catalogs against NCBI NR database with e-value cutoff of 1e<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> and Score&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;60. Based on NCBI Microbial Taxonomy Information Database, species annotation information of genes was obtained and relative abundance of species was calculated at the level of Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus and Species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par12">Ruminal pH and thiamine content were analyzed using one-way ANOVA of SAS 9.2. <italic>P</italic> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered to be significance and 0.05&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.10 was considered as a tendency. Spearman correlations between fungi communities and ruminal fermentation variables or thiamine content were assessed using the PROC CORR procedure of SAS 9.2. Relative abundance of all phyla, and the top 30 species of fungi were chosen to conduct the correlation analysis. A correlation matrix was created and visualized in a heatmap format using R package version 3.3.1. The abundance of fungi communities and ruminal variables were considered to be correlated with each other when the absolute value of correlation coefficients (r) were above 0.55 and <italic>P</italic>-value below 0.05. Barplot, principal coordinate analysis (PCoA), hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) and heat map for different rumen fungi species were conducted using R package version 3.3.1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Nucleotide sequence accession number</title><p id="Par13">All the raw sequences were submitted to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/</ext-link>), under Accession Number SRP144478.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Animal performance and rumen fermentation parameters</title><p id="Par14">As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, HC feeding significantly decreased dry matter intake, milk production, ruminal pH value and the concentrations of thiamine and acetate in rumen fluid, while significantly increased the concentration of propionate and isovalerate compared with CON diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). However, these changes caused by HC diet were inversed by thiamine supplementation (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Butyrate, valerate, isobutyrate and total VFA concentrations were not affected by dietary treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Effects of high-concentrate diet feeding and thiamine supplementation on average dry matter intake (DMI), milk production, ruminal pH, ruminal thiamine content and ruminal VFAs content</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Item</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Experimental treatments</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">SEM</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">CON</th><th align="left">HC</th><th align="left">HCT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Average daily DMI (kg/day)</td><td char="." align="char">21.68<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">19.07<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">20.78<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.278</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Average daily milk production (kg/day)</td><td char="." align="char">27.28<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">22.12<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">23.28<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.894</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ruminal pH</td><td char="." align="char">6.45<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">5.58<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">6.12<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.194</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ruminal Thiamine (&#x000b5;g/L)</td><td char="." align="char">16.16<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">9.51<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">13.53<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.933</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Acetate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">43.237<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">42.619<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">44.076<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.273</td><td char="." align="char">0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Propionate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">12.899<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">13.849<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">11.846<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.632</td><td char="." align="char">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Butyrate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">10.770</td><td char="." align="char">10.354</td><td char="." align="char">10.819</td><td char="." align="char">0.137</td><td char="." align="char">0.356</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isovalerate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">1.403<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.670<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.366<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.059</td><td char="." align="char">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Valerate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">1.212</td><td char="." align="char">1.491</td><td char="." align="char">1.332</td><td char="." align="char">0.059</td><td char="." align="char">0.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isobutyrate (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">0.802</td><td char="." align="char">1.001</td><td char="." align="char">1.047</td><td char="." align="char">0.083</td><td char="." align="char">0.504</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TVFA (mmol/L)</td><td char="." align="char">70.323</td><td char="." align="char">70.983</td><td char="." align="char">70.487</td><td char="." align="char">1.836</td><td char="." align="char">0.156</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SEM, standard error of the mean; CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with thiamine, TVFA, total volatile fatty acid</p><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Means within a row with different letters differ significantly (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Sequencing information</title><p id="Par15">In the present study, 12 metagenomic libraries were constructed. Based on the quality control methods, all pollution data were removed and approximately 45,000,000 reads of per sample were acquired. The GC content of each sample was between 40&#x02013;60% except HCT4, which had a lower GC content of 36.36%. The assembly results showed that a minimum of 130,000 contigs per sample were obtained. The N50 value was between 760 and 890&#x000a0;bp for the samples (shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The aligned reads were annotated for gene prediction. The results indicated that numbers of prediction genes were mostly between 200,000 and 400,000. However sample HC3 was detected to contain a significant higher prediction gene numbers while sample HCT4 contained a significant lower prediction gene numbers.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Quantitative information and quality control of sequencing</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Sample</th><th align="left">Total reads</th><th align="left">Average read length (bp)</th><th align="left">Contigs</th><th align="left">Prediction genes</th><th align="left">N50</th><th align="left">N90</th><th align="left">GC content (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">CON1</td><td char="." align="char">38,117,710</td><td char="." align="char">144.14</td><td char="." align="char">136,750</td><td char="." align="char">243,399</td><td char="." align="char">873</td><td char="." align="char">402</td><td char="." align="char">49.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CON2</td><td char="." align="char">46,684,704</td><td char="." align="char">142.97</td><td char="." align="char">150,605</td><td char="." align="char">261,343</td><td char="." align="char">855</td><td char="." align="char">393</td><td char="." align="char">49.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CON3</td><td char="." align="char">60,005,524</td><td char="." align="char">144.36</td><td char="." align="char">205,536</td><td char="." align="char">355,099</td><td char="." align="char">837</td><td char="." align="char">387</td><td char="." align="char">48.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CON4</td><td char="." align="char">49,418,758</td><td char="." align="char">144.54</td><td char="." align="char">185,420</td><td char="." align="char">305,814</td><td char="." align="char">882</td><td char="." align="char">426</td><td char="." align="char">51.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HC1</td><td char="." align="char">41,149,472</td><td char="." align="char">142.33</td><td char="." align="char">130,666</td><td char="." align="char">258,388</td><td char="." align="char">891</td><td char="." align="char">369</td><td char="." align="char">50.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HC2</td><td char="." align="char">45,783,576</td><td char="." align="char">144.8</td><td char="." align="char">164,161</td><td char="." align="char">360,929</td><td char="." align="char">762</td><td char="." align="char">297</td><td char="." align="char">46.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HC3</td><td char="." align="char">66,780,112</td><td char="." align="char">144.91</td><td char="." align="char">266,675</td><td char="." align="char">539,128</td><td char="." align="char">813</td><td char="." align="char">327</td><td char="." align="char">47.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HC4</td><td char="." align="char">38,925,364</td><td char="." align="char">144.97</td><td char="." align="char">140,820</td><td char="." align="char">280,129</td><td char="." align="char">783</td><td char="." align="char">321</td><td char="." align="char">47.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCT1</td><td char="." align="char">51,513,440</td><td char="." align="char">144.22</td><td char="." align="char">177,350</td><td char="." align="char">270,252</td><td char="." align="char">897</td><td char="." align="char">447</td><td char="." align="char">41.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCT2</td><td char="." align="char">56,614,214</td><td char="." align="char">143.39</td><td char="." align="char">180,487</td><td char="." align="char">283,991</td><td char="." align="char">879</td><td char="." align="char">423</td><td char="." align="char">43.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCT3</td><td char="." align="char">44,973,212</td><td char="." align="char">144.28</td><td char="." align="char">161,734</td><td char="." align="char">254,637</td><td char="." align="char">861</td><td char="." align="char">402</td><td char="." align="char">41.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCT4</td><td char="." align="char">38,932,060</td><td char="." align="char">143.7</td><td char="." align="char">132,493</td><td char="." align="char">180,726</td><td char="." align="char">867</td><td char="." align="char">456</td><td char="." align="char">36.36</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with thiamine</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Effect of HC feeding and thiamine supplementation on relative abundance of fungal communities</title><p id="Par16">Principal coordinates analysis (PCoA) based on unweighted UniFrac distance metrics were conducted to compare the three treatments. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, PCoA axes 1 and 2 accounted for 94.24% and 1.19% of the total variation, respectively. The cows offered HC separated from those offered CON and HCT by PCo1 effectively. Similarly, cows fed CON separated from those fed with HCT by PCo2.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) of fungi community structures of the ruminal fungi in CON, HC and HCT groups. CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with 180&#x000a0;mg thiamine/kg DMI</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2018_680_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par17">In the present study, approximately 1050 species of rumen fungi were identified across all samples in seven characterized phyla and one uncharacterized phylum. All taxonomy results are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Excel. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <italic>Ascomycota, Basidiomycota</italic> and <italic>Chytridiomycota</italic> were the three most phyla for all three treatments. Relative abundance of <italic>Ascomycota</italic> was significantly higher in HC treatment than the other two treatments. <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic>, characterized as a phylum of strictly anaerobic fungi, was identified including 3 genera (<italic>g__Neocallimastix, g__Orpinomyces,</italic> and <italic>g__Piromyces</italic>) and 11 species (<italic>s__Neocallimastix_frontalis, s__Neocallimastix_patriciarum, s__Orpinomyces_joyonii, s__Orpinomyces_sp._C1A, s__Orpinomyces_sp._OUS1, s__Orpinomyces_sp._PC</italic>-<italic>2, s__Orpinomyces_sp._ukk1, s__Piromyces_equi, s__Piromyces_sp,</italic> and <italic>s__Piromyces_sp._E2</italic>) (shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). All identified fungi and their relative abundances in the level of phyla are displayed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. HC feeding significantly decreased the abundance of all phyla of fungi (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) when compared with CON treatment. In contrast, thiamine supplementation significantly increased the abundance of all phyla of fungi (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with HC treatment.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Relative abundance of each ruminal fungi phylum for CON, HC and HCT treatments. CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with 180&#x000a0;mg thiamine/kg DMI</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2018_680_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Effect of high-concentrate diet feeding and thiamine supplementation on relative abundances of fungi phylum in rumen fluid (%)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Item</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Experimental treatments</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">SEM</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">CON</th><th align="left">HC</th><th align="left">HCT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Ascomycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.339<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.107<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">2.040<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.266</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Basidiomycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.116<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.013<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.677<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.090</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Blastocladiomycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.014<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.001<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.092<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.012</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Chytridiomycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.073<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.002<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.506<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.068</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Microsporidia</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.026<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.002<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.175<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.029</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Fungi_noname</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.130<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.015<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.851<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.114</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Glomeromycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.049<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.006<sup>c</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.294<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.039</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>p__Neocallimastigomycota</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0.007<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.002<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.035<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SEM, standard error of the mean; CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with thiamine</p><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Means within a row with different letters differ significantly (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par18">Hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) and heat map analysis was conducted to further understand the effects of HC feeding and thiamine supplementation on ruminal fungi profile. Because little information of fungi phyla was detected, taxonomy level of classes and species were used for HCA and heat map analysis. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, samples of HCT treatment gathered into a cluster which was significantly separated from the other two treatments no matter at the level of class or species. Samples of HC treatment were separated from those of CON at the level of class but not at the level of species. Across all three treatments, classes of <italic>Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Chytridiomycota</italic>, and <italic>Blastocladiomycota</italic> gathered into a big cluster. At the species level, species of <italic>Mucorales</italic> gathered into a big cluster and <italic>Saccharomyces_cerevisiae</italic> which is often used in dairy feed, gathered into a single cluster.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) and heat map analysis on relative abundances of ruminal fungi content from three treatments: CON, control diet; HC, high-concentrate diet; HCT, high-concentrate diet supplemented with 180&#x000a0;mg thiamine/kg DMI. <bold>a</bold> HCA and heat map analysis on relative abundances of fungi class in rumen fluid; <bold>b</bold> HCA and heat map analysis on top 30 relative abundances of fungi species in rumen fluid. Rows represent fungi and columns represent samples. Cells were colored based on the relative abundance of fungi measured in rumen, red represents high rumen levels while green represents low signal intensity and black cells showing the intermediate level</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2018_680_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Correlations between fungi communities and ruminal variables</title><p id="Par19">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the relative abundance of all phyla was negatively correlated with the concentration of TVFA, acetate, propionate and isovalerate (r&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.55, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). In particular, <italic>Chytridiomycota</italic> was positively correlated with butyrate concentration (r&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.55, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). There was a trend that the abundances of all phyla of fungi were positively correlated with ruminal pH and thiamine content (r&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.55, 0.10&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Similarly, all the top 20 species of fungi had significantly negative correlated to TVFA, acetate, propionate and isovalerate (r&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.55, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Whilst, <italic>Tetrapisispora_blattae</italic> and <italic>Allomyces_macrogynus</italic> both had positively relationships with butyrate content (r&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.55, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). In addition, a trend was also found that the abundances of all the top 20 species of fungi were positively correlated with ruminal pH and thiamine content (r&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.55, 0.10&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Correlation analyses between relative abundances of fungi and ruminal VFA concentration, thiamine concentrations, and pH. <bold>a</bold> Correlation analyses between relative abundances of fungi phyla and ruminal VFA concentration, thiamine concentrations, and pH. <bold>b</bold> Correlation analyses between relative abundances of fungi species and ruminal VFA concentration, thiamine concentrations, and pH. The red represents a negative correlation, the green color represents a positive correlation. *Represents strong correlation (|r|&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.55, P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2018_680_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Composition of ruminal fungi</title><p id="Par20">In the present study 7 phyla and almost 1050 species were identified, the sequencing depth and data size were improved when compared with previous studies (Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2015</xref>; Mercado-Garcia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>; O&#x02019;Malley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2014</xref>), and many species of the rumen fungi were first reported such as <italic>Blastocladiomycota, Chytridiomycota, Microsporidia</italic> and <italic>Glomeromycota</italic> result. The proportion of <italic>Ascomycota</italic> in the whole 7 phyla of fungi in HC treatment significantly increased compared with that in the other two treatments, which indicated that phylum <italic>Ascomycota</italic> had better resistibility to the changed condition caused by HC diet. As the most representative species of <italic>Ascomycota</italic>, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> was always used as the additive to alleviate subacute ruminal acidosis in lactating dairy cows (Alzahal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2014</xref>), and the result further elaborated the function of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> in alleviating SARA (Alzahal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2014</xref>). <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic>, although took up a small proportion, attracted more attention in the rumen microbiome (Hibbett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR500">2007</xref>) because of its strictly anaerobic characterization and the ability of producing wide array of cell-bound and cell-free cellulolytic, hemicellulolytic, glycolytic, and proteolytic enzymes (Liggenstoffer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2010</xref>). Sequencing and functional researches of <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic> were proceeded in recent years in order to explore the mechanism of its functions in rumen such as the high-throughput expressed sequence tag (EST) analysis of <italic>Neocallimastix frontalis</italic> (Mi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2009</xref>) and the analysis of the <italic>Orpinomyces</italic> genome (Youssef et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2013</xref>). The results of the present study that the proportion of <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic> was increased after thiamine supplementation in the whole rumen micro-biomass may provide useful information in investigating the mechanism of <italic>Neocallimastigomycota.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Effect of thiamine supplementation on ruminal fungi composition</title><p id="Par21">In the present study, HC significantly decreased the abundance of fungi (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with CON treatment. This finding was in line with several previous studies in which a greater fungal diversity and higher fungal abundance were detected in animals fed high-fiber diets than those offered high-grain diets (Belanche et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>; Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2015</xref>). The main function of rumen fungi is to degrade diet fiber and product absorbable compounds for the host animal (Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2003</xref>; Theodorou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1996</xref>). Because of the higher gain and lower fiber content in HC, less substrates were provided for fungi growth, therefore leading to the decreased abundance of rumen fungi in HC treatment.</p><p id="Par22">However, the fungal abundance increased significantly after thiamine supplementation in HC treatment which indicated that thiamine supplementation promoted the proliferation and metabolism of rumen fungi. Thiamine is an essential nutrient for dairy cows and plays important roles in carbohydrate metabolism (Kamke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>; Subramanya et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2010</xref>). The promotion of carbohydrate metabolism and its interaction with ruminal microbiome might have contribute to the increased fungal abundance.</p><p id="Par23">In ruminal anaerobic environment, ruminal fungi energy generation organelles are represented by hydrogenosomes. These organelles, under anoxic conditions, decarboxylate malate into acetate, CO2 and H2 with concomitant production of energy in the form of ATP (Van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2010</xref>; Yarlett and Hackstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2005</xref>). Rumen fungi exhibit tremendous diversity of CAZymes, which work together to degrade carbohydrates and cellulose into monosaccharides and then the monosaccharides are further hydrolyzed into pyruvate (Hall and Mertens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>). As the cofactor of pyruvate formate-lyase (PFL) and pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase (PFO), thiamine supplementation promoted the reaction of pyruvate generating into acetyl-CoA (Xue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2018</xref>), enhanced the utilization of pyruvate and promoted the degradation efficiency of carbohydrates which lead to more ATP formed to support the metabolism and proliferation of ruminal fungi in the current study. Besides, thiamine supplementation significantly decreased rumen VFAs content and increased ruminal pH (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2016</xref>), which promoted the activity of CAZymes (Fliegerova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>). Therefore, fungal abundance significantly increased in the current study.</p><p id="Par24">Interaction with other microorganisms may also contribute to the change of ruminal fungi. Ruminal microorganism works in harmony to keep the health and productivity of ruminants (Hobson and Stewart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1997</xref>; Mickdam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2016</xref>). In particular, many positive associations were observed between fungi and bacteria, such as <italic>Caecomyces1</italic>&#x02014;<italic>Ruminococcus1</italic> and <italic>Piromyces3</italic>&#x02014;<italic>Succiniclasticum</italic> (Smidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2010</xref>; Tapio et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2017</xref>). Thiamine was detected to induce a significant increase of fungal growth in fungi and bacteria co-culture system (Shimizu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>) which indicated that thiamine promoted the mutualism of fungi and bacteria. In addition, previous study of our team indicated that HC significantly decreased the abundance of <italic>Bacteroides</italic> and <italic>Ruminococcus 1</italic> (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>). As stated above, the decreased <italic>Ruminococcus 1</italic> may partly contribute to the decreased rumen fungi in HC treatment. Thiamine supplementation stimulated the growth of the lactate utilizing bacteria <italic>Ruminococcus 1</italic> (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>), and thus increased the abundance of rumen fungi indirectly.</p><p id="Par25">In conclusion, HC significantly decreased while thiamine supplementation significantly increased the abundance of rumen fungi. These results indicated that thiamine supplementation may effectively attenuate rumen metabolic disorder caused by HC diet through buffering the ruminal pH, shifting the rumen fermentation pattern and increasing the abundance of ruminal fungi. The findings in this study could therefore contribute to the further understanding of the mechanism of thiamine&#x02019;s function in dairy cows and provide effective strategies to improve dairy cows&#x02019; health under high-concentrate feeding regime.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec18"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13568_2018_680_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Ingredient and chemical composition of the experimental diets.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13568_2018_680_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2.</bold> Raw data of DMI and milk production.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13568_2018_680_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3.</bold> Taxonomy results of ruminal fungi.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>FX, XP and BX designed the study. FX and Fuyu Sun conducted the experiment. FX, LJ, YG and XN analyzed the data. FX wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par26">We thank the Beijing Key Laboratory for Dairy Cow Nutrition, Beijing University of Agriculture, Beijing, China for supporting the experimental equipment. We sincerely thank Dr. Yiguang Zhao for the contribution to English editing. This study was funded by the Project of National Nature Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31572435) and the National Key Research and Development Plan (2016YFD0700205, 2016YFD0700201).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par27">All authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par28">All the raw sequences were submitted to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/</ext-link>), under Accession Number SRP144478.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par29">All authors carefully read and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par30">This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals performed by any of the authors.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par31">The study was funded by the Project of National Nature Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31572435) and the National Key Research and Development Plan (2016YFD0700205, 2016YFD0700201).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par32">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alzahal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionissopoulos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Laarman</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcbride</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active dry <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> can alleviate the effect of subacute ruminal acidosis in lactating dairy cows</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>7751</fpage><lpage>7763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2014-8212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25282426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aronesty</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of sequencing utility programs</article-title><source>Open Bioinform J</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1875036201307010001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Okubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsurumaru</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metaproteomic identification of <italic>Diazotrophic Methanotrophs</italic> and their localization in root tissues of field-grown rice plants</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>5043</fpage><lpage>5052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00969-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24928870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belanche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Doreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorby</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinloche</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shifts in the rumen microbiota due to the type of carbohydrate and level of protein ingested by dairy cattle are associated with changes in rumen fermentation</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2012</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1684</fpage><lpage>1692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.112.159574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22833657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaucheyras-Durand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment of cellulolytic bacteria and development of fermentative activities in the rumen of gnotobiotically-reared lambs receiving the microbial additive <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae CNCM I</italic>-<italic>1077</italic></article-title><source>Reprod Nutr Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/rnd:2001112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11368245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enemark</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The monitoring, prevention and treatment of sub-acute ruminal acidosis (SARA): a review</article-title><source>Vet J</source><year>2008</year><volume>1997</volume><issue>176</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2007.12.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Purvis</surname><given-names>HT</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukharnikov</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Krehbiel</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Desilva</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rumen microbial population dynamics during adaptation to a high-grain diet</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>7482</fpage><lpage>7490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00388-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20851965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fliegerova</surname><given-names>Katerina</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaerger</surname><given-names>Kerstin</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>Kerstin</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rumen Fungi</article-title><source>Rumen Microbiology: From Evolution to Revolution</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer India</publisher-name><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 100-year review: carbohydrates-characterization, digestion, and utilization</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>10078</fpage><lpage>10093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29153156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR500"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hibbett</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Huhndorf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;cking</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A higher-level phylogenetic classification of the Fungi</article-title><source>Mycol Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mycres.2007.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><source>The rumen microbial ecosystem</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Flade</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Hadidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruscheweyh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tappu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGAN community edition&#x02014;interactive exploration and analysis of large-scale microbiome sequencing Data</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e1004957</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27327495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavendale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Froula</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on thiaminase of fungi</article-title><source>J Vitaminol</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavendale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Froula</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rumen metagenome and metatranscriptome analyses of low methane yield sheep reveals a Sharpea-enriched microbiome characterised by lactic acid formation and utilisation</article-title><source>Microbiome</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-016-0201-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27760570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Indugu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchiarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitta</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associative patterns among anaerobic fungi, methanogenic archaea, and bacterial communities in response to changes in diet and age in the rumen of dairy cows</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>781</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26284058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of lignocellulosic biomass by enzymes from anaerobic fungi</article-title><source>Abstr Pap Am Chem S</source><year>2003</year><volume>225</volume><fpage>U274</fpage><lpage>U274</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>De novo assembly of human genomes with massively parallel short read sequencing</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.097261.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liggenstoffer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Couger</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshahed</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic diversity and community structure of anaerobic gut fungi (phylum <italic>Neocallimastigomycota</italic>) in ruminant and non-ruminant herbivores</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1225</fpage><lpage>1235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2010.49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiome-metabolome analysis reveals unhealthy alterations in the composition and metabolism of ruminal microbiota with increasing dietary grain in a goat model</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25471302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Derakhshani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Khafipour</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Loor</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of subacute ruminal acidosis affects the ruminal microbiome and epithelium</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>701</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27242724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27242724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercado-Garcia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellulose degradation in anaerobic condition by filament fungi</article-title><source>Faseb J</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>Ib245</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongseog</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of functional genes in carbohydrate metabolic pathway of anaerobic rumen fungus <italic>Neocallimastix frontalis PMA02</italic></article-title><source>Asian Aust J Anim Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1555</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2009.80371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mickdam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Khiaosa-Ard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Metzler-Zebeli</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><name><surname>Klevenhusen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chizzola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zebeli</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rumen microbial abundance and fermentation profile during severe subacute ruminal acidosis and its modulation by plant derived alkaloids in vitro</article-title><source>Anaerobe</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2016.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26868619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Henske</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Haitjema</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering anaerobic gut fungi for the production of fuels and bioactive compounds</article-title><source>Abstr Pap Am Chem S</source><year>2014</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>1155</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orpin</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the rumen flagellate Neocallimastix frontalis</article-title><source>J Gen Microbiol</source><year>1976</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-91-2-249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between thiamine and subacute ruminal acidosis induced by a high-grain diet in dairy cows</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>8790</fpage><lpage>8801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2016-10865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illumina sequencing approach to characterize thiamine metabolism related bacteria and the impacts of thiamine supplementation on ruminal microbiota in dairy cows fed high-grain diets</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1818</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbohydrate fermentation by three species of polycentric ruminal fungi from cattle and water buffalo in tropical Australia</article-title><source>Anaerobe</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1075-9964(95)80418-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16887506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitta</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Indugu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchiarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhukya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metagenomic assessment of the functional potential of the rumen microbiome in Holstein dairy cows</article-title><source>Anaerobe</source><year>2016</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2015.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26700882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A metagenome-wide association study of gut microbiota in type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>490</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Prifti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Chatelier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Batto</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations of the human gut microbiome in liver cirrhosis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>513</volume><issue>7516</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25079328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezaeian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beakes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and estimation of anaerobic zoosporic fungi along the digestive tracts of sheep</article-title><source>Mycol Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0953756204000929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15535073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sekhavati</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassiry</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesgaran</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavasoli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applying slide-cover-glass method for cultivating anaerobic rumen fungi and employing polymerase chain reaction technique for their molecular identification</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>488</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thiamine synthesis regulates the fermentation mechanisms in the fungus <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title><source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source><year>2016</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1768</fpage><lpage>1775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09168451.2016.1158631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26967817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanya</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic alcohol consumption and intestinal thiamin absorption: effects on physiological and molecular parameters of the uptake process</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00132.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanya</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic alcohol consumption and intestinal thiamin absorption: effects on physiological and molecular parameters of the uptake process</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00132.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Negussie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shingfield</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taxon abundance, diversity, co-occurrence and network analysis of the ruminal microbiota in response to dietary changes in dairy cows</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0180260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28704445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theodorou</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mennim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinci</surname><given-names>APJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anaerobic fungi in the digestive tract of mammalian herbivores and their potential for exploitation</article-title><source>P Nutr Soc</source><year>1996</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS19960088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Lima E</given-names></name><name><surname>Deminicis</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cez&#x000e1;rio</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspects of acidosis in ruminants with a focus on nutrition: a review</article-title><source>J Agric Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>90</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>DGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogenosomes and mitosomes: conservation and evolution of functions</article-title><source>J Eukaryot Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GC-MS analysis of the ruminal metabolome response to thiamine supplementation during high grain feeding in dairy cows</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-018-1362-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29770108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yarlett</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackstein</surname><given-names>JHP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogenosomes: one organelle, multiple origins</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2005</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2005)055[0657:HOOMO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;r&#x00131;m</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of biogas potential of anaerobic digesters using rumen fungi</article-title><source>Renew Energy</source><year>2017</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2017.03.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Couger</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Struchtemeyer</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liggenstoffer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prade</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Atiyeh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshahed</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of the anaerobic fungus <italic>Orpinomyces</italic> sp. <italic>strain C1A</italic> reveals the unique evolutionary history of a remarkable plant biomass degrader</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>4620</fpage><lpage>4634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00821-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23709508</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>