<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7028950</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">59839</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-59839-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genomic scan of selective sweeps in Djallonk&#x000e9; (West African Dwarf) sheep shed light on adaptation to harsh environments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>Isabel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>Iv&#x000e1;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Amadou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Pardal</surname><given-names>Luc&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Men&#x000e9;ndez-Arias</surname><given-names>Nuria A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6872-1045</contrib-id><name><surname>Goyache</surname><given-names>F&#x000e9;lix</given-names></name><address><email>fgoyache@serida.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0625 911X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419063.9</institution-id><institution>Servicio Regional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Desarrollo Agroalimentario, </institution></institution-wrap>E-33394 Gij&#x000f3;n, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0570 9190</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.434777.4</institution-id><institution>Institut de l&#x02019;Environnement et des Recherches Agricoles (INERA), </institution></institution-wrap>Ouagadougou, 04 BP 8645 Burkina Faso </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1503 7226</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5808.5</institution-id><institution>CIBIO - InBIO, Universidade do Porto, </institution></institution-wrap>4485-661 Vair&#x000e3;o, Portugal </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>2824</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The Djallonk&#x000e9; (West African Dwarf) sheep is a small-sized haired sheep resulting from a costly evolutionary process of natural adaptation to the harsh environment of West Africa including trypanosome challenge. However, genomic studies carried out in this sheep are scant. In this research, genomic data of 184 Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep (and 12 Burkina-Sahel sheep as an outgroup) generated using medium-density SNP Chips were analyzed. Three different statistics (iHS, XP-EHH and nSL) were applied to identify candidate selection sweep regions spanning genes putatively associated with adaptation of sheep to the West African environment. A total of 207 candidate selection sweep regions were defined. Gene-annotation enrichment and functional annotation analyses allowed to identify three statistically significant functional clusters involving 12 candidate genes. Genes included in Functional Clusters associated to selection signatures were mainly related to metabolic response to stress, including regulation of oxidative and metabolic stress and thermotolerance. The bovine chromosomal areas carrying QTLs for cattle trypanotolerance were compared with the regions on which the orthologous functional candidate cattle genes were located. The importance of cattle BTA4 for trypanotolerant response might have been conserved between species. The current research provides new insights on the genomic basis for adaptation and highlights the importance of obtaining information from non-cosmopolite livestock populations managed in harsh environments.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Population genetics</kwd><kwd>Functional genomics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>MICIIN-FEDER AGL2016-77813-R. CompGen</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>SFRH/BPD/94518/2013</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Drift and selection may cause selective sweep signatures on the genome, characterized by reduced diversity and extensive linkage disequilibrium. Favorable alleles increase in frequency more rapidly than expected for a neutral genetic scenario and further alter the allele frequencies of genomic variants near the beneficial mutation. The identification of signatures of selection has been carried out on several sheep breeds using genome-wide single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Most analyses allowed to identify signatures of positive selection for economically important traits such as parasite resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, dairy production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, meat yield and growth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, fat metabolism and deposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> or reproduction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Other traits affecting breeds&#x02019; definition such as morphology, horn shape or coat color have caused selective sweeps on the sheep genome as well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">However, there is an increasing interest in identifying selection signatures caused by human-mediated selection pressure for adaptation to different environmental conditions contrasting in climate (mainly precipitations and temperature), vegetation and altitude<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. This approach allows to identify sheep populations (or breeds) more robustly suited to future climate changes and to obtain new insights on the history of the species after domestication.</p><p id="Par4">Domestication and dissemination of sheep is a complex process, initiated about 11,000 years before present (yBP), which included different waves, specialization for different production goals and adaptation to different environmental conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. When compared with Northern Africa, the initial appearance of pastoralist communities based on small stock in Sub-Saharan West Africa may have been delayed by thousand years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Reviewing the literature, Muiga and Hanotte<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> suggested that domestic sheep entered into central Nile valley and central Sahara around 6,000 yBP reaching West Africa by 3,700 yBP. This lag in successful introduction of small ruminant livestock into West Africa stems from new animal diseases encountered by pastoral colonists entering biogeographic zones south of the Sahel, namely trypanosomiasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Native West African domestic ruminants (cattle, sheep and goat) share distinctive traits, namely trypanotolerance and small size. These species were subject to similar processes of adaptation to an extremely difficult environmental scenario and to trypanosome challenge<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Djallonk&#x000e9; (West African Dwarf) sheep<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> are a small sized haired sheep population spread in the humid West and Central African regions. Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep have the ability to maintain undepressed production and reproduction performance under parasite challenge even in the presence of a persistent parasitaemia. Therefore, they are considered resilient to trypanosome challenge<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Most studies aiming at the identification of selective sweeps on the sheep genome have been carried out using highly structured populations including different cosmopolitan (commercial) and local sheep breeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Although there exist methodologies accounting for population structuring, such as hapFLK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, genetic heterogeneity amongst breeds carrying distinct mutations with similar phenotypic effects may lead selective sweeps to not reach statistical significance, particularly when sample size is moderate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">In this research, genomic data generated using medium-density Chips on a sample of Burkina Faso Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep were assessed to identify candidate selection sweep regions spanning genes associated with different biological pathways putatively involved in the adaptation of sheep to the environmental conditions of the humid areas of West Africa. The genomic profile of this population, compared with that of a small sample of Burkina-Sahel sheep when necessary, was explored for signatures of selection using various Extended Haplotype Homozygosity (EHH-)based statistics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The corresponding cattle orthologous genomic regions were compared with the bovine chromosomal areas in which Quantitative Traits Loci (QTL) for trypanotolerance&#x02013;related traits have been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sample used</title><p id="Par8">A total of 184 DNA samples of Djallonk&#x000e9; lambs (64 males and 120 females) previously analyzed using microsatellites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> were available. Up to 166 individuals were sampled in the surroundings of Mangodara (latitude 9&#x000b0;53&#x02032;59.99&#x02033;N; longitude 4&#x000b0;20&#x02032;59.99&#x02033;W; Como&#x000e9; province), southern Burkina Faso. The other 18 individuals (9 males and 9 females) were sampled in D&#x000e9;dougou (latitude 12&#x000b0;27&#x02032;48.17&#x02033;N; longitude 3&#x000b0;27&#x02032;38.7&#x02033;W; Mouhoun province), southwestern Burkina Faso. Both sampling areas belong to the environmental Sudan-Guinea Savannah humid region (tse-tse challenged) of Burkina Faso<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The Sudan-Guinea Savannah environmental region has annual rainfall higher than 900 millimeters (with precipitations in Mangodara and D&#x000e9;dougou varying from 1,000 to 1,200 millimeters per year), predominance of woodlands and savannahs, and temperatures varying from 19&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 36&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Additionally, 12 individuals belonging to the Burkina-Sahel sheep breed were sampled in the surroundings of Dori (latitude 14&#x000b0;02&#x02032;7.44&#x02033;N; longitude 0&#x000b0;02&#x02032;4.20&#x02033;E; S&#x000e9;no Province), located on the arid environmental Sahel region of Northern Burkina Faso, to be used as an outgroup. The Sahel environmental region has less than 600 millimeters of rainfall per year, temperatures varying from 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 43&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and bushy vegetation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Morphological and genetic description of both the Djallonk&#x000e9; and the Burkina-Sahel sheep populations of Burkina Faso is available in the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The management of the Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep of Burkina Faso has been described as well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Sheep breeding in Burkina Faso is based on small-holders and carried out in extensive conditions with no supplementation. In the Sudan-Sahel environmental area, animals perform communal grazing of native pasture with no restrictions during the dry season and about 12&#x02009;hours a day during the rainy season. In the Sahel area, management system is traditional and extensive with little or no management inputs: shelter or minerals. Sheep are managed by their owners (Fulani ethnic group). Communal grazing is less frequent. In all cases, use of fodder crops and conserved forages is negligible. Planned matings are not usual.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>SNP genotyping and quality control</title><p id="Par9">The whole dataset was typed using the Ovine 50&#x02009;K SNP BeadChip following standard protocols (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.illumina.com">http://www.illumina.com</ext-link>). The software GenomeStudio (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) was used to generate standard.ped and map files. Sample and marker-based quality control measures were performed using the program PLINK V 1.09<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. GenCall score cutoff of 0.15 and average sample call rate of 99% were considered. All unmapped SNPs, those mapping to sexual chromosomes, SNPs with a genotyping rate lower than 90% or those below a Minor Allele Frequency threshold of 0.05 were removed. To avoid departures from Hardy-Weinberg proportions due to genotyping errors, SNPs that did not pass Hardy-Weinberg test for P&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.001 were removed as well. A total of 46,977 SNPs located on the 26 ovine autosomes passed the quality control for the whole sample analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Diversity and population structuring analyses</title><p id="Par10">Genetic diversity of the available population was assessed using the software VCFtools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Within subpopulation (Djallonk&#x000e9; and Burkina-Sahel) inbreeding and between subpopulations F<sub>ST</sub> were computed.</p><p id="Par11">A clustering analysis was carried out using the program Admixture v1.23<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> which calculates maximum likelihood estimates of individual ancestries based on data provided by multiple loci. Analyses were conducted for 1&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;K&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;8 being K the number of clusters given the data. The optimal number of clusters was determined via cross-validation as the value of K exhibiting the lower cross-validation error compared to other K values. Data set was divided into 5 folders for each K. Folders were sequentially used as test sets while the other four were used for training.</p><p id="Par12">The program PLINK V 1.09<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> was used to compute Principal Component Analysis (PCA). Eigenvectors computed for each individual were used to construct dispersion plots accounting for the Admixture Cluster to which individuals were assigned. The 75% confidence regions of the relationships among individuals within cluster were illustrated using contour plots. Plots were constructed using the library ggplot2 of R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/">http://CRAN.R-project.org/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification of selective sweeps</title><p id="Par13">Three complementary EHH-based statistics, integrated Haplotype Score<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> (iHS), XP-EHH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> and nSL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, were used to assess genome-wide signatures of selection in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep. These three approaches were proposed to overcome the main concern affecting the original EHH test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> i.e. the yield of a high number of false positives due to the strong influence on results of the demographic history of the population under studied.</p><p id="Par14">The iHS test compares the EHH between derived and ancestral alleles within a population searching for loci where the derived allele resides on a longer haplotype than the ancestral allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. In this way, the iHS values are less affected by the demographic history of the population and are more suitable for identifying incomplete sweeps, where the selected allele is not fixed in the sample.</p><p id="Par15">The XP-EHH test compares the frequencies of the selected haplotypes between two populations to detect ongoing or nearly fixed selection signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Therefore, the XP-EHH test is more robust than the EHH statistics in scenarios of complete selective sweeps. This test has an increased power to detect selection signatures using small sample sizes and allows to use groups of genetically similar populations.</p><p id="Par16">In contrast to iHS and XP-EHH, which measures the length of haplotypes in terms of genetic distance and thereby uses recombination, the nSL statistics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> measures haplotype lengths in terms of the number of segregating sites in the sample, making it more robust to recombination rate variations. In addition, although both iHS and nSL target at the identification of incomplete sweeps, the nSL statistic has improved power in detecting soft sweeps<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par17">Both large positive and negative iHS, XP-EHH and nSL scores were considered potentially informative. Although negative iHS scores would mean that a derived allele would have swept up in frequency and, therefore, could be considered of more interest, large positive values can indicate that ancestral alleles hitchhike with the selected site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Furthermore, scenarios in which selection switch to favor an ancestral allele cannot be discarded. Similar rationale can be applied to the recombination-free counterpart of iHS, the nSL test. In the case of XP-EHH scores large positive and negative values would identify selection events in the studied population and in the reference population, respectively. Both cases are informative in scenarios of poor differentiation.</p><p id="Par18">All estimates were carried out using the program <italic>selscan</italic> v.1.0.4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://github.com/szpiech/selscan">http://github.com/szpiech/selscan</ext-link>, fitting the parameters recommended by the authors: maximum EHH extension in bp (&#x0201c;&#x02013;max-extend&#x0201d; option) 1000000, maximum gap allowed between two SNPs in bp (&#x0201c;&#x02013;max-gap&#x0201d; option) 200000, EHH decay cutoff (&#x0201c;&#x02013;cutoff&#x0201d; option) 0.05. Whatever the statistics computed, the output results for each SNP were frequency-normalized over all chromosomes using the program <italic>norm</italic>, provided with <italic>selscan</italic>. This normalization was carried out using default parameters as well: number of frequency bins (&#x0201c;&#x02013;bins&#x0201d; option) 100. As implemented by default in the program <italic>norm</italic>, normalized values higher than |2| were used to identify SNPs under selection.</p><p id="Par19">The program <italic>selscan</italic> is &#x02018;dumb&#x02019; with respect ancestral/derived alleles, simply assigning the &#x0201c;reference&#x0201d; allele depending on previous arbitrary allele coding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Unstandardized iHS scores are then computed as ln(iHH1/iHH0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, being iHH the integrated haplotype homozygosity for the ancestral (0) and derived (1) haplotypes. There is empirical evidence suggesting that iHS values obtained from a given subset of SNPs with or without ancestral allele information (i.e. random assignment) are highly consistent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Therefore, this has been proved to be a reliable strategy.</p><p id="Par20">Previous studies aiming at the ascertainment of the genomic diversity in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep used as reference population Sahel sheep sampled in the same geographical area<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Therefore, Burkina-Sahel individuals were used for the XP-EHH analyses.</p><p id="Par21">Candidate selection sweep regions were defined starting from: a) individual SNPs identified as being under selection by at least two of the statistics applied; and b) adjacent SNPs identified as being under selection by at least two different statistics. Two SNPs were considered adjacent if their 75&#x02009;kb up- or down-stream regions overlapped. All other SNPs identified as being under selection by any statistics with their 75&#x02009;kb up- or down-stream regions sequentially intersecting with the 75&#x02009;kb regions surrounding the SNPs selected using the strategies a) and b) described above were assigned to the corresponding selection sweep region.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Functional characterization of the candidate regions</title><p id="Par22">Candidate genes were considered if their boundaries fell within 75&#x02009;kb up- or down-stream the selection sweep regions defined. Protein-coding genes found within the candidate regions were retrieved from the Ensembl Genes 91 database, based on the Oar v3.1 ovine reference genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.livestockgenomics.csiro.au/sheep/oar3.1.php">http://www.livestockgenomics.csiro.au/sheep/oar3.1.php</ext-link>) using the BioMart tool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. The Ensembl Genes 91 database and the BioMart tool were also used to identify the corresponding orthologous cattle genes, based on the UMD3.1 bovine reference genome. All the identified genes were processed using the functional annotation tool implemented in DAVID Bioinformatics resources 6.8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> to determine enriched functional terms. An enrichment score of 1.3, which is equivalent to the Fisher exact test P-value of 0.05, was used as a threshold to define the significantly enriched functional terms in comparison to the whole bovine reference genome background. Relationships among genomic features in different chromosome positions were represented using the R software package shinyCircos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Overlap with cattle trypanotorelance-related QTLs</title><p id="Par23">The bovine QTLs for trypanotolerance&#x02013;related traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> which were mapped on the bovine Btau 4.0 reference genome assembly were downloaded from the cattle QTL database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.animalgenome.org/cgi-bin/QTLdb/BT/index">http://www.animalgenome.org/cgi-bin/QTLdb/BT/index</ext-link>). The QTL genome coordinates were then re-mapped on the bovine UMD 3.1 reference genome assembly using the NCBI genome remapping online service (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/tools/remap">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/tools/remap</ext-link>). The intersectBed function of the BedTools software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup> was used to overlap these trypanotolerance-related QTLs with the bovine regions on which the orthologous functional ovine candidate genes identified were located.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Genetic diversity and structuring of data</title><p id="Par24">Mean inbreeding (and standard deviation) in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep was of 0.058&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.070. This was higher than the value computed for the Burkina-Sahel sample (0.014&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.020). Differentiation between Djallonk&#x000e9; and Burkina-Sahel sheep, assessed computing weighted Weir and Cockerham&#x02019;s F<sub>ST</sub>, was 0.066.</p><p id="Par25">The results of the admixture analysis informed that the lowest cross-validation error was at K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, differences between cross-validation errors for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 were lower than 0.005. Most Djallonk&#x000e9; individuals (144 for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, 145 for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and 140 for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) grouped into a single Cluster. However, assignment of the Burkina-Sahel individuals into a given Cluster was not clear. No differentiation was found between Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep sampled either in Mangodara or D&#x000e9;dougou. Most D&#x000e9;dougou samples (from 75% for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 to 100% for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) clustered within the main group formed by Mangodara samples.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Plots showing cross-validation errors for each K tested using the program Admixture v1.23, with the lowest error for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 (Plot <bold>A</bold>), and dispersion of the Djallonk&#x000e9; and Burkina&#x02013;Sahel individuals according the two first factors computed via PCA (Plots <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>). Factors 1 and 2 explained 3.2% and 2.4% of the total variance, respectively. Contour plots illustrate the 75% confidence region of the relationships among the individuals assigned to each Cluster identified using Admixture v1.23 for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 (Plot B), K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 (Plot C) and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 (Plot <bold>D</bold>). The location of most Burkina-Sahel individuals is highlighted Furthermore, barplots of individual ancestries estimated using Admixture v1.23 for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 are shown (Plot <bold>E</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_59839_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e656"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">Furthermore, most Burkina-Sahel individuals (10) clustered with Djallonk&#x000e9; individuals for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). Although Burkina-Sahel individuals tended to form particular Clusters for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C,D</xref>), they shared these Clusters with a number of Djallonk&#x000e9; individuals for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 (4) and for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 (7).</p><p id="Par27">PCA identified 19 factors with eigenvalue higher than 1 which accounted for a total of 25.1% of the genetic variance. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the dispersion of the individuals and the 75% confidence region of the relationships between individuals assigned to each Cluster identified using Admixture v1.23. Independently of the number of K considered, PCA did not allow to assess a clear separation of the individuals. This was particularly remarkable for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>) in which the 75% confidence region of dispersion of the individuals assigned to each of the three clusters overlapped. Although this did not happen for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, PCA illustrated a weak structure in the population analyzed: a significant number of individuals assigned to different clusters were highly intermingled in the middle of the plots.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Candidate regions under selection</title><p id="Par28">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the Manhattan plots illustrating the SNPs identified as being under selection pressure on all ovine autosomes according to the three tests assayed. After normalization 974 SNPs (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), 1,633 (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>) and 110 (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>) SNPs were considered to be under selection using the iHS, XP-EHH and nSL tests, respectively.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Manhattan plots summarizing results corresponding to iHS (Plot <bold>A</bold>), XP-EHH (Plot <bold>B</bold>) and nSL (Plot <bold>C</bold>) analyses. SNPs with normalized values higher than |2| are highlighted in green.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_59839_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e707"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">After crossing the output of the three tests applied, a total of 207 candidate selection sweep regions on all autosomes, except for OAR20 and OAR21, were defined (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). These regions comprised a total of 34,957,703&#x02009;bp and 555 different SNPs. Up to 153 SNPs were identified as being under selection by two different statistics. Four chromosomes (OAR1, 2, 3 and 23) gathered 46% of the candidate selection sweep regions.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the candidate selection sweep regions identified per ovine chromosome (OAR).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>OAR</th><th>N</th><th>Length</th><th>n</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>18</td><td>3549100</td><td>67 (10)<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>34</td><td>6581006</td><td>44 (34)</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>27</td><td>5892878</td><td>105 (19)</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>16</td><td>2450404</td><td>45 (12)</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>1845327</td><td>27 (10)</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>10</td><td>2590704</td><td>43 (5)</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>4</td><td>521393</td><td>11 (1)</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>1097043</td><td>17 (5)</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>5</td><td>983744</td><td>17 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>4</td><td>1077755</td><td>16 (9)</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>2</td><td>116626</td><td>2 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>7</td><td>822135</td><td>16 (4)</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>7</td><td>960058</td><td>18 (3)</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>1</td><td>57444</td><td>2 (0)</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>6</td><td>914153</td><td>21 (3)</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>6</td><td>181219</td><td>7 (3)</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>4</td><td>578619</td><td>9 (4)</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>10</td><td>1669082</td><td>27 (7)</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>2</td><td>153579</td><td>3 (1)</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>3</td><td>486195</td><td>7 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>17</td><td>1407368</td><td>34 (11)</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>2</td><td>286693</td><td>3 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>1</td><td>107671</td><td>2 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>4</td><td>627507</td><td>12 (2)</td></tr><tr><td>Totals</td><td>207</td><td>34957703</td><td>555 (153)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The number of selection sweeps identified (N), the sum of their lengths (in bp) and the sum of the SNPs defining them (n) are given per chromosome.</p><p><sup>a</sup>sum of the SNPs identified by two different EHH-based statistics.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Identification of functional candidate genes linked to selection sweeps</title><p id="Par30">Gene-annotation enrichment analysis allowed to identify a total of 491 potential candidate ovine genes in the 75&#x02009;kb up- and down-stream regions surrounding the selection sweep regions defined previously. A full description of these 491 ovine genes, including their identification, description and location is given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>. Details on the corresponding orthologous cattle genes are given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> as well.</p><p id="Par31">Functional annotation conducted on these genes allowed to identify 22 different functional term clusters (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). However, only three functional term clusters were significantly enriched (enrichment score higher than 1.3; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Functional Cluster 1 (enrichment score&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.24) included four genes (<italic>ALB</italic>, <italic>GC</italic>, <italic>AFP</italic> and <italic>AFM</italic>) involved in transport functions of the plasma membrane and homeostasis. Functional Cluster 2 (enrichment score&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.39) included four genes (<italic>MC2R</italic>, <italic>CIB1</italic>, <italic>MC5R</italic> and <italic>CAV1</italic>) involved in angiogenesis, answer to ischemia and hypoxia. Functional Cluster 3 (enrichment score&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.31) included four genes (<italic>LDLRAD4</italic>, <italic>LRP11</italic>, <italic>CFI</italic> and <italic>VLDLR</italic>) involved in lipid metabolism and response to temperature stress.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Significantly enriched functional term clusters (enrichment score higher than 1.3) for genes identified within the 75&#x02009;kb regions flanking the candidate selection sweeps identified using genome-wide iHS, XP-EHH and nSL statistics following DAVID analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Functional Cluster (enrichment score)</th><th>Category</th><th>Term and Description</th><th>Genes</th><th>P-Value</th><th>Fold Enrichment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Cluster 1 (3.24)</td><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR014760:Serum albumin, N-terminal</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000012835 (<italic>GC</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>8.61E-05</td><td>38.40</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR000264:ALB/AFP/VDB</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000012835 (<italic>GC</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>8.61E-05</td><td>38.40</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR020857:Serum albumin, conserved site</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000012835 (<italic>GC</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>8.61E-05</td><td>38.40</td></tr><tr><td/><td>SMART</td><td>SM00103:ALBUMIN</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000012835 (<italic>GC</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>8.81E-05</td><td>37.89</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR020858:Serum albumin-like</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000012835 (<italic>GC</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>1.70E-04</td><td>32.00</td></tr><tr><td/><td>PIR_SUPERFAMILY</td><td>PIRSF002520:serum albumin</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>1.19E-03</td><td>47.29</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR021177:Serum albumin/Alpha-fetoprotein</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>2.51E-03</td><td>36.00</td></tr><tr><td/><td>GOTERM_BP_DIRECT</td><td>GO:0006810~transport</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782 (<italic>ALB</italic>), ENSOARG00000013966 (<italic>AFP</italic>), ENSOARG00000014129 (<italic>AFM</italic>)</td><td>4.33E-01</td><td>2.04</td></tr><tr><td>Cluster 2 (1.39)</td><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR023415:Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) receptor class A, conserved site</td><td>ENSOARG00000003950 (<italic>MC2R</italic>), ENSOARG00000002239 (<italic>MC5R</italic>), ENSOARG00000001337 (<italic>CAV1</italic>)</td><td>1.70E-02</td><td>12.47</td></tr><tr><td/><td>SMART</td><td>SM00192:LDLa</td><td>ENSOARG00000003950 (<italic>MC2R</italic>), ENSOARG00000002239 (<italic>MC5R</italic>), ENSOARG00000001337 (<italic>CAV1</italic>)</td><td>5.20E-02</td><td>8.08</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR002172:Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) receptor class A repeat</td><td>ENSOARG00000003950 (<italic>MC2R</italic>), ENSOARG00000012128 (<italic>CIB1</italic>), ENSOARG00000002239 (<italic>MC5R</italic>), ENSOARG00000001337 (<italic>CAV1</italic>)</td><td>7.59E-02</td><td>4.04</td></tr><tr><td>Cluster 3 (1.31)</td><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR023415:Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) receptor class A, conserved site</td><td>ENSOARG00000002144 (<italic>LDLRAD4</italic>), ENSOARG00000002898 (<italic>LRP11</italic>), ENSOARG00000005291 (<italic>CFI</italic>), ENSOARG00000013303 (<italic>VLDLR</italic>)</td><td>3.83E-02</td><td>5.33</td></tr><tr><td/><td>SMART</td><td>SM00192:LDLa</td><td>ENSOARG00000002144 (<italic>LDLRAD4</italic>), ENSOARG00000002898 (<italic>LRP11</italic>), ENSOARG00000005291 (<italic>CFI</italic>), ENSOARG00000013303 (<italic>VLDLR</italic>)</td><td>5.10E-02</td><td>4.74</td></tr><tr><td/><td>INTERPRO</td><td>IPR002172:Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) receptor class A repeat</td><td>ENSOARG00000002144 (<italic>LDLRAD4</italic>), ENSOARG00000002898 (<italic>LRP11</italic>), ENSOARG00000005291 (<italic>CFI</italic>), ENSOARG00000013303 (<italic>VLDLR</italic>)</td><td>5.96E-02</td><td>4.46</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Circular map, created using the ShinyCircos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> software, summarizing information on Functional Clusters identified using selection sweeps in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep. Chromosomes are shown in the outermost circle. The innermost circles show the distribution of selection sweeps within a chromosome. Differences in height among selection sweeps inform on the number of SNPs defining them. Candidate genes forming the significantly enriched functional term clusters are indicated besides their genomic localization. At the center of the map, links among candidate genes belonging to the same functional cluster are illustrated using the same color.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_59839_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1591"/></fig></p><p id="Par32">A description of the genes involved in the definition of these three functional clusters is given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The four genes forming Functional Cluster 1 were located on OAR6 and in close vicinity spanning a chromosomal area of 87,639&#x02009;bp (from position 88,136,611 to position 88,224,250). Functional Cluster 3 included gene <italic>CFI</italic> which was located on OAR6 as well, although on a distant area. Functional Clusters 2 and 3 had neighboring genes located on OAR23 (genes <italic>MC2R</italic> and <italic>MC5R</italic> for Cluster 2 and gene <italic>LDLRAD4</italic> for Cluster 3) on an area spanning 247,960&#x02009;bp.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Description of the sheep genes included in the three functional clusters displaying enrichment score higher than 1.3.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Functional</th><th colspan="2">Gene</th><th colspan="4">Sheep gene information</th><th colspan="4">Orthologous cattle gene information</th></tr><tr><th>Cluster</th><th>name</th><th>description</th><th>EnsemblID</th><th>OAR</th><th>start</th><th>end</th><th>Cattle EnsemblID</th><th>BTA</th><th>start</th><th>end</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Cluster 1</td><td><italic>ALB</italic></td><td>albumin [Source:NCBI gene;Acc:443393]</td><td>ENSOARG00000013782</td><td>6</td><td>88136611</td><td>88159187</td><td>ENSBTAG00000017121</td><td>6</td><td>90232762</td><td>90251126</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>GC</italic></td><td>GC, vitamin D binding protein [Source:HGNC Symbol;Acc:HGNC:4187]</td><td>ENSOARG00000012835</td><td>6</td><td>86619919</td><td>86657661</td><td>ENSBTAG00000013718</td><td>6</td><td>88695940</td><td>88739180</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>AFP</italic></td><td>alpha fetoprotein [Source:HGNC Symbol;Acc:HGNC:317]</td><td>ENSOARG00000013966</td><td>6</td><td>88166794</td><td>88190190</td><td>ENSBTAG00000017131</td><td>6</td><td>90258976</td><td>90280522</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>AFM</italic></td><td>afamin [Source:HGNC Symbol;Acc:HGNC:316]</td><td>ENSOARG00000014129</td><td>6</td><td>88198267</td><td>88224250</td><td>ENSBTAG00000047833</td><td>6</td><td>90291078</td><td>90312046</td></tr><tr><td>Cluster 2</td><td><italic>MC2R</italic></td><td>melanocortin 2 receptor [Source:NCBI gene;Acc:443482]</td><td>ENSOARG00000003950</td><td>23</td><td>43893855</td><td>43894748</td><td>ENSBTAG00000011038</td><td>24</td><td>44006264</td><td>44024553</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>CIB1</italic></td><td>calcium and integrin binding 1 [Source:NCBI gene;Acc:100141300]</td><td>ENSOARG00000012128</td><td>18</td><td>20723490</td><td>20727112</td><td>ENSBTAG00000021275</td><td>21</td><td>22043354</td><td>22046525</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>MC5R</italic></td><td>Ovis aries melanocortin 5 receptor (MC5R), mRNA. [Source:RefSeq mRNA;Acc:NM_001078656]</td><td>ENSOARG00000002239</td><td>23</td><td>43867867</td><td>43870160</td><td>ENSBTAG00000009143</td><td>24</td><td>43983880</td><td>43984857</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>CAV1</italic></td><td>caveolin 1 [Source:NCBI gene;Acc:445468]</td><td>ENSOARG00000001337</td><td>4</td><td>51786039</td><td>51820791</td><td>ENSBTAG00000017869</td><td>4</td><td>52173110</td><td>52208687</td></tr><tr><td>Cluster 3</td><td><italic>LDLRAD4</italic></td><td>low density lipoprotein receptor class A domain containing 4 [Source:HGNC Symbol;Acc:HGNC:1224]</td><td>ENSOARG00000002144</td><td>23</td><td>43646788</td><td>43801055</td><td>ENSBTAG00000009139</td><td>24</td><td>43861727</td><td>43919241</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>LRP11</italic></td><td>LDL receptor related protein 11 [Source:VGNC Symbol;Acc:VGNC:30988]</td><td>ENSOARG00000002898</td><td>8</td><td>73814860</td><td>73836141</td><td>ENSBTAG00000032007</td><td>9</td><td>88115145</td><td>88183314</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>CFI</italic></td><td>complement factor I [Source:NCBI gene;Acc:101119307]</td><td>ENSOARG00000005291</td><td>6</td><td>15708801</td><td>15753015</td><td>ENSBTAG00000034501</td><td>6</td><td>16765034</td><td>16815352</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>VLDLR</italic></td><td>very low density lipoprotein receptor [Source:HGNC Symbol;Acc:HGNC:12698]</td><td>ENSOARG00000013303</td><td>2</td><td>70468444</td><td>70486178</td><td>ENSBTAG00000018517</td><td>8</td><td>42109679</td><td>42141155</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Besides the gene name and description, the following information is provided: the identification of the gene retrieved from the Ensembl Genes 91 database, the ovine chromosome (OAR) on which the gene is located and the positions (in bp) of start and end of the gene within the chromosome. The same information is given for the orthologous cattle genes.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Correspondence with cattle trypanotolerance-related QTLs</title><p id="Par33">The relationship between the orthologous cattle genes listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and the cattle QTLs reported for trypanotolerance-related traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> are given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>. Only the cattle gene <italic>CAV1</italic>, assigned to Functional Cluster 2, intersected with a QTL (QTL ID no. 10515) reported on BTA4 for trypanosomes&#x02019; load.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">As expected<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, the population analyzed is poorly structured. This is true even if the Burkina-Sahel individuals are considered (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This situation is consistent with the more common West African livestock scenario in which no artificial selection programmes exist and long-distance livestock trading is intense.</p><p id="Par35">Although Sahelian and Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep show large morphological differences and are expected to have different ancestral origins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, the Burkina-Sahel sheep do not show a clear separation from the Djallonk&#x000e9; individuals (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). At the neutral loci level, it is assumed that genetic differentiation in West African livestock ruminant populations is basically due to geographic distance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Morphology, production goals or differences in origin do not result in high genetic differentiation. The poor genetic structuring identified may be due to different unobserved founder events underlying data as a consequence of a very traditional management system in which unplanned natural matings are the rule<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par36">In scenarios of poor differentiation amongst individuals, the use of EHH-based tests to identify genomic areas under selection is preferable to F<sub>ST</sub>-based methods which need at least two different populations in dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. We further tested this running the software BayeScan v. 2.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> on our Djallonk&#x000e9; genotypes. Only four SNPs (OAR1_22330907.1, OAR12_17378202.1, s56240.1 on OAR14 and OAR16_10423797.1) were identified as being under diversifying selection (positive &#x003b1; values). The inclusion of the Burkina-Sahel individuals in the analyses allowed to identify ten SNPs under diversifying selection (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). However, the set of SNPs listed above and their 75&#x02009;kb up- or down-stream regions did not overlap with the genomic regions surrounding the SNPs identified using EHH-based tests.</p><p id="Par37">The 207 selection sweep regions identified in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep spanned about 35 Mbp which is about 1.3% of the roughly 2.65 Gbp covered by SNPs typed. These figures are consistent with those reported in previous works using similar conservative criteria in the definition of selection signatures. The concordant genomic regions identified using two different EHH-based statistics on three different sheep breeds (Sunite, German Mutton and Dorper) typed with the same SNP Chip used here spanned chromosomal regions summing up from 1,049,753&#x02009;bp (Dorper) to 1,507,244&#x02009;bp (Sunite)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The analysis of the genomic profile, using three different methods (F<sub>ST</sub>, iSH and RsB), of three Brazilian sheep breeds gave only 5 (out of 246) coincident selection signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. When only two tests were considered the number of coincident selection signatures was 37<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="Sec15"><title>Biological importance of the functional clusters identified</title><p id="Par38">Gene-annotation enrichment analysis carried out allowed to identify various functional term clusters involved in signaling pathways associated directly or indirectly with environmental adaptation, such as control of metabolic stress, homeostasis, modulation of immune and inflammatory responses, cell proliferation and migration (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). The statistically significant Functional Clusters identified depicted particular genetic aspects of adaptation to harsh environments. Although some of the genes included in such Functional Clusters are involved in immune response (e.g. <italic>GC</italic> and <italic>CFI</italic> genes), they are mainly related to metabolic response to stress.</p><p id="Par39">Functional Cluster 1 included four genes (<italic>ALB</italic>, <italic>GC</italic>, <italic>AFP</italic> and <italic>AFM</italic>) belonging to the family of albumin genes. Because of their location at the same chromosome locus and in the same transcriptional orientation across species, they are proposed to originate from common predecessor and to be cooperatively regulated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Albumin (<italic>ALB</italic>) is involved on transport of metals, fatty acids, cholesterol, bile pigments, and drugs. It is a key element in the regulation of osmotic pressure and distribution of fluid between different compartments. In general, albumin represents the major and predominant antioxidant in plasma, a body compartment known to be exposed to continuous oxidative stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Variants of the albumin genes family, including the fetal counterpart of serum albumin (<italic>AFP</italic>) and afamin/alpha-albumin (<italic>AFM</italic>) genes, are associated with the development of the metabolic syndrome in adult humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. In turn, the <italic>GC</italic> gene is part of the complement system, a key component of innate immunity and susceptibility to diseases with a major role in tissue homeostasis, degeneration, and regeneration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The <italic>GC</italic> gene has major functions including the modulation of immune and inflammatory responses via regulation of chemotaxis and macrophage activation, transport by binding of fatty acids in collaboration with albumin and control of bone development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par40">Functional Cluster 2 included two genes (<italic>MC2R</italic> and <italic>MC5R</italic>) encoding proteins belonging to the G protein-coupled receptors family involved in the response to stress via binding plasma adrenocorticotropin hormone (ACTH). While the <italic>MC2R</italic> gene acts on adrenal steroidogenesis and regulation of the glucocorticoid axis, the <italic>MC5R</italic> gene regulates the function of sebaceous glands with effect on water repulsion and thermoregulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. In turn, the <italic>CIB1</italic> gene encodes a protein involved in cell proliferation, particularly proplatelets, therefore acting on thrombopoiesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, while the <italic>CAV1</italic> gene has a critical role in signal transduction and trafficking for its interplay with steroid receptors and is associated with the metabolic syndrome in humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par41">Genes assigned to Functional Cluster 3 have a major role on response to stress and immunity. The <italic>LDLRAD4</italic> gene encodes a protein involved in the regulation of the transforming growth factor- &#x000df; (TGF-&#x000df;) signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> which plays a pivotal role in cell differentiation, apoptosis, cell migration, production of matrix proteins, angiogenesis, and anti-proliferative responsiveness. The <italic>VLDLR</italic> gene is also involved in the regulation of cell proliferation and migration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Another low density lipoprotein receptor gene belonging to this Cluster (<italic>LPR11</italic>) is associated with chronic stress caused by food or water deprivation or elevated or cold temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Finally, the complement factor I (<italic>CFI</italic>) gene encodes a serine protease forming part of the complement system, which is involved in innate and adaptive immune responses for prevention and control of diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>General discussion on adaptation to West African environment</title><p id="Par42">The genomic regions harboring candidate genes of functional importance identified in the current study are, in general, different to those previously reported in the literature. This is not surprising in the case of works aiming at the characterization of the effect on the sheep genome of directional selection for dairy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> or meat traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. However, interestingly enough, it also occurred when reports aiming at the identification of genomic signals of adaptation to extreme environments were considered. It is worth pointing out that most studies in this field aimed at the identification of genomic areas related to adaptation to high altitude<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> or to high temperature in basically arid environments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. Such works involved several sheep populations bred in different geographical areas highly contrasting in environments, production systems and goals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. Therefore, the ability to identify selection signatures related to thermotolerance or hypoxia may be affected by the influence of others more likely linked to production or reproduction performance.</p><p id="Par43">The Djallonk&#x000e9; population analyzed here is a homogeneous population managed in a harsh, hot and humid environment subject to different disease challenges, namely trypanosomosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Although it is assumed that genes related to immune response and thermotolerance are basic for environmental adaptation, the lack of concordance between the genomic signals identified here and those previously reported would suggest that the genomic areas involved in resistance to hot climate stress may be different if they are identified in populations bred either in humid or arid areas. In this respect, the genomic areas conserved between sheep and goat indigenous to the hot arid environment of Egypt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> are completely different than those identified as functionally important in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep. In any case, it cannot be discarded that the history of the population is affecting results. The only coincidence between our study and others in the literature is a selection signature on OAR23 carrying out genes <italic>MC5R</italic> and <italic>MC2R</italic> in Ethiopian Menz and Red Maasai breeds (East African sheep)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. While the Ethiopian Menz is a fat-tailed coarse wooled sheep probably descending from very ancient importations from Arabia (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eth.dagris.info/node/2448">http://eth.dagris.info/node/2448</ext-link>), the Red Maasai is a hair sheep like Djallonk&#x000e9;, although medium to large body sized, with well known resistance to gastrointestinal parasites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par44">Trypanosome challenge has been hypothesized to be a major historical force influencing the formation of native West African domestic ruminant populations including Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. In consequence, we could expect that orthologous cattle chromosomal areas in which some QTLs for trypanotolerance related traits were previously identified<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> would coincide with the genomic areas harboring genes of functional importance for adaptation in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep. However, only one orthologous candidate gene located on BTA4 (<italic>CAV1</italic>) had a clear relationship with those QTLs.</p><p id="Par45">QTL information on cattle trypanotolerance was refined experimental herds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> and outbred populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Such analyses suggested that QTLs located on BTA2, BTA4 and BTA7 (with genes <italic>ARHGAP15</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>, <italic>TICAM1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>, <italic>CXCR4</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> and <italic>INHBA</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> being the stronger candidates to underlie these QTLs) could have a major role on cattle trypanotolerance response. Although recent analyses failed in identifying causal mutations on the cattle <italic>ARHGAP15, TICAM1, CXCR4</italic> and <italic>INHBA</italic> genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> the importance of BTA2, BTA4 and BTA7 for trypanotolerance cannot be neglected. The case of BTA4 would have been confirmed by the current analyses. Moreover, the sheep chromosomal areas orthologous to the QTLs reported on BTA4 (OAR4) might have been conserved between species to play a role for adaptation to the same harsh environment and trypanosome challenge.</p><p id="Par46">In summary, the genome of the Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep provided new insights on the genomic basis for adaptation. This sheep population is subject to the particularly harsh environment of the hot-humid, trypanosome challenged, West Africa. The genomic areas identified are associated with innate immunity and thermotolerance. Results further suggest that genes involved in the regulation of oxidative and metabolic stress can be target of research for the ascertainment of the genetic basis of adaptation. Moreover, our findings suggest that the functional importance of cattle BTA4 for trypanotolerant response might have been conserved between species. Furthermore, our findings highlight the importance of obtaining information from non-cosmopolite livestock populations managed in particularly harsh environments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="Par47">Blood and hair root samples used here were collected by veterinary practitioners with the permission and in presence of the owners. For this reason, permission from the Ethics Committee for Health Research in Burkina Faso (Joint Order 2004-147/MS/MESSE of May 11, 2004) was not required. In all instances, veterinarians followed standard procedures and relevant national guidelines to ensure appropriate animal care.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec18"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_59839_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Dataset 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-020-59839-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was partially supported by the grant MICIIN-FEDER AGL2016-77813-R. CompGen. LP-P is supported by grant SFRH/BPD/94518/2013.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>F.G. and I.A. conceived and planned the project; F.G., I.F. and L.P.-P. did the data analyses; F.G., I.A. and I.F. wrote the paper; A.T. undertook sampling and discussed and interpreted genetic data in light of breeding evidence; I.A., and N.M.-A. obtained samples and did laboratory work; L.P.-P. and N.M.-A. discussed and interpreted genetic data in light of the statistical evidence. All authors gave final approval for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The dataset used and analyzed during the current study is available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par48">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ianella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Caetano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection and evaluation of selection signatures in sheep</article-title><source>Pesq. Agropec. Bras.</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s0100-204x2018000500001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McRae</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemmell</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signatures of selection in sheep bred for resistance or susceptibility to gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title><source>BMC Genom.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>637</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez-Gil</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of selection mapping to identify genomic regions associated with dairy production in sheep</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e94623</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094623</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24788864?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24788864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manunza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population structure of eleven Spanish ovine breeds and detection of selective sweeps with BayeScan and hapFLK</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>27296</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep27296</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27272025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27272025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moioli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scat&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Steri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Catillo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signatures of selection identify loci associated with milk yield in sheep</article-title><source>BMC Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>76</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-14-76</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24004915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24004915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purfield</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>McParland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution of runs of homozygosity and selection signatures in six commercial meat sheep breeds</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0176780</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0176780</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28463982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28463982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide specific selection in three domestic sheep breeds</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0128688</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128688</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26083354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26083354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nejati-Javaremi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moradi-Shahrbabak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic scan of selective sweeps in thin and fat tail sheep breeds for identifying of candidate regions associated with fat deposition</article-title><source>BMC Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-13-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22364287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22364287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection signature analysis reveals genes associated with tail type in Chinese indigenous sheep</article-title><source>Anim. Genet.</source><year>2017</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/age.12477</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27807880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27807880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis reveals population structure and selection in Chinese indigenous sheep breeds</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1384-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25888314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis reveals signatures of selection for important traits in domestic sheep from different ecoregions</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>863</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3212-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27809776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouveia</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide search for signatures of selection in three major Brazilian locally adapted sheep breeds</article-title><source>Livest. Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2017.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fariello</surname><given-names>M-I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection signatures in worldwide sheep populations</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e103813</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25126940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25126940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>F-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adaptations to climate-mediated selective pressures in sheep</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3324</fpage><lpage>3343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu264</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25249477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25249477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mwacharo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic footprints of dryland stress adaptation in Egyptian fat-tail sheep and their divergence from East African and western Asia cohorts</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>17647</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-17775-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29247174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing of native sheep provides insights into rapid adaptations to extreme environments</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2576</fpage><lpage>2592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw129</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27401233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27401233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis reveals adaptation to high altitudes in Tibetan sheep</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>26770</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep26770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27230812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27230812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chessa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Revealing the history of sheep domestication using retrovirus integrations</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1170587</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19390051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gifford-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal Disease Challenges to the Emergence of Pastoralism in Sub-Saharan</article-title><source>Africa. Afr. Archaeol. Review</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006601020217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muigai</surname><given-names>AWT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanotte</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origin of African sheep: archaeological and genetic perspectives</article-title><source>Afr. Archaeol. Rev.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10437-013-9129-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multivariate characterization of morphological traits in Burkina Faso sheep</article-title><source>Small Rum. Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2008.09.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite analysis characterizes Burkina Faso as a genetic contact zone between Sahelian and Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep</article-title><source>Anim. Biotech.</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10495390902786926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geerts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Osaer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanotolerance in small ruminants of sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2008.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19200783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19200783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F-P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A genome scan of recent positive selection signatures in three sheep populations</article-title><source>J. Int. Agr.</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(15)61080-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fariello</surname><given-names>M-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Boitard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sancristobal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Servin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting signatures of selection through haplotype differentiation among hierarchically structured populations</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/Genetics.112.147231</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23307896?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23307896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabeti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detecting recent positive selection in the human genome from haplotype structure</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>419</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12397357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanotte</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping of quantitative trait loci controlling trypanotolerance in a cross of tolerant West African N&#x02019;Dama and susceptible East African Boran cattle</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>7443</fpage><lpage>7448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1232392100</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12805560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Usefulness of running animal models in absence of pedigrees: estimation of genetic parameters for gastrointestinal parasite resistance traits in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep of Burkina Faso</article-title><source>Small Rum. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2018.01.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ouadba, J. M. Development of national monograph on the biological diversity of Burkina Faso: Data gathering, ecological considerations (in French) pp 45 (Minist. Envir. et de l&#x02019;Eau, Ouagadougou, 1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic relationships of the Cuban hair sheep inferred from microsatellite polymorphism</article-title><source>Small Rum. Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2011.10.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resistance to gastrointestinal parasite infection in Djallonk&#x000e9; sheep</article-title><source>Animal</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1354</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731116002640</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28091356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28091356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PLINK: a toolset for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysis</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519795</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17701901?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr330</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3137218?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange.</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancements to the ADMIXTURE algorithm for individual ancestry estimation</article-title><source>BMC Bioinform.</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange.</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast model-based estimation of ancestry in unrelated individuals</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1655</fpage><lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.094052.109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19648217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voight</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudaravalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A map of recent positive selection in the human genome</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16494531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabeti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide detection and characterization of positive selection in human populations</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>449</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1124309</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17943131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrer-Admetlla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M. Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Korneliussen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On detecting incomplete soft or hard selective sweeps using haplotype structure</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>1291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu077</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24554778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24554778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the performance of selection scans to detect selective sweeps in domestic dogs</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.13485</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26589239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26589239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szpiech</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>selscan</italic>: an efficient multithreaded program to perform EHH based scans for positive selection</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2824</fpage><lpage>2827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25015648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25015648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide scan reveals population stratification and footprints of recent selection in Nelore cattle</article-title><source>Genet. Sel. Evol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12711-018-0381-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29720080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29720080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of pooled genome sequences from Djallonke and Sahelian sheep of Ghana reveals co-localisation of regions of reduced heterozygosity with candidate genes for disease resistance and adaptation to a tropical environment</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>816</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6198-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31699027?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31699027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamora</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spudich</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida-King</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staines</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derwent</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerhornou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flicek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ensembl BioMarts: a hub for data retrieval across taxonomic space</article-title><source>Database</source><year>2011</year><volume>2011</volume><issue>0</issue><fpage>bar030</fpage><lpage>bar030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/bar030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21785142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang da</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2008.211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19131956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>shinyCircos: an R/Shiny application for interactive creation of Circos plot</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx763</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29186362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20110278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ascertaining gene flow patterns in livestock populations of developing countries: a case study in Burkina Faso goat</article-title><source>BMC Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>35</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-13-35</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22564289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22564289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missohou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity and differentiation in nine West African local goat breeds assessed via microsatellite polymorphism</article-title><source>Small Rum. Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2011.04.005.</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaggiotti</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome scan method to identify selected loci appropriate for both dominant and codominant markers: A Bayesian perspective</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.108.092221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18780740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18780740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarevich</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of alpha-fetoprotein gene expression</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10702646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10702646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>P. Rondeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarnus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The antioxidant properties of serum albumin</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2008</year><volume>582</volume><fpage>1783</fpage><lpage>1787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2008.04.057</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18474236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18474236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between alpha-fetoprotein and metabolic syndrome in a Chinese asymptomatic population: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Lipids Health Dis.</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>85</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-016-0256-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27121855?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27121855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dieplinger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieplinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Afamin &#x02014; A pleiotropic glycoprotein involved in various disease states</article-title><source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source><year>2015</year><volume>446</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2015.04.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25892677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phieler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavakis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the complement system in metabolic organs and metabolic diseases</article-title><source>Semin. Immunol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smim.2013.04.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23684628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23684628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speeckaert</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Speeckaert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van Geel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Delanghe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D Binding Protein: a multifunctional protein of clinical importance</article-title><source>Adv. Clinic. Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-800094-6.00001-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramachandrappa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorrigan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The melanocortin receptors and their accessory proteins</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2013.00009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kostyak</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2012. Calcium- and integrin-binding protein 1 regulates megakaryocyte ploidy, adhesion, and migration</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2012</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2011-04-346098</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22128142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22128142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baudrand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prevalent caveolin-1 gene variant is associated with the metabolic syndrome in Caucasians and Hispanics</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><year>2015</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1674</fpage><lpage>1681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2015.09.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26475177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26475177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TMEPAI family: involvement in regulation of multiple signaling pathways</article-title><source>J. Biochem.</source><year>2018</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jb/mvy059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29945215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29945215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TFPI or uPA-PAI-1 complex affect cell function through expression variation of type II very low density lipoprotein receptor</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2010</year><volume>584</volume><fpage>3469</fpage><lpage>3473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2010.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20624392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic regulatory network analysis reveals that low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 11 is involved in stress responses in mice</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2014.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25262641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25262641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roversi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for complement factor I control and its disease-associated sequence polymorphisms</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>12839</fpage><lpage>12844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1102167108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21768352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E-SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple genomic signatures of selection in goats and sheep indigenous to a hot arid environment</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2016</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.2015.94</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26555032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26555032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel loci associated with gastrointestinal parasite resistance in a red Maasai x Dorper backcross population</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0122797</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122797</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25867089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25867089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic and expression analysis of cattle identifies candidate genes in pathways responding to <italic>Trypanosoma congolense</italic> infection</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>9304</fpage><lpage>9309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1013486108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21593421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayo</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of selection signatures within candidate regions underlying trypanotolerance in outbred cattle populations</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1801</fpage><lpage>1813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04141.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19302350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayo</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association studies in QTL regions linked to bovine trypanotolerance in a West African crossbred population</article-title><source>Anim. Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2011.02227.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22404348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Pardal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyache</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>African cattle do not carry unique mutations on the exon 9 of the ARHGAP15 gene</article-title><source>Anim. Biotech.</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10495398.2015.1053606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Pardal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyache</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of haplotype structuring for two candidate genes for trypanotolerance in cattle</article-title><source>J. Anim. Breed. Genet.</source><year>2016</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jbg.12181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26365013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26365013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Pardal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyache</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of specific alleles for the bovine Chemokine (C-X-C) receptor type 4 (CXCR4) gene in West African cattle questions its role as a candidate for trypanotolerance</article-title><source>Infec. Genet. Evol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2016.04.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27117936</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>