<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">IUCrJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">IUCrJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IUCrJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>IUCrJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-2525</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Union of Crystallography</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4547826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">yc5004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2052252515011665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="coden">IUCRAJ</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2052252515011665</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Crystal chemistry of layered structures formed by linear rigid silyl-capped molecules</article-title><alt-title>Chemistry of layered structures</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lumpi</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kautny</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000f6;ger</surname><given-names>Berthold</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="b">b</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;hlich</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><aff id="a"><label>a</label>Institute of Applied Synthetic Chemistry, Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, <country>Austria</country></aff><aff id="b"><label>b</label>Institute of Chemical Technologies and Analytics, Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, <country>Austria</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor">Correspondence e-mail: <email>bstoeger@mail.tuwien.ac.at</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>01</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>Pt 5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">m150500</issue-id><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Daniel Lumpi et al. 2015</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/uk/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits
unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original authors and source are cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665">A full version of this article is available from Crystallography Journals Online.</self-uri><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Silyl capped aryl <italic>bis</italic>-ene&#x02013;yne compounds and their derivatives possess a rich crystal chemistry: merotypism, polymorphism, polytypism, twinning and incommensurate modulation.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The crystallization behavior of methylthio- or methylsulfonyl-containing spacer extended <italic>Z</italic>,<italic>Z</italic>-<italic>bis</italic>-ene&#x02013;yne molecules capped with trimethylsilyl groups obtained by (tandem) thiophene ring fragmentation and of two non-spacer extended analogs were investigated. The rigid and linear molecules generally crystallized in layers whereby the flexibility of the layer interfaces formed by the silyl groups leads to a remarkably rich crystal chemistry. The molecules with benzene and thiophene spacers both crystallized with <italic>C</italic>2/<italic>c</italic> symmetry and can be considered as merotypes. Increasing the steric bulk of the core by introduction of ethylenedioxythiophene (EDOT) gave a structure incommensurately modulated in the [010] direction. Further increase of steric demand in the case of a dimethoxythiophene restored periodicity along [010] but resulted in a doubling of the <bold>c</bold> vector. Two different polytypes were observed, which feature geometrically different layer interfaces (non-OD, order&#x02013;disorder, polytypes), one with a high stacking fault probability. Oxidation of the methylthio groups of the benzene-based molecule to methylsulfonyl groups led to three polymorphs (two temperature-dependent), which were analyzed by Hirshfeld surface <italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub>/<italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub> fingerprint plots. The analogously oxidized EDOT-based molecule crystallized as systematic twins owing to its OD polytypism. Shortening of the backbone by removal of the aryl core resulted in an enantiomorphic structure and a further shortening by removal of a methylthio-ene fragment again in a systematically twinned OD polytype.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>arene spacers</kwd><kwd>incommensurately modulated structures</kwd><kwd>layer interfaces</kwd><kwd>order&#x02013;disorder polytypes</kwd><kwd>Hirshfeld surface fingerprint plots</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction &#x000a0; </title><p>The controlled formation of layers plays an important role in the design of materials. For example, hybrid organic&#x02013;inorganic layered perovskites (Mitzi, 2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb39"> &#x025b8;</xref>) are natural quantum well structures and can be tuned to specific electronic, magnetic and optical properties. The combination of layers with different properties enables the synthesis of multi-functional composites (Coronado <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb9"> &#x025b8;</xref>). In the field of organic electronics the formation of layers has been shown to be a viable strategy to improve conductivity (Anthony <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb5"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Efficient charge transport in organic materials is governed by nearest-neighbor electronic coupling. The intermolecular coupling is maximized when a face-to-face orientation of aromatic molecules is realized, as a consequence of enhanced interactions of the &#x003c0;-electron clouds of adjacent molecules (Mueller &#x00026; Bunz, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb40"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Anthony <italic>et al.</italic> (2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb5"> &#x025b8;</xref>) modified pentacene by connecting it at the central C atoms to triisopropylsilyl (TIPS) groups <italic>via</italic> rigid ethyne bridges. As opposed to plain pentacene, the resulting TIPS-pentacene molecules crystallized in layers (Fig.&#x000a0;1<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1"> &#x025b8;</xref>), whereby the pentacene cores are arranged in face-to-face orientation. As a result, a significantly lower resistivity perpendicular to the pentacene was reported (Anthony <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb5"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Hence, TIPS-pentacene yielded promising solution-processed OFET (organic field effect transistor) devices (Park <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb41"> &#x025b8;</xref>). In addition to the modified stacking arrangement the structures showed improved stability and solubility. On this basis a general molecular design for improved &#x003c0;-stacking was proposed by Anthony <italic>et al.</italic> (2002<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb6"> &#x025b8;</xref>), and intense research in the field of substituted acene derivatives arose from these findings and is of ongoing interest (Anthony, 1994<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb3"> &#x025b8;</xref>, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb4"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Besides technological importance, layered structures are interesting from a crystallographic point of view. Polymorphs (different crystal structures of the same composition) that crystallize in different arrangements of equivalent layers are called polytypes. Polytypes are ubiquitous in all classes of solid materials and are often the cause of crystallographically challenging problems, like twinning (the systematic association of equivalent macroscopic domains with different orientations; Hahn, 2006<italic>b</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb29"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and stacking disorder. In order&#x02013;disorder (OD) polytyes (Dornberger-Schiff &#x00026; Grell-Niemann, 1961<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb12"> &#x025b8;</xref>; Ferraris <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb17"> &#x025b8;</xref>) pairs of layers are equivalent and therefore all polytypes are locally equivalent. The symmetry of a polytype is described by groupoids, a generalization of the group concept (Fichtner, 1986<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb21"> &#x025b8;</xref>). For OD polytypes these groupoids are classified into OD groupoid families (Fichtner, 1977<italic>b</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb19"> &#x025b8;</xref>), in analogy to space group types. These were tabulated for the special case of OD structures composed of layers of one kind with identical lattices (Fichtner, 1977<italic>a</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb18"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Nevertheless, many issues remain unsolved. For example, OD structures composed of layers with different lattices have received only a little attention. Yet in some structures, like K<sub>2</sub>HAsO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;2.5H<sub>2</sub>O (St&#x000f6;ger, Weil &#x00026; Zobetz, 2012<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb53"> &#x025b8;</xref>), the different lattices of the layers are the decisive factor giving rise to OD polytypism. Moreover, we have discovered structures that follow the basic principle of OD theory, namely locally equivalent stacking possibilities, but do not follow the strict definition of OD theory (St&#x000f6;ger, Kautny <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb50"> &#x025b8;</xref>; St&#x000f6;ger &#x00026; Weil, 2013<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb52"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Also, as we will show in this work, polytypes that are not locally equivalent must not be overlooked. The symmetry groupoids of these kinds of polytypes are virtually unexplored. Thus, to shed new light on OD theory and related kinds of polytypism, we are in search of suitable model compounds. A fundamental advantage of organic over in&#x000ad;organic compounds is the ease of introduction of systematic geometric and electronic modifications.</p><p>An ideal basis for the crystal engineering of layered structures seemed to be spacer-extended ene&#x02013;yne molecules synthesized by tandem thiophene ring-fragmentation (TRF) reactions (Bobrovsky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb7"> &#x025b8;</xref>) owing to the generality and flexibility of the TRF protocol. The makeup of these mol&#x000ad;ecules resembles the TIPS-pentacene described above, though with smaller aromatic rings and a side chain extended by an ene fragment and a methylthio group (Fig. 2<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2"> &#x025b8;</xref>). An interesting aspect of these ene&#x02013;yne scaffolds is the possibility to selectively oxidize the methylthio group to modify electronic properties, but also introduce structure-directing hydrogen-bond acceptors.</p><p>The first reports on controlled TRF reactions go back to Gronowitz &#x00026; Torbj&#x000f6;rn (1970<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb27"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and Jakobsen (1970<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb31"> &#x025b8;</xref>). They were explored in detail by Gronowitz &#x00026; Frejd (1978<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb26"> &#x025b8;</xref>), Iddon (1983<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb30"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and Gilchrist (1987<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb23"> &#x025b8;</xref>). This approach enables the selective yield of <italic>Z</italic>-isomers of ene&#x02013;yne compounds as determined by the cyclic structure of thiophene. The exploration of tandem fragmentation reactions affording double-sided ring-opened (ene&#x02013;yne) products was first reported by Fuller <italic>et al.</italic> (1999<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb22"> &#x025b8;</xref>) on substituted thieno[3,2-<italic>b</italic>]thiophenes.</p><p>The first synthesized molecule of the class depicted in Fig. 2<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2"> &#x025b8;</xref> was BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) [<underline>b</underline>enzene <underline>s</underline>pacer-<underline>e</underline>xtended with <underline>m</underline>ethylthio group; spacer = benzene, Si<italic>R</italic>
<sub>3</sub> = trimethylsilyl (TMS)]. As expected, in analogy to TIPS-pentacene and related molecules (Anthony <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb5"> &#x025b8;</xref>, 2002<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb6"> &#x025b8;</xref>), BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) crystallizes in distinct molecular layers delimited by the bulky and flexible silyl groups. Therefore, this molecule was chosen as the starting point of the systematic crystallographic studies presented in this work.</p><p>It has to be noted that, in traditional crystal engineering, directed intermolecular interactions, notably <italic>via</italic> hydrogen bonding or, less commonly, halogen bonds, are used to induce controlled &#x02018;self-assembly&#x02019; of molecules (Aaker&#x000f6;y <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb1"> &#x025b8;</xref>). In the case at hand, no such bonding exists, since the layer-delimiting moieties are trialkylsilyl groups. Nevertheless, the special makeup of the molecules clearly induces crystallization as layered structures, and therefore variations of the spacer-extended ene&#x02013;yne compounds can be considered as a form of crystal engineering.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title>Results and discussion &#x000a0; </title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1.</label><title>Molecular modifications &#x000a0; </title><p>The scope of molecular modifications and expected impacts on the layer structures are schematized in Fig. 3<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3"> &#x025b8;</xref>. The main focus is modification of the spacer to control the intermolecular spacing and width of the layer backbone, with special attention paid to the effects on the layer interface. The latter is also determined by the nature of the silyl groups. Finally, the possibility of introducing potential structure-directing hydrogen-bond acceptors by oxidation of the methylthio groups is used to create new kinds of layer structures.</p><sec id="sec2.1.1"><label>2.1.1.</label><title>Spacer modifications &#x000a0; </title><p>The variations of the spacer unit are illustrated in Fig. 4<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4"> &#x025b8;</xref>. Firstly, the <italic>para</italic>-substituted benzene (<italic>mmm</italic>) spacer was replaced by the electron-rich 2,5-substituted thiophene (2<italic>mm</italic>) to TSEM (<bold>2</bold>). Thiophene is, from a technological point of view, an interesting core, since polythiophene has been successfully applied in the field of organic semiconductors.</p><p>To analyze the effects of a bulkier spacer extending into the layer plane, we enlarged the spacer to a 3,4-ethyl&#x000ad;ene&#x000ad;dioxythiophene (EDOT) bicycle, which is, like thiophene, commonly used in the field of organic semiconductors, to give ESEM (<bold>3</bold>). Surprisingly, the resulting crystal structure was incommensurately modulated. Such a structure can be described by a periodic basic structure and periodic modulation functions, but since the periodicities are incommensurate, the overall structure is only quasi-periodic (Janssen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb32"> &#x025b8;</xref>; van Smaalen, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb46"> &#x025b8;</xref>). A review of incommensurately modulated organic molecular structures was given by Sch&#x000f6;nleber (2011<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb45"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>To better understand the reasons for the modulation, we synthesized the ring-opened 3,4-dimethoxythiophene compound DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) featuring even more steric bulk. After numerous failed crystallization attempts, we were able to obtain two non-incommensurate polymorphs, which can be considered as polytypes, from the same crystallization dish and which will be designated as polytype I and II, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.1.2"><label>2.1.2.</label><title>Oxidation to sulfonyl compounds &#x000a0; </title><p>The electronic makeup of the molecules was modified by oxidation of the thioether functionality to the corresponding sulfonyl functions (Lumpi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb37"> &#x025b8;</xref>). We obtained crystals of the disulfonyl analog of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>): oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) and the fully oxidized trisulfonyl analog of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>): oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>).</p><p>For oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) we observed three polymorphs: polymorph I reversibly transforms into polymorph II upon cooling below <italic>ca</italic> 150&#x02005;K. Polymorph III is unrelated to the former two and features no phase transition from 100&#x02005;K up to the melting point. So far we were unable to determine the crystallization conditions needed to selectively obtain either polymorph.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.1.3"><label>2.1.3.</label><title>Backbone modifications &#x000a0; </title><p>An important argument of OD theory concerns the layer thickness: only for thick layers can interatomic interactions over a layer width be ignored. Thus, in a further modification we shortened the backbone (Fig. 5<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5"> &#x025b8;</xref>). At first the spacer was removed to NSEM (<underline>n</underline>on-<underline>s</underline>pacer-<underline>e</underline>xtended with <underline>m</underline>ethylthio group; Bobrovsky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb7"> &#x025b8;</xref>). We were unable to obtain single crystals suitable for structure determination of the TMS-containing molecule. Therefore, we synthesized and grew crystals of the corresponding <italic>tert</italic>-butyl-dimethylsilyl (TBDMS) compound NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>).</p><p>Finally, we shortened the backbone further by removing a &#x02014;CH=C(SMe)&#x02014; fragment to the single-sided ring-opened product ASYM (<bold>6</bold>). The name ASYM indicates a lack of symmetry in the direction of the main axis of the molecule. Despite the name, the molecule does not possess a stereogenic center and it can be considered as symmetric by reflection. Besides the short length, the compound seemed especially interesting in the light of OD theory, since the latter differentiates between polar and nonpolar layers. By growing crystals of a molecule that is polar with respect to the main axis, we were hoping to obtain polar layers, yet even ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) crystallized in nonpolar layers.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2.</label><title>Molecular structures &#x000a0; </title><p>The molecules presented in this work are essentially rigid, but possess three kinds of pivotal points, as depicted in Fig. 6<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6"> &#x025b8;</xref>. The main pivotal point is the connection of the side chains to the aromatic spacers (or the connection of the side chains in the case of non-spacer-extended molecules). Moreover, the methylthio (or methylsulfonyl) groups as well as the silyl groups can freely rotate. Nevertheless, the overall forms of the molecules feature little possibility for variation.</p><p>In Table 1<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1"> &#x025b8;</xref> the rotation angles about the freely rotatable bonds of the title compounds are compiled.</p><p>In general, the geometries of the molecules are similar. The most notable trend is that in molecules with a benzene spacer the C=C(&#x02014;spacer&#x02014;)C=C torsion angle is 180&#x000b0; (all mol&#x000ad;ecules are symmetric by inversion), <italic>i.e.</italic> the methylthio or methylsulfonyl groups are located at opposite sides of the molecules (Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic>). In molecules with a thiophene or a thiophene dioxide spacer, on the other hand, the torsion angle is small, <italic>i.e.</italic> the methylthio or methylsulfonyl groups face the same direction. Whereas in the methylthio/thiophene containing molecules [TSEM (<bold>2</bold>), ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>)] the S atoms of the methylthio groups are in close vicinity to the S atom of the thiophene ring (Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>), in the oxidized trisulfone compound oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) the methylsulfonyl groups are located at the opposite side of the aromatic ring owing to steric repulsion (Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>).</p><p>With the exception of the non-spacer-extended molecules [NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>), ASYM (<bold>6</bold>)], the methylthio and methylsulfonyl groups feature a distinct inclination to the plane of the ene fragment. In contrast, in NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) and ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) one methylthio unit is nearly perfectly aligned with the ene fragment. Whereas the CH<sub>3</sub> unit of the methylthio groups is generally turned towards the spacer (C=C&#x02014;S&#x02014;CH<sub>3</sub> torsion angle &#x0003e;&#x02005;90&#x000b0;), the methylsulfonyl groups face the side chain (C=C&#x02014;SO<sub>2</sub>&#x02014;CH<sub>3</sub> torsion angle &#x0003c;&#x02005;90&#x000b0;). An exception is polymorph II of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>), whereby the two unique molecules show the two behaviors, respectively.</p><p>The silyl group is in most cases in a <italic>gauche</italic> conformation to the side chain with inclination angles of &#x0223c;&#x02005;10&#x02013;30&#x000b0;. Only the TMS groups in one out of two molecules in polymorph II of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) and one out of two TMS groups in ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) are in a nearly perfect <italic>anti</italic> position (176.7 and 178.4&#x000b0;, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3.</label><title>Layer stacking &#x000a0; </title><p>With the exception of polymorph III of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>), all structures crystallize in distinct crystallochemical layers, whereby the silyl groups are located at the layer interfaces. In Table 2<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2"> &#x025b8;</xref> the symmetry of the layers and the operations relating adjacent layers are compiled. Here and in the following text, layer group types are designated with lower case Bravais symbols reflecting the two-dimensionality of the lattice (Kopsky &#x00026; Litvin, 2006<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb35"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and parentheses indicating the direction of missing translation symmetry as is customary in OD theory (Dornberger-Schiff &#x00026; Grell-Niemann, 1961<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb12"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>The main axis of the molecules is in general distinctly inclined with respect to the stacking direction and the molecules in adjacent layers are inclined in the same direction as schematized in Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>a</italic>). In oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>), on the other hand, the molecules feature only a little inclination, resulting in a layer stacking comparable to the scheme in Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>b</italic>). The layer stacking in polytype II of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) and in NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) are exceptions: The molecules in adjacent layers are inclined in opposite directions (Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>). Indeed, these two are the only structures presented in this work that lack inversion symmetry relating adjacent layers (Table 2<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4.</label><title>Structural relationships &#x000a0; </title><p>Before describing the individual crystal structures in detail (&#x000a7;2.5<xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2.5"/>), here an overview of the structural relationships of the crystals under investigation is given. The relationships and interesting crytallographical features are summarized in Fig. 9<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9"> &#x025b8;</xref>. The 11 structures can be partitioned into two families and three unrelated structures.</p><p>The first family is made up of the structures of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and of the analogs obtained by substitution of the aromatic spacer [TSEM (<bold>2</bold>), ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>)]. BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) are merotypes, <italic>i.e.</italic> belong to a family of structures that possess layers common to all members, but also layers found only in certain members (Makovicky, 1997<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb38"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Although the term originates from the crystallography of minerals, an interpretation of molecular organic structures in terms of merotypism has for example been given by our group (St&#x000f6;ger, Kautny <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb50"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Increase of the steric bulk of the thiophene spacer in TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) to EDOT in ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) leads to an incommensurately modulated structure with a basic structure isostructural (K&#x000e1;lm&#x000e1;n <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb34"> &#x025b8;</xref>) with TSEM (<bold>2</bold>). The modulation is a compromise between the need for additional space by the EDOT spacer and the retention of the structure of the interlayer contacts formed by the TMS groups.</p><p>On further increase of the steric bulk to dimethoxythiophene in DSEM (<bold>4</bold>), periodicity is restored. Although structurally related, the symmetries of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) are not related by a group/subgroup relationship. Crystals of two DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) polytypes were grown in which layers connect in geometrically different ways (non-OD polytypes). Owing to these alternative stacking possibilities, the second polymorph crystallizes as antiphase domains (domains related by translation symmetry; Wondratschek, 1976<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb56"> &#x025b8;</xref>), leading to weak diffraction intensities. Different possible kinds of connecting layers are also the likely reason for the non-OD twinning (the interface is geometrically different from the individuals) of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>).</p><p>Oxidation of the methylthio groups and removal of the spacer leads to unrelated structures. oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) exists as three polymorphs making up the second family. Two polymorphs (I and II) are structurally related. Whereas the arrangement of the molecules is retained, one out of two molecules inverts orientation. Thus, although the term is usually reserved for inorganic structures, both polymorphs can be considered isopointal (same space group and Wyckoff positions of molecules; de Faria <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb16"> &#x025b8;</xref>), but not isostructural. Polymorph III is structurally unrelated and the only analyzed structure that is not composed of layers.</p><p>Of the remaining three structures, oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) and ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) crystallize as OD twins, since their layers possess higher symmetry than adjacent layers. In these twins, the layer interface can be considered as a fragment of a different polytype that is locally equivalent to the twin individuals.</p><p>Finally, NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) is the only structure crystallizing in a Sohncke space group (the crystal is enantiomorphic).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5.</label><title>Crystal structure details &#x000a0; </title><sec id="sec2.5.1"><label>2.5.1.</label><title>BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>In the structures of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) the molecules are arranged in layers parallel to (100) with <italic>p</italic>(1)2/<italic>c</italic>1 symmetry (Figs. 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>). Yet, owing to the intrinsically different symmetries of the <italic>para</italic>-substituted benzene (<italic>mmm</italic>) and 2,5-substituted thiophene (<italic>mm</italic>2) rings, the molecules are located on different Wyckoff positions: Whereas the BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) molecules are symmetric by inversion, the TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) molecules are located on the twofold rotation axes. Adjacent BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) molecules are related by the mutual operation: twofold rotations for BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and inversions for TSEM (<bold>2</bold>).</p><p>Despite this difference, the outer parts of the layers are virtually identical in both structures. Moreover, adjacent layers connect in equivalent ways <italic>via</italic> 2<sub>1</sub> screws, <italic>n</italic> glides, inversions and the centering translations (Figs. 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>).</p><p>Thus, to relate their symmetry, the crystal structures of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>), are &#x02018;sliced&#x02019; into two kinds of layers, which do not correspond to layers in the chemical sense. The <italic>A</italic> layers [<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>], which are composed of the &#x02014;C&#x000a0;C&#x02014;TMS fragments of adjacent molecules, are equivalent in both structures. The <italic>B</italic> layers [<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>] containing the center unit (aromatic rings, ene fragment and methylthio groups) on the other hand are fundamentally different (Figs. 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>).</p><p>Since the <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> layers of both structures crystallize in the same layer group type, BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) possess the same space-group symmetry. Yet, in a comparable cell setting, the <italic>B</italic> layers are translated along <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi3.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> in TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) compared with BSEM (<bold>1</bold>), thus the former is described in the non-standard <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi4.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> setting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi5.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>The BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) molecule is slightly longer than the TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) molecule (Si&#x02013;Si distance of 16.36 <italic>versus</italic> 16.07&#x02005;&#x000c5;). However, since the inclination of the BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) molecules with respect to the layer plane is slightly more pronounced, the molecular layer width is smaller (<italic>a</italic>sin&#x003b2;/2 = 16.89 <italic>versus</italic> 17.10&#x02005;&#x000c5;) and the packing in the [001] direction less dense [<italic>c</italic> = 10.3442&#x02005;(18) <italic>versus</italic> 10.1978<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb1"> &#x025b8;</xref>(8)&#x02005;&#x000c5;]. The benzene rings require more space in the [010] direction compared with the thiophene rings, as observed by an increased lattice parameter <italic>b</italic> of 6.8690&#x02005;(12) <italic>versus</italic> 6.7415&#x02005;(4)&#x02005;&#x000c5;. These small structural modifications have nearly no impact on the layer interface (Figs. 11<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 11<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>).</p><p>The crystal of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) was twinned by reflection at (001). Often, OD theory is a convenient tool to understand twinning in layered structures (St&#x000f6;ger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb51"> &#x025b8;</xref>): the twin domain is interpreted as an alternative but locally equivalent stacking sequence. Application of OD theory to TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) did not lead to such a convincing interpretation, since no local pseudosymmetry is present. From a crystallochemical point of view, the only plausible twin interface is the boundary of the molecular layers. The molecule contact would then resemble more closely Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>c</italic>) than Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>a</italic>). Thus, the twin interface is geometrically different from the twin individuals. The possibility of such a twinning is demonstrated by the DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) polytypes (&#x000a7;2.5.3<xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2.5.3"/>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.2"><label>2.5.2.</label><title>ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>The basic structure of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) is isostructual with TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) (Fig. 10<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>). Compared with TSEM (<bold>2</bold>), the ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) molecules are more strongly inclined with respect to the layer plane, resulting in a larger monoclinic angle of &#x003b2; = 102.301&#x02005;(2)&#x000b0; <italic>versus</italic> &#x003b2; = 96.889&#x02005;(5)&#x000b0; and smaller layer widths (<italic>a</italic>sin&#x003b2; = 31.72 <italic>versus</italic> 34.19&#x02005;&#x000c5;). As expected, the lattice parameter <italic>b</italic> increases significantly from 6.7415&#x02005;(4) to 8.4003&#x02005;(5)&#x02005;&#x000c5; owing to the additional space needed by the ethyl&#x000ad;ene&#x000ad;di&#x000ad;oxy group.</p><p>The actual structure is incommensurately modulated with a modulation wavevector of <bold>q</bold> = &#x003c3;<sub>2</sub>
<bold>b</bold>* with &#x003c3;<sub>2</sub> = 0.6223&#x02005;(1) &#x02243; 5/8. Although incommensurately modulated structures are non-periodic, they can be conveniently described by embedding into 3+<italic>n</italic> superspace (Janssen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb32"> &#x025b8;</xref>; van Smaalen, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb46"> &#x025b8;</xref>). The superspace of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) has 3+1-dimensional superspace group symmetry (van Smaalen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb47"> &#x025b8;</xref>; Stokes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb54"> &#x025b8;</xref>) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi6.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, a non-standard setting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi7.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, No. 15.3 (Janssen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb33"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Since <bold>q</bold> is parallel to the layer planes, the layers are equivalent. Adjacent layers are related by a 2<sub>1</sub> screw with intrinsic translation along <bold>a</bold>
<sub>s2</sub>/2 + <bold>a</bold>
<sub>s4</sub>/2, corresponding to an increase of the internal coordinate <italic>t</italic> by (&#x003c3;<sub>2</sub> + 1)/2.</p><p>The twofold rotation of the molecules in the basic structure features an intrinsic translation along <bold>a</bold>
<sub>s4</sub>/2 in internal space. Thus, half of each molecule is completed by a second half located at <italic>t</italic> + 1/2. The individual molecules are therefore generally not symmetric by twofold rotation and the actual S1 atoms are not located on the twofold rotation axis.</p><p>In Figs. 12<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>b</italic>) and 12<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>c</italic>) the progression from the unmodulated chains of molecules along [010] in TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) to the modulated chains in ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) is depicted. On the one hand, the steric repulsion of the ethyl&#x000ad;ene&#x000ad;dioxy groups and the S atoms requires more space in the [010] direction, on the other hand the layer contacts <italic>via</italic> the TMS groups remain similar to those of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) (Figs. 11<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic> and 11<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>). To accommodate for both, the structure reacts by different rotations of adjacent molecules in an incommensurate way.</p><p>The distance of the equatorial H112 atoms of the ethyl&#x000ad;ene&#x000ad;dioxy group to the S atoms is plotted against the internal coordinate <italic>t</italic> in Fig. 13<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13"> &#x025b8;</xref>. Roughly two regions can be distinguished. For approximately half of the <italic>t</italic> values, marked by a gray backdrop in Fig. 13<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13"> &#x025b8;</xref>, an H112 atom is close to the thiophene S. Adjacent molecules are inclined to each other and the H112 atom protrudes into the cavity defined by the three S atoms. For the remaining <italic>t</italic> values, the molecules feature little inclination and the two H112 atoms connect only to the S atoms of the methylthio atom. In Fig. 12<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>b</italic>) H&#x02014;S distances up to an arbitrary value of 2.91&#x02005;&#x000c5; are indicated to highlight the two kinds of contacts.</p><p>Owing to the rigidity of the ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) molecules small rotations of the EDOT core translate into larger displacements of the TMS groups (Figs. 14<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 14<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>). Therefore, the connection of adjacent layers <italic>via</italic> the TMS groups features a wide variation of interatomic distances (Fig. 11<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11"> &#x025b8;</xref>). This surprising flexibility of the interlayer contacts enables incommensurate modulation.</p><p>The variation of the geometry of the ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) molecules is pictured in Figs. 14<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>c</italic>) and 14<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14"> &#x025b8;</xref>(<italic>d</italic>). The interatomic distances are close to constant (Fig. 15<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and in good agreement with the expected values (Allen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb2"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Whereas the core of the molecule is virtually identical in all molecules, the side arms (yne fragment, TMS group) feature significant bending (Fig. 14<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>), needed to contact adjacent layers.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.3"><label>2.5.3.</label><title>DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>Like in TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) and ESEM (<bold>3</bold>), the DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) molecules in both polytypes are arranged in rods running along the [010] direction (Fig. 12<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>). In contrast to ESEM (<bold>3</bold>), periodicity in the [010] direction is restored by rotating all molecules in a rod in the same direction (Fig. 12<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>). The symmetry of the rods is thus reduced from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi8.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi9.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>. The rods form pairs which are related by inversion and adjacent pairs are related by 2<sub>1</sub> screws. As a consequence the <bold>c</bold> lattice vector is doubled compared with TSEM (<bold>2</bold>). Owing to the different arrangements of the rods the DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) layers cannot be considered as superstructures of the TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) layers and indeed, their symmetry groups (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> with doubled <bold>c</bold> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi11.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>) are not related by a group/subgroup relationship.</p><p>Although the DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) polytypes are non-OD polytypes, in the following discussion the naming conventions of OD theory will be used (Ferraris <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb17"> &#x025b8;</xref>): the layers are designated as <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic>, whereby the <italic>n</italic> is a serial index. <bold>a</bold>
<sub>0</sub> is the vector normal to the layer planes with the length of one layer thickness.</p><p>Given an <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> layer, the adjacent <italic>A</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic>+1</sub> layer can appear in two different orientations. <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> and <italic>A</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic>+1</sub> are either related by the operations listed in Table 2<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2"> &#x025b8;</xref>, line 4, or those in line 5. The symmetry elements are indicated in Fig. 16<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p><p>Thus, the layers can be connected to an infinity of polytypes, which are not OD polytypes because (<italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic>, <italic>A</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic>+1</sub>) layer pairs are not necessarily equivalent [<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi11.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi13.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry, respectively]. The polytypes differ from other non-OD polytypes we discussed before (St&#x000f6;ger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012<italic>a</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb50"> &#x025b8;</xref>; St&#x000f6;ger &#x00026; Weil, 2013<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb52"> &#x025b8;</xref>). In the latter, which we designated as &#x02018;non-classic OD&#x02019; polytypes, every polytype is at every point locally equivalent to all other polytypes, <italic>i.e.</italic> every point belongs to at least two equivalence regions (Grell, 1984<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb24"> &#x025b8;</xref>). In DSEM (<bold>4</bold>), on the other hand, the contact plane of the layers differs geometrically among polytypes as depicted in Fig. 17<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17"> &#x025b8;</xref>. As in the case of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) this demonstrates a remarkable flexibility of the layer contacts and confirms the assumption that the twinning of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) is likewise caused by non-equivalent layer contacts.</p><p>Although the symmetry groupoids of these kind of non-OD polytypes were not elaborated up to now, the OD concept of polytypes with a <italic>maximum degree of order</italic> (MDO) (Dornberger-Schiff, 1982<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb11"> &#x025b8;</xref>) can nevertheless be applied. There are two polytypes that cannot be decomposed into simpler polytypes. They are generated by continuous application of either set of operations relating the adjacent layers. The MDO<sub>1</sub> polytype has <italic>C</italic>2/<italic>c</italic> symmetry and lattice vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi14.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>; MDO<sub>2</sub>
<italic>Pccn</italic> symmetry and lattice vector 2<bold>a</bold>
<sub>0</sub>.</p><p>The observed polytypes I and II are MDO<sub>1</sub> and MDO<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Indeed, it is well documented for OD structures that ordered polytypes are in the vast majority of cases MDO. Fragments of the MDO<sub>2</sub> polytype in MDO<sub>1</sub> result in twinning by reflection at a plane normal to [001]. No such twinning was observed in the investigated crystal. Stacking faults in MDO<sub>2</sub>, on the other hand, results in antiphase domains (Wondratschek, 1976<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb56"> &#x025b8;</xref>), since the MDO<sub>2</sub> domains are related by translation. Although in principle not directly observable in diffraction patterns, we suspect that such stacking faults exist and cause the systematic low scattering power of the polytype II crystals.</p><p>As opposed to OD structures, where ordered polytypes usually feature desymmetrization of the layers compared to the idealized description (&#x0010e;urovi&#x0010d;, 1979<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb14"> &#x025b8;</xref>), the <italic>A</italic> layers in both MDO polytypes of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) possess the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi15.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry of the idealized description. A deviation from the idealized model is nevertheless observed by a slight variation of the lattice parameters and layer widths across structures [<italic>a</italic>sin&#x003b2; = 33.765 <italic>versus</italic> 33.630&#x02005;(10)&#x02005;&#x000c5;, <italic>b</italic> = 8.1665&#x02005;(5) <italic>versus</italic> 8.271&#x02005;(2)&#x02005;&#x000c5; and <italic>c</italic> = 20.0791&#x02005;(12) <italic>versus</italic> 19.717&#x02005;(6)&#x02005;&#x000c5;] and a small deviation of the molecular conformations (Fig. 18<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18"> &#x025b8;</xref>). As expected, the largest deviation is observed for the TMS groups, which are located in geometrically different environments in both polytypes.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.4"><label>2.5.4.</label><title>oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>), polymorphs I and II &#x000a0; </title><p>Both polymorphs consist of two crystallographically different oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecules (Fig. 19<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19"> &#x025b8;</xref>), called <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, both located on centers of inversion (<italic>Z</italic>&#x02032; = 2/2). In both polymorphs, the crystallographically independent molecules feature different conformations: The molecules in polymorph I differ by the conformation of the TMS groups with respect to the remaining molecule, whereas in polymorph II the major difference pertains to the orientation of the methylsulfonyl groups (Fig. 19<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Nevertheless, the torsion angle differences between all four conformations (Table 1<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1"> &#x025b8;</xref>) are too small for the molecules to be considered as conformers according to the criteria of Cruz-Cabeza &#x00026; Bernstein (2014<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb10"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Thus, the changes in these polymorphs are only conformational adjustments, though to a rather large degree in the molecule of polymorph II that has a different orientation of the methylsulfonyl groups.</p><p>The molecules are arranged in layers parallel to (001) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi16.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry, whereby the <italic>B</italic> molecules form rods along [100], connected by the <italic>A</italic> molecules (Fig. 20<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>The most striking difference between the two polymorphs is the orientation of the <italic>A</italic> molecules, which are rotated by nearly 180&#x000b0;. In projection along [100], the S atoms of the methylsulfonyl groups are nearly superimposed in polymorph II, while in polymorph I the methylsulfonyl groups of subsequent molecules point in opposite directions (Fig. 21<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig21"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Thus, the I <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi17.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> II phase transition has to be considered reconstructive, which is consistent with the destruction of large single crystals on cooling. The transformation is accompanied by an inclination of the molecules with respect to the stacking direction (Figs. 21<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig21"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic> and 21<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig21"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>d</italic>). In consequence, the layer interfaces are fundamentally different in the two polytypes (Fig. 22<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig22"> &#x025b8;</xref>), demonstrating again the flexibility in layer arrangements allowed by the TMS groups.</p><p>Although methylsulfonyl groups are potential hydrogen bond acceptors, the oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecules do not possess classical hydrogen-bond donors. Indeed, attempts to analyze the phase transition by listing the weak hydrogen bonds of the two polymorphs were inconclusive, since these lists depend on rather arbitrary distance and angle limits. A more holistic and unbiased approach for the description of molecular inter&#x000ad;actions in polymorphs, which was established in the last decade, is the analysis of molecular Hirshfeld surfaces (Spackman &#x00026; Jayatilaka, 2009<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb48"> &#x025b8;</xref>). The <italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub>/<italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub> fingerprint plots (Spackman &#x00026; McKinnon, 2002<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb49"> &#x025b8;</xref>) of the two molecules in both polymorphs are depicted in Fig. 23<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig23"> &#x025b8;</xref>. As expected, contacts not involving H atoms, as well as those involving S and Si atoms, are negligible. First conclusions can be drawn from the shape of the plots: In both polymorphs, the individual plots are not symmetric by reflection at the <italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub> = <italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub> line, but the plots of the crystallographically independent molecules are approximately related by such an operation. Thus, the closest contacts are mostly between non-equivalent molecules along the [010] direction. An exception are the regions 1 and 2 in Fig. 23<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig23"> &#x025b8;</xref>, which correspond to C=C&#x02014;H&#x022ef;O and SC&#x02014;H&#x022ef;C&#x000a0;C contacts of equivalent molecules along [100] (Fig. 20<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Surprisingly, the fingerprint plot of the <italic>A</italic> molecule of polymorph I resembles the plot of the <italic>B</italic> molecule of polymorph II and <italic>vice versa</italic>. Thus, one could say that the roles of the donor and acceptor are reversed on phase transition, although overall the type of interatomic interaction remains similar. The most prominent interactions are indicated in Fig. 23<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig23"> &#x025b8;</xref> and correlated to the actual atoms in Fig. 20<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20"> &#x025b8;</xref> and Table 3<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3"> &#x025b8;</xref>. A striking feature that is only observed in polymorph I is region 6, a very short C&#x02014;H&#x022ef;H&#x02014;C contact (2.30&#x02005;&#x000c5;) between two aromatic protons. Thus, although there is no definite proof, one might speculate that, on cooling, the structure contracts until these H atoms are too close and the structure becomes unstable. This conjecture would not have been insinuated without the analysis of fingerprint plots.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.5"><label>2.5.5.</label><title>oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>), polymorph III &#x000a0; </title><p>The molecules in polymorph III of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) are not arranged in distinct silyl-group delimited layers (Fig. 24<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig24"> &#x025b8;</xref>). One crystallographically unique oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecule is located on a center of inversion. It can again not be considered a different conformer. As expected, the Hirshfeld fingerprint plot (Fig. 21<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig23"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>e</italic>) is nearly symmetric by reflection at <italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub> = <italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub>. It most closely resembles the plot of the <italic>A</italic> molecule in polymorph II, but the H&#x022ef;C contacts are distinctly less prominent, indicating an energetically more favorable packing. Indeed, polymorph III has higher symmetry (same space group type, but <italic>Z</italic>&#x02032; = 1/2 <italic>versus</italic> 2/2) and distinctly higher density (1.267 <italic>versus</italic> 1.229&#x02005;g&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> at 100&#x02005;K). Thus, the I <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi17.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> II transition is an example of Ostwald&#x02019;s rule stating that a system does not change into the thermodynamically stable, but the nearest metastable state.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.6"><label>2.5.6.</label><title>oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>The oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecules are arranged in layers parallel to (001) with (idealized) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi19.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry (Fig. 25<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig25"> &#x025b8;</xref>), which are, despite possessing the same layer group type, structurally unrelated to the layers in BSEM (<bold>1</bold>), TSEM (<bold>2</bold>), the basic structure of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>).</p><p>One crystallographically unique molecule is located on a general position. The layers are stacked in such a way that the <italic>b</italic>-glide planes do not overlap. In consequence oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) belongs to a category I OD family composed of layers of one kind. The OD groupoid family symbol reads according to the notation introduced by Dornberger-Schiff &#x00026; Grell-Niemann (1961<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb12"> &#x025b8;</xref>) as<disp-formula id="fdu1"><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efd1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" position="float"/></disp-formula>It has to be noted that in this case <bold>c</bold>
<sub>0</sub> is conveniently chosen not normal to the layer planes, to reflect the monoclinic point group 2/<italic>m</italic>11 of the OD family (Fichtner, 1979<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb20"> &#x025b8;</xref>), whereby a second metric parameter describing the relative layer positions vanishes. In one possible arrangement of the (<italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic>, <italic>A</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic>+1</sub>) layer pair, <italic>A</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic>+1</sub> is related to <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> by a 2<sub><italic>r</italic></sub> screw with intrinsic translation along <italic>r</italic>
<bold>a</bold>/2 or equivalently by an <italic>n</italic>
<sub>1,2</sub> glide with intrinsic translation along (<bold>b</bold>/2) + <bold>c</bold>
<sub>0</sub>. The other geometrically equivalent arrangements are derived using the <italic>NFZ</italic> relationship (&#x0010e;urovi&#x0010d;, 1997<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb15"> &#x025b8;</xref>): Given an <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> layer, an adjacent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi20.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layer can appear in <italic>Z</italic> = <italic>N</italic>/<italic>F</italic> = [<italic>p</italic>11(1):<italic>pb</italic>1(1)] = 2 orientations, related by the <italic>b</italic> glides of <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic>. <italic>p</italic>11(1) and <italic>pb</italic>1(1) are the groups of those layer operations that do not invert the orientation of the layers with respect to the stacking direction [called &#x003bb;-&#x003c4; partial operations (POs) in the OD literature].</p><p>These stacking possibilities give rise to two MDO polytypes: MDO<sub>1</sub> {<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <bold>c</bold> = <bold>c</bold>
<sub>0</sub> + [(<italic>r</italic> &#x02212; 1)/2]<bold>a</bold>} and MDO<sub>2</sub> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi22.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <bold>c</bold> = 2<bold>c</bold>
<sub>0</sub>), obtained by continuous application of the 2<sub><italic>r</italic></sub> screws and <italic>n</italic>
<sub>1,2</sub> glides, respectively. The symmetry of the two polytypes is schematized in Fig. 26<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig26"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p><p>The major polytype of the crystals under investigation is the MDO<sub>1</sub> polytype. Fragments of the MDO<sub>2</sub> polytype were observed indirectly by systematic twinning. The twin element corresponds to the plane of the <italic>b</italic> glides of the <italic>A</italic> layers. This kind of twinning is fundamentally different from that in TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) or the polytypism of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>). The latter is only possible owing to the flexibility of the layer contacts, whereas in oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) the layer contacts are equivalent in all polytypes.</p><p>In the major MDO<sub>1</sub> polytype, the symmetry of the <italic>A</italic> layers is reduced by an index of 2 from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi19.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi24.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>. This translates to a small deviation of &#x003b3; = 89.771&#x02005;(2)&#x000b0; from the ideal value of 90&#x000b0; imposed by the rectangular layer lattice and a small deviation of the atoms from the positions compared with the idealized <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi19.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layers. Significant deviations from ideal symmetry are limited to the TMS groups, which are located at the layer interfaces [deviations of 0.272&#x02005;&#x000c5; (Si2) up to 0.508&#x02005;&#x000c5; (C10)]. This is expected, since the layer interfaces are located in an environment which deviates from the ideal layer symmetry. The closer the atoms are located to the center of the layers, the smaller the deviation. The C atoms of the yne fragment connecting to the TMS group deviate by 0.130&#x02005;&#x000c5; (C8) and 0.138&#x02005;&#x000c5; (C16), all other atoms by less than 0.100&#x02005;&#x000c5;.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.7"><label>2.5.7.</label><title>NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>Although achiral, the NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) mol&#x000ad;ecules crystallize in the Sohncke group <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi26.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>. The crystal under investigation was enantiomerically pure [Flack parameter 0.03&#x02005;(3)]. An estimation of the number of achiral molecules crystallizing in Sohncke groups was given by Pidcock (2005<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb42"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>Whereas the central part of the molecule is nearly symmetric by twofold rotation, the TBDMS groups feature a distinctly different orientation with respect to the methylthio groups, resulting in molecules with 1 symmetry (Figs. 27<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig27"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>a</italic> and 27<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig27"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>). The molecules are arranged in layers parallel to (001) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi27.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry. The layers in turn are connected by 2<sub>1</sub> screws with axes parallel to [100] and [010] (Fig. 27<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig27"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>c</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.8"><label>2.5.8.</label><title>ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) &#x000a0; </title><p>The ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) molecules are located on general positions. Despite being polar with respect to the main direction, they are arranged in nonpolar layers parallel to (010) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi28.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry (Fig. 28<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig28"> &#x025b8;</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to the other layered structures, the TMS groups are not as clearly located at the layer interface: every second group is moved away from the surface into the layers. This can be attributed to ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) being the shortest of the molecules under investigation.</p><p>The systematic twinning of ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) can be explained by local pseudosymmetry: With the exception of one TMS group, the molecules are practically symmetric by reflection at (100) (Fig. 28<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig28"> &#x025b8;</xref>
<italic>b</italic>). Thus the structure can be &#x02018;sliced&#x02019; into OD layers (Grell, 1984<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb24"> &#x025b8;</xref>) of two kinds, which do not correspond to layers in the crystallochemical sense (Fig. 28<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig28"> &#x025b8;</xref>). The <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers contain the parts of the molecule that possess mirror symmetry, whereas the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> layers are made up of the remaining TMS groups.</p><p>As a consequence, the structure belongs to a category IV OD family composed of nonpolar layers of two kinds. The corresponding OD groupoid family symbol reads according to the notation introduced by Grell &#x00026; Dornberger-Schiff (1982<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb25"> &#x025b8;</xref>) as<disp-formula id="fdu2"><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efd2.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" position="float"/></disp-formula>Accordingly, the structure is made up of an alternating stacking of <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> and <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> layers, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi29.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi30.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> symmetry, respectively. <bold>b</bold>
<sub>0</sub> is chosen not normal to the layer planes so that one metric parameter vanishes. In one possible arrangement of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi31.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layer pair, the origin of <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> is reached from the origin of <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> by translation along (<bold>b</bold>
<sub>0</sub>/2) + <italic>s</italic>
<bold>a</bold>.</p><p>According to the <italic>NFZ</italic> relationship, given an <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi32.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layer, the adjacent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi33.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layers can appear in <italic>Z</italic> = <italic>N</italic>/<italic>F</italic> = [<italic>pm</italic>(1)1:<italic>p</italic>1(1)1] = 2 orientations, related by the <italic>m</italic> operation of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi32.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> layer. For the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> layers on the other hand, there is only one way to connect to the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers, since all &#x003bb;-&#x003c4; POs of <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi35.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>) apply likewise to <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup>.</p><p>These stacking possibilities give rise to two MDO polytypes: MDO<sub>1</sub> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <bold>b</bold> = <bold>b</bold>
<sub>0</sub> + 2<italic>s</italic>
<bold>a</bold>) is obtained by continuous application of the inversion operations of the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers; MDO<sub>2</sub> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi37.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <bold>b</bold> = 2<bold>b</bold>
<sub>0</sub>) by application of the 2<sub>1</sub> screws. The symmetry of the two polytypes is schematized in Fig. 29<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig29"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p><p>The bulk of the ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) crystals under investigation are made up of the MDO<sub>1</sub> polytype, whereas fragments of the MDO<sub>2</sub> polytype are located at the twin interface. A twin element corresponds to the mirror plane of the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers. Again, all polytypes are locally equivalent and no flexibility of the layer contact is needed for twinning.</p><p>In MDO<sub>1</sub>, the symmetry of the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers is reduced by an index of 2 from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi29.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi39.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>. This is reflected by a deviation of &#x003b2; = 92.510&#x02005;(2)&#x000b0; from the ideal value of 90&#x000b0; according to the rectangular layer lattice, and by a slight deviation of the molecules from their idealized positions. Under the assumption of &#x003b2; = 90&#x000b0;, the only non-negligible deviations (&#x0003e;&#x02005;0.1&#x02005;&#x000c5;) of non-H atoms from the idealized positions of the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> layers are observed for the atoms of the TMS group that are not located on the mirror plane (C10, C11, deviation of 0.11&#x02005;&#x000c5;) and for the C3 atom, which connects to the TMS group in the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> layer (deviation of 0.12&#x02005;&#x000c5;).</p><p>The deviation of &#x003b2; from the ideal value of 90&#x000b0; by 2.51&#x000b0; is remarkably large and distinctly larger than in the case of oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>). As a consequence, the lattices of the twin domains do not match (deviation of 5&#x000b0;) and the crystals are distinctly distorted at the twin interface. The orthorhombic MDO<sub>2</sub> fragment at the twin interface possesses an ideal angle of 90&#x000b0; and it therefore enables the passage of the two extremes of the MDO<sub>1</sub> domains.</p><p>In contrast to oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>), the desymmetrization does not result in two crystallographically unique molecules, but rather in a desymmetrization of the <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> parts of the molecule from <italic>m</italic> to 1 symmetry.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3.</label><title>Experimental &#x000a0; </title><p>Detailed syntheses and spectroscopic characterizations of all compounds are given by Lumpi (2013<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb36"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Single crystals of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) (<italic>i</italic>-PrOH, EtOH), oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) (EtOH), ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) (EtOH, in a glove-box with N<sub>2</sub> atmosphere), oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) (MeOH) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) (EtOH) were obtained by slow evaporation at room temperature. Crystallization of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) from solvents failed to give single crystals suitable for single-crystal diffraction. Tiny single crystals were instead afforded by crystallization of the oily sample at &#x0223c;293&#x02005;K over a time period of several months.</p><p>Single-crystal data were collected and processed on a Bruker Kappa APEXII diffractometer system (Bruker, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb8"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Data were reduced using the <italic>SAINT-Plus</italic> (Bruker, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb8"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and <italic>EVAL</italic> (Duisenberg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb13"> &#x025b8;</xref>) suites and corrected for absorption effects with <italic>SADABS</italic> or <italic>TWINABS</italic> (Bruker, 2008<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb8"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Structures were solved with <italic>SUPERFLIP</italic> (Palatinus &#x00026; Chapuis, 2007<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb43"> &#x025b8;</xref>) and refined with <italic>JANA</italic>2006<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb1"> &#x025b8;</xref> (Pet&#x00159;&#x000ed;&#x0010d;ek <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb44"> &#x025b8;</xref>). More details on single-crystal diffraction and structure refinement are available as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#suppinfoanchor">supplementary materials</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4.</label><title>Conclusion and outlook &#x000a0; </title><p>We set out to create layered structures, expecting to obtain OD polytypes due to different local layer symmetry. We were indeed successful with the systematic twins oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>a</italic></bold>) and ASYM (<bold>6</bold>). Surprisingly though, we observed numerous other crystallographic phenomena, which are not caused by local layer symmetry but by the remarkable flexibility of the layer contacts. On the one hand, a given layer contact can accommodate significant distortion leading to the incommensurate modulation of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>). On the other hand, identical layers can connect in fundamentally different ways as observed in the non-OD polytypism of TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) and DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) and the layer contacts can accomodate the different molecular arrangements observed in the temperature-dependent polymorphism of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>).</p><p>These phenomena demonstrate the necessity of a generalization of space-group symmetry to local symmetry. These so-far unexplored groupoids are necessary not only for the description of polytypism, but also of structural relationships like the merotypism of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>).</p><p>Future synthetic work will focus on the core of the layers (alterations of the aromatic spacer and an elongation of the methylthio groups), as well as the application of other silyl groups like TBDMS or TIPS to induce different layer contacts as in NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>). Besides studying crystallographic phenomena, the application of acene or polythiophene derivatives may also enable the application of the layer motifs in the field of functional organic materials. To achieve this goal an adjustment of the steric bulk of the cores and the size of the silyl groups will be needed to obtain an optimum face-to-face stacking of the extended aromatic cores. Moreover, the merotypism of BSEM (<bold>1</bold>) and TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) presents an opportunity for the controlled epitaxial growth of different kinds of molecules, a crucial point in the design of devices.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Crystal structure: contains datablock(s) ASYM, BSEM, BSEMOX1, BSEMOX2, BSEMOX3, DSEM1, DSEM2, ESEM, ESEMOX, NSEM, TSEM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004sup1.cif">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004sup1.cif</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="chemical" mime-subtype="x-cif" xlink:href="m-02-00584-sup1.cif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e119" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) ASYM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ASYMsup2.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ASYMsup2.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-ASYMsup2.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e126" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) BSEM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMsup3.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMsup3.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-BSEMsup3.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e133" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) BSEMOX1. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX1sup4.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX1sup4.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-BSEMOX1sup4.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e140" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) BSEMOX2. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX2sup5.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX2sup5.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-BSEMOX2sup5.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e147" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) BSEMOX3. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX3sup6.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004BSEMOX3sup6.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-BSEMOX3sup6.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e154" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) DSEM1. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004DSEM1sup7.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004DSEM1sup7.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-DSEM1sup7.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e161" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) DSEM2. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004DSEM2sup8.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004DSEM2sup8.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-DSEM2sup8.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e169" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) ESEMOX. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ESEMOXsup9.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ESEMOXsup9.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-ESEMOXsup9.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e176" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) NSEM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004NSEMsup10.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004NSEMsup10.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-NSEMsup10.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e183" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) TSEM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004TSEMsup11.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004TSEMsup11.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-TSEMsup11.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e190" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Supporting information file. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004sup12.pdf">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004sup12.pdf</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="m-02-00584-sup12.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e197" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Structure factors: contains datablock(s) ESEM. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ESEMsup13.hkl">10.1107/S2052252515011665/yc5004ESEMsup13.hkl</ext-link>
</p><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="m-02-00584-ESEMsup13.hkl" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e204" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>CCDC references: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=927469">927469</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=927470">927470</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=927472">927472</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=927473">927473</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=928106">928106</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=928107">928107</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=928108">928108</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=928110">928110</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=1407074">1407074</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=1407075">1407075</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=csd&#x00026;csdid=1407076">1407076</ext-link>
</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are indebted to V. Carl, D. Koch, J. Steindl and D. Wurm for supporting the synthetic experiments. The authors also thank W. Skranc for preliminary work on the discussed topic. The help of Martin Lutz with the use of the <italic>EVAL</italic> software package is highly appreciated. The X-ray centre of the Vienna University of Technology is acknowledged for providing access to the single-crystal diffractometer. This publication was supported by TU Vienna research funds.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bb1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aaker&#x000f6;y, C. B., Champness, N. R. &#x00026; Janial, C. (2010). <italic>Cryst. Eng. Commun.</italic>
<bold>12</bold>, 22&#x02013;43.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allen, F. H., Watson, D. G., Brammer, L., Orpen, A. G. &#x00026; Taylor, R. (2006). <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic>, Vol. C, ch. 9.5, pp. 790&#x02013;881. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anthony, J. E. (1994). <italic>Induced &#x003c0;-Stacking in Acenes</italic>, Vol. 1, <italic>Functional Organic Materials &#x02013; Syntheses, Strategies and Applications</italic>, ch. 14. Weinheim: Wiley-VCH Verlag.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anthony, J. E. (2008). <italic>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</italic>
<bold>47</bold>, 452&#x02013;483.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anthony, J. E., Brooks, J. S., Eaton, D. L. &#x00026; Parkin, S. R. (2001). <italic>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</italic>
<bold>123</bold>, 9482&#x02013;9483.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anthony, J. E., Eaton, D. L. &#x00026; Parkin, S. R. (2002). <italic>Organic Lett.</italic>
<bold>4</bold>, 15&#x02013;18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bobrovsky, R., Hametner, C., Kalt, W. &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;hlich, J. (2008). <italic>Heterocycles</italic>, <bold>76</bold>, 1249&#x02013;1259.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bruker (2008). <italic>APEX2</italic>, <italic>RLATT</italic>, <italic>SAINT</italic>, <italic>SADABS</italic> and <italic>TWINABS</italic>. Bruker AXS Inc., Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coronado, E., Gal&#x000e1;n-Mascar&#x000f3;s, J. R., G&#x000f3;mes-Garcia, C. J. &#x00026; Laukhin, V. (2000). <italic>Nature</italic>, <bold>408</bold>, 447&#x02013;449.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cruz-Cabeza, A. J. &#x00026; Bernstein, J. (2014). <italic>Chem. Rev.</italic>
<bold>114</bold>, 2170&#x02013;2191.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dornberger-Schiff, K. (1982). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>38</bold>, 483&#x02013;491.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb12"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dornberger-Schiff, K. &#x00026; Grell-Niemann, H. (1961). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic>
<bold>14</bold>, 167&#x02013;177.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Duisenberg, A. J. M., Kroon-Batenburg, L. M. J. &#x00026; Schreurs, A. M. M. (2003). <italic>Appl. Cryst.</italic>
<bold>36</bold>, 220&#x02013;229.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb14"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">&#x0010e;urovi&#x0010d;, S. (1979). <italic>Krist. Tech.</italic>
<bold>14</bold>, 1047&#x02013;1053.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">&#x0010e;urovi&#x0010d;, S. (1997). <italic>EMU Notes Mineral.</italic>
<bold>1</bold>, 3&#x02013;28.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Faria, J. L. de, Hellner, E., Liebau, F., Makovicky, E. &#x00026; Parth&#x000e9;, E. (1990). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>46</bold>, 1&#x02013;11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferraris, G., Makovicky, E. &#x00026; Merlino, S. (2008). <italic>Crystallography of Modular Materials</italic>, Vol. 15, <italic>IUCr Monographs on Crystallography</italic>. Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fichtner, K. (1977<italic>a</italic>). <italic>Krist. Tech.</italic>
<bold>12</bold>, 1263&#x02013;1267.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fichtner, K. (1977<italic>b</italic>). <italic>Beitr. Algebra. Geom.</italic>
<bold>6</bold>, 71&#x02013;99.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fichtner, K. (1979). <italic>Krist. Tech.</italic>
<bold>14</bold>, 1453&#x02013;1461.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fichtner, K. (1986). <italic>Comput. Math. Appl. B</italic>, <bold>12</bold>, 751&#x02013;762.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fuller, L. S., Iddon, B. &#x00026; Smith, K. A. (1999). <italic>J. Chem. Soc. Perkin Trans.</italic> pp. 1273&#x02013;1278.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gilchrist, T. L. (1987). <italic>Adv. Heterocycl. Chem.</italic>
<bold>41</bold>, 41&#x02013;74.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grell, H. (1984). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>40</bold>, 95&#x02013;99.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grell, H. &#x00026; Dornberger-Schiff, K. (1982). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>38</bold>, 49&#x02013;54.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gronowitz, S. &#x00026; Frejd, T. (1978). <italic>Chem. Heterocycl. Compd.</italic>
<bold>14</bold>, 353&#x02013;367.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gronowitz, S. &#x00026; Torbj&#x000f6;rn, F. (1970). <italic>Acta Chem. Scand.</italic>
<bold>24</bold>, 2656&#x02013;2658.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hahn, T. (2006<italic>a</italic>). <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic>, Vol. A, ch. 1.4, pp. 7&#x02013;11. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hahn, T. (2006<italic>b</italic>). <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic>, Vol. D, ch. 3.3, pp. 393&#x02013;448. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Iddon, B. (1983). <italic>Heterocycles</italic>, <bold>20</bold>, 1127&#x02013;1171.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jakobsen, H. J. (1970). <italic>Acta Chem. Scand.</italic>
<bold>24</bold>, 2663&#x02013;2665.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Janssen, T., Chapuis, G. &#x00026; de Boissieu, M. (2007). <italic>Aperiodic Crystals &#x02014; From Modulated Phases to Quasicrystals</italic>, Vol. 21, <italic>IUCr Monographs on Crystallography</italic>. Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Janssen, T., Janner, A., Looijenga-Vos, A. &#x00026; de Wolff, P. M. (2006). <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic>, Vol. C, ch. 9.8, pp. 907&#x02013;955. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb34"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">K&#x000e1;lm&#x000e1;n, A., P&#x000e1;rk&#x000e1;nyi, L. &#x00026; Argay, G. (1993). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> B<bold>49</bold>, 1039&#x02013;1049.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb35"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kopsky, V. &#x00026; Litvin, D. B. (2006). <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic>, Vol. E. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lumpi, D. (2013). Dissertation, Vienna University of Technology, Austria.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb37"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lumpi, D., Gl&#x000f6;cklhofer, F., Holzer, B., St&#x000f6;ger, B., Hametner, C., Reider, G. A. &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;hlich, J. (2014). <italic>Cryst. Growth Des.</italic>
<bold>14</bold>, 1018&#x02013;1031.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb38"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Makovicky, E. (1997). <italic>EMU Notes Mineral.</italic>
<bold>1</bold>, 315&#x02013;343.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb39"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mitzi, D. B. (2001). <italic>J. Chem. Soc. Dalton Trans.</italic> pp. 1&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb40"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mueller, T. J. J. &#x00026; Bunz, U. H. F. (2007). <italic>Functional Organic Materials &#x02013; Syntheses, Strategies and Applications</italic>. IUCr Monographs on Crystallography. Weinheim: Wiley-VCH Verlag.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb41"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Park, S. K., Jackson, T. N., Anthony, J. E. &#x00026; Mourey, D. A. (2007). <italic>Appl. Phys. Lett.</italic>
<bold>91</bold>, 063514.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb42"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pidcock, E. (2005). <italic>Chem. Commun.</italic> pp. 3457&#x02013;3459.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb43"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Palatinus, L. &#x00026; Chapuis, G. (2007). <italic>J. Appl. Cryst.</italic>
<bold>40</bold>, 786&#x02013;790.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb44"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pet&#x00159;&#x000ed;&#x0010d;ek, V., Du&#x00161;ek, M. &#x00026; Palatinus, L. (2014). <italic>Z. Kristallogr.</italic>
<bold>229</bold>, 345&#x02013;352.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb45"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sch&#x000f6;nleber, A. (2011). <italic>Z. Kristallogr.</italic>
<bold>226</bold>, 499&#x02013;517.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb46"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smaalen, S. van (2007). <italic>Incommensurate Crystallography</italic>, Vol. 20, <italic>IUCr Monographs on Crystallography</italic>. Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb47"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smaalen, S. van, Stokes, H. T. &#x00026; Campbell, B. J. (2013). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>69</bold>, 75&#x02013;90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb48"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spackman, M. A. &#x00026; Jayatilaka, D. (2009). <italic>CrystEngComm</italic>, <bold>11</bold>, 19&#x02013;32.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb49"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spackman, M. A. &#x00026; McKinnon, J. J. (2002). <italic>CrystEngComm</italic>, <bold>4</bold>, 378&#x02013;392.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb50"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">St&#x000f6;ger, B., Kautny, P., Lumpi, D., Zobetz, E. &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;hlich, J. (2012). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> B<bold>68</bold>, 667&#x02013;676.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">St&#x000f6;ger, B., Pokorny, B., Lumpi, D., Zobetz, E. &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;hlich, J. (2013). <italic>Z. Kristallogr.</italic>
<bold>228</bold>, 106&#x02013;112.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb52"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">St&#x000f6;ger, B. &#x00026; Weil, M. (2013). <italic>Mineral. Petrol.</italic>
<bold>107</bold>, 253&#x02013;263.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb53"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">St&#x000f6;ger, B., Weil, M. &#x00026; Zobetz, E. (2012). <italic>Z. Kristallogr.</italic>
<bold>227</bold>, 859&#x02013;868.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb54"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stokes, H. T., Campbell, B. J. &#x00026; van Smaalen, S. (2011). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>67</bold>, 45&#x02013;55.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb55"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wolff, S. K., Grimwood, D. J., McKinnon, J. J., Turner, M. J., Jayatilaka, D. &#x00026; Spackman, M. A. (2012). <italic>CrystalExplorer</italic>, Version 3.1. University of Western Australia.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bb56"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wondratschek, H. (1976). <italic>Acta Cryst.</italic> A<bold>32</bold>, 664&#x02013;666.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Crystal structure of TIPS-pentacene (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>) featuring distinct layers of pentacene cores and TIPS groups connected by &#x02014;C&#x000a0;C&#x02014;bridges viewed down [010]. Coordinates taken from Anthony <italic>et al.</italic> (2001<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb5"> &#x025b8;</xref>). H atoms and disorder of the TIPS groups were omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig1"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>General structure of spacer-extended ene&#x02013;yne molecules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig2"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Scope of molecular modifications (bottom) and expected impact on the structures (top).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig3"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Spacer-extended ene&#x02013;yne molecules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig4"/></fig><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Non-spacer-extended ene&#x02013;yne molecules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig5"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Rotational degrees of freedom in spacer-extended molecule.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig6"/></fig><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Characteristic geometries of molecules featuring (<italic>a</italic>) a benzene spacer, (<italic>b</italic>) a thiophene spacer and methylthio groups, (<italic>c</italic>) a thiophene dioxide spacer and methylsulfonyl groups. C, O, S and Si atoms are represented by gray, red, yellow and orange ellipsoids drawn at 90% probability levels, H atoms by white spheres of arbitrary radius.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig7"/></fig><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Scheme of the layer contacts of the title compounds observed in (<italic>a</italic>) the common case, (<italic>b</italic>) oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) and (<italic>c</italic>) polytype II of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) and NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>). Silyl groups are represented by rectangles, the yne fragments by lines and the center unit of the molecules (spacer, methylthio/methylsulfonyl and ene fragment) by ellipses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig8"/></fig><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Structural relationships of the crystals under investigation. Structures crystallizing as layers are marked by a yellow backdrop; those with same and opposite inclination in adjacent layers or little inclination (see Fig. 8<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8"> &#x025b8;</xref>) by green, blue and pink backdrops, respectively. Twinning or antiphase domains are indicated in cursive.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig9"/></fig><fig id="fig10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>The crystal structures of (<italic>a</italic>) BSEM (<bold>1</bold>), (<italic>b</italic>) TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) and (<italic>c</italic>) the basic structure of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) viewed down the monoclinic axis [010]. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity. Symmetry elements with the exception of the glide planes are indicated by the graphical symbols standardized in <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic> (Hahn, 2006<italic>a</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb28"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Boundaries between the <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> layers are indicated by dashed lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig10"/></fig><fig id="fig11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Contact of TMS groups in two adjacent layers of (<italic>a</italic>) BSEM (<bold>1</bold>), (<italic>b</italic>) TSEM (<bold>2</bold>) and (<italic>c</italic>) ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) projected on the layer plane (100). Groups of the lower layer are gray and blurred, other color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity. The extent of the unit cell [of the basic structure in the case of ESEM (<bold>3</bold>)] is indicated by black lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig11"/></fig><fig id="fig12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Chain of (<italic>a</italic>) TSEM (<bold>3</bold>), (<italic>b</italic>) ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) and (<italic>c</italic>) DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) molecules running along [010]. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. In (<italic>b</italic>) intermolecular H&#x022ef;S contacts up to 2.91&#x02005;&#x000c5; are indicated by green rods to highlight the different types of intermolecular contacts. An arrow indicates a twofold rotation of the chain. If it is dashed it is valid only for the basic structure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig12"/></fig><fig id="fig13" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>Distance of the equatorial H112 atoms of the ethylenedioxy bridge in ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) to the S atoms in the adjacent molecules plotted against <italic>t</italic>. The curves of the two H112 atoms are red and black, respectively. The distances to the S atoms of the methylthio groups and the thiophene ring are drawn using continuous and dashed lines, respectively. Gray backdrops mark the ranges where an H atom protrudes into the cavity formed by the three S atoms of the adjacent molecule.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig13"/></fig><fig id="fig14" position="float"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>Overlap of an ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) molecule at 24 equidistant <italic>t</italic> values (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>c</italic>) projected approximately on the molecular plane and (<italic>b</italic>, <italic>d</italic>) viewed down the twofold axis of the basic structure. In (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) the orientation of the molecules from the actual structure is unchanged; In (<italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>) the molecules are rotated to minimize the interatomic distances of the thiophene rings. Bond colors with similar hue signify close <italic>t</italic> values, complementary colors a shift of <italic>t</italic> + 1/2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig14"/></fig><fig id="fig15" position="float"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>All intramolecular bond lengths in ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) involving non-H atoms plotted against <italic>t</italic>. Symmetry-equivalent distances located at <italic>t</italic> + 1/2 are not listed. Color codes: Si&#x02014;C: black; C&#x02014;S aliphatic: pink; C&#x02014;S aromatic: green; C&#x02014;C single bond (spacer to ene, ene to yne and yne to TMS): blue; C&#x02014;O: red dashed; C&#x02014;C aromatic: red; C&#x02014;C double bond: blue dashed; C&#x02014;C triple bond: black dashed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig15"/></fig><fig id="fig16" position="float"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>The crystal structures of polytypes (<italic>a</italic>) I and (<italic>b</italic>) II of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) viewed down [010]. Color codes and symbols as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity. The <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> layers are indicated to the right by brackets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig16"/></fig><fig id="fig17" position="float"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p>Geometrically non-equivalent contacts of two layers in polytypes (<italic>a</italic>) I and (<italic>b</italic>) II of DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) projected on the layer plane (100). The TMS groups and the connecting <italic>sp</italic>
<sup>1</sup> hybridized C atom are shown. Atoms of the lower layer are gray and blurred, color codes of the top layer as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig17"/></fig><fig id="fig18" position="float"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p>Overlap of the DSEM (<bold>4</bold>) molecules in polytypes I and II, drawn in red and blue, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig18"/></fig><fig id="fig19" position="float"><label>Figure 19</label><caption><p>Overlap of the independent oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecules in (<italic>a</italic>) the high-temperature polymorph I and (<italic>b</italic>) the low-temperature polymorph II. The molecules are drawn in red and blue, respectively. H atoms have been omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig19"/></fig><fig id="fig20" position="float"><label>Figure 20</label><caption><p>Layers in polymorphs (<italic>a</italic>) I and (<italic>b</italic>) II of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) viewed approximately along the main axis of the molecules. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity. C&#x02014;H&#x022ef;O and C&#x02014;H&#x022ef;C contacts are indicated by arrows originating from the &#x02018;donor&#x02019; C atoms, C&#x02014;H&#x022ef;H&#x02014;C contacts by double-sided arrows connecting the C atoms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig20"/></fig><fig id="fig21" position="float"><label>Figure 21</label><caption><p>Crystal structures of the polymorphs (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) I and (<italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>) II of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>), viewed down (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>c</italic>) [010] and (<italic>b</italic>, <italic>d</italic>) [100]. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig21"/></fig><fig id="fig22" position="float"><label>Figure 22</label><caption><p>Layer contacts in the polymorphs (<italic>a</italic>) I and (<italic>b</italic>) of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) projected on the layer plane (100). Only the TMS groups are shown. Atoms of the lower layer are gray and blurred, color codes of the top layer as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>. H atoms have been omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig22"/></fig><fig id="fig23" position="float"><label>Figure 23</label><caption><p>
<italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub>/<italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub> fingerprint plots of the oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) molecules in polymorphs (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) I, (<italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>) II and (<italic>e</italic>) III, calculated with <italic>CrystalExplorer</italic> (Wolff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb55"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Regions where H&#x022ef;H, H&#x022ef;O and H&#x022ef;C dominate are drawn in yellow, red and blue, respectively, other regions in gray. Brighter colors indicate a higher proportion of the surface. Regions discussed in the text connecting two <italic>B</italic> molecules or <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> molecules are marked by green and red ellipses, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig23"/></fig><fig id="fig24" position="float"><label>Figure 24</label><caption><p>Crystal structure of polymorph III of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) viewed down [100]. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig24"/></fig><fig id="fig25" position="float"><label>Figure 25</label><caption><p>The crystal structure of oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>) viewed down (<italic>a</italic>) [010] and (<italic>b</italic>) [100]. The location of the <italic>A<sub>n</sub></italic> layers is indicated by brackets to the right. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig25"/></fig><fig id="fig26" position="float"><label>Figure 26</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the symmetry of the (<italic>a</italic>) MDO<sub>1</sub> and (<italic>b</italic>) MDO<sub>2</sub> polytypes of oxESEM (<bold>3<italic>b</italic></bold>). Triangles are black on one and white on the other side. (Partial) symmetry operations of a layer and relating adjacent layers are indicated by the graphical symbols standardized in <italic>International Tables for Crystallography</italic> (Hahn, 2006<italic>a</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bb28"> &#x025b8;</xref>). Additionally for operations with non-crystallographic intrinsic translations the printed symbol is given.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig26"/></fig><fig id="fig27" position="float"><label>Figure 27</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) The NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) molecule viewed down two different directions, showing the different conformations of the methylthio group with respect to the TBDMS groups (top group: <italic>gauche</italic>, bottom group: <italic>eclipsed</italic>) and (<italic>c</italic>) crystal structure of NSEM-TBDMS (<bold>5</bold>) viewed down [100]. H atoms have been omitted for clarity. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig27"/></fig><fig id="fig28" position="float"><label>Figure 28</label><caption><p>The crystal structure of ASYM (<bold>6</bold>) viewed down (<italic>a</italic>) [100] and (<italic>b</italic>) [001]. The <italic>A</italic>
<sup>1</sup> and <italic>A</italic>
<sup>2</sup> OD layers are marked by a gray and white backdrop, respectively. The boundaries of the crystallochemical layers are indicated by dotted lines. Color codes as in Fig. 7<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig28"/></fig><fig id="fig29" position="float"><label>Figure 29</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the symmetry of the (<italic>a</italic>) MDO<sub>1</sub> and (<italic>b</italic>) MDO<sub>2</sub> polytypes of ASYM (<bold>6</bold>). Symbols as in Fig. 26<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig26"> &#x025b8;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-fig29"/></fig><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Torsion angles in the title compounds ()</title><p>For structures with two crystallographically different molecules each molecule is listed in a separate row. For the incommensurately modulated ESEM (<bold>3</bold>) minimum and maximum values are indicated. For thiophene spacers the S atom was used as terminal atom, for benzene spacers the C atom with a torsion angle &#x0003e;90. For the CSi(CC)CC torsion angle the atom with the angle closest to 0 or 180 was chosen.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Molecule</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">CCspacer</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">CC(spacer)CC</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">CCSCH<sub>3</sub>
</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">CSi(CC)CC</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">BSEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">144.26(8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">138.00(6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">30.09(8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">TSEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">152.0(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">68.5(5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">129.3(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">28.8(4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ESEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">156.36165.31(12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">47.452.4(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">149.81162.53(17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">149.81162.53(17)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">DSEM, polytype I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">156.66(19), 163.93(17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">50.2(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">121.71(19), 111.17(19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">160.0(2), 158.9(2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">DSEM, polytype II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">157.1(4), 162.7(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">51.4(7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">124.7(4), 111.2(5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">160.8(4), 22.1(5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxBSEM, polymorph I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">132.80(11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">57.32(11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">151.46(10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">131.49(10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">62.46(9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">24.84(10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxBSEM, polymorph II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">127.7(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">71.8(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">176.7(5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">128.5(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">109.2(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">29.9(3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxBSEM, polymorph III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">124.93(17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char=" " charoff="50" valign="top">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">84.82(15) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">23.9(18)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxESEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">44.6(3), 63.7(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">14.9(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">80.0(2), 66.8(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">159.6(2), 151.0(2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">46.2(3), 64.2(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">17.2(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">78.8(2), 67.8(3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">159.6(2), 153.4(2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">NSEM-TBDMS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">76.32(12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">179.50(7), 164.04(8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">170.82(7), 10.18(8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ASYM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">179.3(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="char" char="." charoff="50" valign="top">166.7(2), 178.4(2)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Symmetry of the overall structures and the molecular layers and operations relating adjacent layers in the crystals under investigation</title><p>For the incommensurately modulated ESEM (<bold>3</bold>), symmetry and operations of the basic structure are listed. Pseudosymmetry of OD structures is not listed.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Structure</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Space group</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Layer group</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Operations relating adjacent layers </th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">BSEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>C</italic>2/<italic>c</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>(1)2/<italic>c</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi42.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, 2<sub>1</sub> [010], <italic>n</italic> [010]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">TSEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>I</italic>2/<italic>c</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>(1)2/<italic>c</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi44.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, 2<sub>1</sub> [010], <italic>a</italic> [010]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ESEM, basic structure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>I</italic>2/<italic>c</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>(1)2/<italic>c</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi44.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, 2<sub>1</sub> [010], <italic>a</italic> [010]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">DSEM, polytype I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>C</italic>2/<italic>c</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>(1)2<sub>1</sub>/<italic>c</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi48.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, 2<sub>1</sub> [010], <italic>n</italic> [010]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">DSEM, polytype II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>Pccn</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>(1)2<sub>1</sub>/<italic>c</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2<sub>1</sub> [100], <italic>c</italic> [100], 2 [001], <italic>n</italic> [001]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxBSEM, polymorph I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi50.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><bold>c</bold></sub>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxBSEM, polymorph II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi50.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><bold>c</bold></sub>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">oxESEM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi50.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><bold>c</bold></sub>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">NSEM-TBDMS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>P</italic>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>p</italic>12<sub>1</sub>(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2<sub>1</sub> [100], 2<sub>1</sub> [001]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ASYM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi21.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi39.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="m-02-00584-efi41.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><bold>b</bold></sub>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Prominent intermolecular contacts in the <italic>d</italic>
<sub>i</sub>/<italic>d</italic>
<sub>e</sub> fingerprint plots of the I and II polymorphs of oxBSEM (<bold>1<italic>b</italic></bold>) marked in Fig. 23<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig23"> &#x025b8;</xref>
</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Polymorph I</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Polymorph II</th></tr><tr><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Region</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Atoms</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Molecular groups</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Atoms</th><th style="border-bottom:1px solid black;" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Molecular groups</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C5H5O2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">enesulfone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C11H112C7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Methylsulfoneyne</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C11H113C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Methylsulfonebenzene</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C11H111C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Methylsufonebenzene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C11H112C2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Methylsulfonebenzene</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C9H93O2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">TMSsulfone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C5H5O2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Enesulfone</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C5H5O1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Enesulfone</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C3H3H3C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Benzenebenzene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>