<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html><body><tei xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemalocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd">
<teiheader xml:lang="en">
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<title level="a" type="main">National and Global Petroleum Assessment Assessment of Undiscovered, Technically Recoverable Conventional Oil and Gas Resources in the</title>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher></publisher>
<availability status="unknown"><licence></licence></availability>
<date type="published" when="2024-01">January 2024</date>
</publicationstmt>
<sourcedesc>
<biblstruct>
<analytic>
<author>
<affiliation key="aff0">
<note type="raw_affiliation">Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation</note>
<orgname type="laboratory">Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation</orgname>
</affiliation>
</author>
<title level="a" type="main">National and Global Petroleum Assessment Assessment of Undiscovered, Technically Recoverable Conventional Oil and Gas Resources in the</title>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2024-01">January 2024</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<idno type="MD5">1264C29776EF61241AF0857E620ED87A</idno>
</biblstruct>
</sourcedesc>
</filedesc>
<encodingdesc>
<appinfo>
<application ident="GROBID" version="0.8.0" when="2024-05-03T09:06+0000">
<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"></ref>
</application>
</appinfo>
</encodingdesc>
<profiledesc>
<abstract></abstract>
</profiledesc>
</teiheader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Introduction<p><s>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) has conducted a quantitative assessment of the undiscovered, technically recoverable conventional oil and gas resources in reservoirs within the Upper Jurassic (Oxfordian) Smackover Formation across the onshore Gulf Coast basin, including State waters, in Texas, Louisiana, Arkansas, Mississippi, Alabama, and Florida.</s><s>The Smackover Formation is one of the most developed units within the Upper Jurassic-Cretaceous-Tertiary Composite Total Petroleum System (TPS; <ref target="#b3" type="bibr">Condon and Dyman, 2006</ref>; fig.</s><s><ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">1</ref>), with drilling and production activities dating back to the 1920s.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Geologic Background<p><s>The Smackover Formation comprises strata deposited during a widespread marine transgression in the Gulf of Mexico Basin and formed a regionally extensive carbonate shelf during the Late Jurassic (Oxfordian; <ref target="#b9" type="bibr">Salvador, 1991)</ref>.</s><s>Two informal intervals of the Smackover Formation are generally recognized.</s><s>The lower part of the Smackover Formation (also informally named the Brown Dense shale), composed of organic-rich calcareous shales overlying the Upper Jurassic Norphlet Formation, serves as the source for oil and gas found in numerous overlying reservoirs, including the grain-supported limestones and packstones of the    upper part of the Smackover.</s><s>Though the formation is primarily regarded as calcareous, there are sandstone deposits in some landward areas, including central Mississippi, southeastern Arkansas, and northeastern Louisiana due to fluvial input.</s><s>Porosity of carbonates in the upper part of the Smackover Formation is highly variable due to differences in ooid content and degree of dolomitization.</s><s>A variety of diagenetic alteration processes affect porosity, including the influence of meteoric water generating gypsum brines from anhydrites of the Upper Jurassic Buckner Formation <ref target="#b4" type="bibr">(Heydari, 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Differences in the petroleum system across the formation from east to west are related to variability in (1) heat flux affecting thermal history, (2) organic matter type affecting the timing of oil generation and petroleum properties, and (3) thermochemical sulfate reduction affecting hydrocarbon preservation.</s></p><p><s>Factors related to the technical recoverability of hydrocarbons in conventional Smackover Formation accumulations were accounted for in the development of assessment unit (AU) boundaries.</s><s>Pressure and temperature limits on drilling were evaluated and determined based on published reports and information obtained from operators regarding the limitations of drilling and completion equipment <ref type="bibr">(Whidden and others, 2023)</ref>.</s><s>Three-dimensional basin modeling was conducted using stratigraphic, lithologic, and temperature data <ref type="bibr">(IHS Markit, 2021)</ref>.</s><s>The model established basin-wide burial history trends and helped delineate depths to maximum temperatures and pressures.</s><s>Specifically, the assessment excluded areas where reservoirs were estimated to be beyond technically recoverable limits based on the presence of excessively high temperatures or pressures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Assessment Units<p><s>The petroleum-system framework is the basis for defining assessment units (AUs) in the USGS assessment process.</s><s>Based on this approach, five conventional AUs were defined in the Smackover Formation (fig.</s><s><ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">1</ref>; table 1; <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">Birdwell and Schenk, 2024)</ref>.</s><s>These AUs were differentiated based on four principal criteria: (1) spatial and stratigraphic variability in lithologies within the Smackover <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">(Snedden and Galloway, 2019)</ref>; (2) the presence and extent of peripheral faults, salt basins, and other structural features compiled from a wide range of sources; (3) thermal maturity boundaries based on vitrinite reflectance equivalence (VR oe , in percent) and gas-to-oil ratio data (IHS Markit, 2021), which determined the dominant form of petroleum present (oil or gas); and (4) degree of siliciclastic influence from the ancestral Mississippi River delta <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">(Shew and Garner, 1990)</ref>.</s><s>The fourth factor has a complex impact on oil and gas prospects in the area of influence because it could account for additional conventional reservoirs, but it may also facilitate migration of oil and gas out of the Smackover Formation or dilute the source rock quality of the lower part of the Smackover.</s><s>Additional field-scale petroleum system properties across the region were obtained from Nehring Associates Inc. ( <ref type="formula">2018</ref>) and were also considered in defining AUs.</s></p><p><s>Both the Smackover Western and Eastern Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AUs are located within the extent of the inner platform ramp and carbonate shelf depositional environments defined and refined during the last 30 years (Snedden and Galloway, 2019 and references therein).</s><s>These AUs are bounded to the north by the extent of deposition of the Smackover Formation in the onshore Gulf Coast or the onset of oil generation based on thermal maturity (greater than 0.55 percent VR oe ) and gas-to-oil ratios calculated from cumulative production (greater than 20,000 cubic feet of natural gas per barrel of oil).</s><s>They are bounded to the south by the downdip 1.78 percent VR oe thermal maturity boundary for oil to gas cracking or by State waters.</s><s>Differences in the stratigraphy within the upper part of the Smackover <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">(Budd and Loucks, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mancini and others, 2004;</ref><ref target="#b5" type="bibr">Heydari and Baria, 2006)</ref> and in properties of the organic matter in the lower part of the Smackover <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">(Sassen, 1989)</ref> are distinguishing factors between these AUs.</s><s>For example, microbialites have only been identified as important features in the Eastern Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone AU, mainly in southeastern Alabama.</s></p><p><s>The Smackover East-Central Interbedded Sandstone and Carbonate Shoal Conventional Oil and Gas AU is distinguished from the updip and peripheral fault zone AUs by the presence of a thick fluvial sandstone package deposited between them by the ancestral Mississippi River.</s><s>It is also bounded to the north by the known extent of Smackover deposition and to the south by the 1.78 percent VR oe thermal maturity line.</s></p><p><s>The Smackover Peripheral Fault Zone and Carbonate Shelf Conventional Oil and Gas AU is located within the inner platform and carbonate shelf depositional environments but is defined to the north by the 1.78 percent VR oe thermal maturity boundary for gas generation.</s><s>Downdip limits vary across the AU and are either defined by the extent of the inner platform ramp and carbonate shelf depositional environments or the limits of the modeled 260 degrees Celsius temperature or 25,000 pounds per square-inch pressure cutoff lines for technically recoverable conventional resources (cutoff is determined by whichever boundary is farthest inland from the coastline).</s></p><p><s>The Smackover Downdip Salt Basin Conventional Oil and Gas AU is defined to the north by the extent of carbonate ramp and shelf deposition and to the south by the technically recoverable boundaries related to temperature and pressure described above.</s><s>The depositional environment for this AU is represented by the open shelf-outer platform described by <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">Snedden and Galloway (2019)</ref>.</s><s>The Smackover Formation is currently undrilled in this area, but because of the anticipated absence of the reservoir facies typical of the upper part of the Smackover, traps and reservoirs are expected to be related to salt structures and debris flows carrying sands sourced from fluvial inputs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Undiscovered, Technically Recoverable Resources Summary<p><s>The USGS assessed undiscovered, technically recoverable resources for five conventional AUs in the Smackover Formation of the U.S. Gulf Coast region.</s><s>The estimated mean totals for conventional oil and gas resources (table 2) are 143 million barrels of oil (MMBO), with an F95-F5 range from 83 to 227 MMBO; 1,084 billion cubic feet of gas (BCFG), with an F95-F5 range from 393 to 2,317 BCFG; and 72 million barrels of natural gas liquids (MMBNGL), with an F95-F5 range from 26 to 154 MMBNGL.</s></p></div><figure xml:id="fig_0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><label></label><figdesc><div><p><s>Cretaceous-Tertiary Composite Total Petroleum System boundary is shown in plum</s></p></div></figdesc></figure>
<figure xml:id="fig_1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Figure 1 .<label>1</label><figdesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Map showing location of five Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation conventional oil and gas assessment units (AUs) in the U.S. Gulf Coast region.</s></p></div></figdesc><graphic coords="1,58.20,425.92,354.66,268.53" type="bitmap"></graphic></figure>
<figure xml:id="fig_2" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><label></label><figdesc><div><p><s>Using a geology-based assessment methodology, the U.S. Geological Survey estimated undiscovered, technically recoverable mean resources of 143 million barrels of oil and 1,084 billion cubic feet of natural gas in conventional accumulations for the Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation in the onshore U.S. Gulf Coast region.</s></p></div></figdesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><label></label><figdesc><div><p></p></div></figdesc><graphic coords="4,27.95,562.31,560.16,170.28" type="bitmap"></graphic></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">CUB EXPLANATION Smackover Western Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover Eastern Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover East-Central Interbedded Sand and Carbonate Shoal Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover Peripheral Fault Zone and Carbonate Shelf Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover Downdip Salt Basin Conventional Oil and Gas AU Upper Jurassic-Cretaceous-Tertiary Composite Total Petroleum System (part) Base<label></label><figdesc></figdesc><table><row><cell>GULF OF MEXICO</cell></row></table><note><p><s>map from U.S. Department of the Interior, National Park Service</s></p></note></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Table 1 .<label>1</label><figdesc><div><p><s>Key input data for five conventional oil and gas assessment units in the Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation, U.S. Gulf Coast region.</s><s>Shading indicates not applicable.</s><s>AU, assessment unit; MMBO, million barrels of oil; BCFG, billion cubic feet of gas]</s></p></div></figdesc><table></table><note><p><s>[</s></p></note></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_2" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Assessment input data- Conventional AUs Smackover Western Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover Eastern Updip and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU Minimum Median Maximum Calculated mean Minimum Median Maximum Calculated mean<label></label><figdesc></figdesc><table><row><cell>Number of oil fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>30.7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>40.6</cell></row><row><cell>Number of gas fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10.3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>11.0</cell></row><row><cell>Size of oil fields (MMBO)</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>1.6</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>1.9</cell></row><row><cell>Size of gas fields (BCFG)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>400</cell><cell>12.8</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>500</cell><cell>13.9</cell></row><row><cell>AU probability</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment input data-</cell><cell cols="2">Smackover East-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Conventional AUs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_3" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Central Interbedded Sand and Carbonate Shoal Conventional Oil and Gas AU Smackover Peripheral Fault Zone and Carbonate Shelf Conventional Oil and Gas AU Minimum Median Maximum Calculated mean Minimum Median Maximum Calculated mean<label></label><figdesc></figdesc><table><row><cell>Number of oil fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>5.3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5.1</cell></row><row><cell>Number of gas fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5.1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>11.4</cell></row><row><cell>Size of oil fields (MMBO)</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1.1</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1.1</cell></row><row><cell>Size of gas fields (BCFG)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>300</cell><cell>9.9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>500</cell><cell>13.9</cell></row><row><cell>AU probability</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment input data-Conventional AUs</cell><cell cols="4">Smackover Downdip Salt Basins Conventional Oil and Gas AU Minimum Median Maximum Calculated mean</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of oil fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>3.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of gas fields</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>32.3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Size of oil fields (MMBO)</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1.1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Size of gas fields (BCFG)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>400</cell><cell>12.9</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AU probability</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_4" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Table 2 .<label>2</label><figdesc><div><p><s>Quantitative results for five conventional oil and gas assessment units in the Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation, U.S. Gulf Coast region.</s><s>Results shown are fully risked estimates.</s><s>F95 represents a 95-percent chance of at least the amount tabulated; other fractiles are defined similarly.</s><s>Shading indicates not applicable.</s><s>MMBO, million barrels of oil; BCFG, billion cubic feet of gas; NGL, natural gas liquids; MMBNGL, million barrels of natural gas liquids]</s></p></div></figdesc><table></table><note><p><s>[</s></p></note></figure>
<figure type="table" xml:id="tab_5" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Total petroleum system and assessment units (AUs) AU probability Accumulation type Total undiscovered resources Oil (MMBO) Gas (BCFG) NGL (MMBNGL)<label></label><figdesc></figdesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>F95</cell><cell>F50</cell><cell cols="3">F5 Mean F95</cell><cell>F50</cell><cell>F5</cell><cell cols="2">Mean F95</cell><cell>F50</cell><cell cols="2">F5 Mean</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="7">Jurassic-Cretaceous-Tertiary Composite Total Petroleum System</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Smackover Western Updip</cell><cell></cell><cell>Oil</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>81</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>97</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>50</cell><cell>110</cell><cell>294</cell><cell>132</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Smackover Eastern Updip</cell><cell></cell><cell>Oil</cell><cell>45</cell><cell cols="2">73 117</cell><cell>76</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>87</cell><cell>141</cell><cell>91</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>and Peripheral Fault Zone Conventional Oil and Gas AU</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>38</cell><cell>122</cell><cell>385</cell><cell>154</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>Smackover East-Central</cell><cell></cell><cell>Oil</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Interbedded Sand and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Carbonate Shoal Conventional Oil and</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>18</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>126</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Gas AU</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Smackover Peripheral Fault</cell><cell></cell><cell>Oil</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Zone and Carbonate Shelf Conventional Oil and Gas AU</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>34</cell><cell>122</cell><cell>412</cell><cell>159</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Smackover Downdip Salt</cell><cell></cell><cell>Oil</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Basins Conventional Oil and Gas AU</cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>154</cell><cell>372</cell><cell>821</cell><cell>414</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>Total undiscovered conventional resources</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>83</cell><cell>137</cell><cell>227</cell><cell>143</cell><cell>393</cell><cell cols="3">930 2,317 1,084</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>154</cell><cell>72</cell></row></table></figure>
<back>
<div type="funding">
<div><p>, <rs type="institution">U.S. Gulf Coast</rs>, 2022</p></div>
</div> <div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Smackover Formation Assessment Team<p><s>Justin E. Birdwell, Katherine J. Whidden, Stanley T. Paxton, Scott A. Kinney, Rand D. Gardner, Janet K. Pitman, Katherine L. French, Tracey J. Mercier, Cheryl A. Woodall, Heidi M. Leathers-Miller, and Christopher J. Schenk</s></p></div> </div>
<div type="references">
<listbibl>
<biblstruct xml:id="b0">
<monogr>
<ptr target="ttps://www.usgs.gov/programs/energy-resources-program"></ptr>
<title level="m">Assessment results are also available at the USGS Energy Resources Program website</title>
<imprint></imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Assessment results are also available at the USGS Energy Resources Program website, at h ttps://www .usgs.gov/ programs/ energy-resources-program. References Cited</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b1">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">USGS Gulf Coast Petroleum Systems Project-Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation conventional resources, assessment unit boundaries, assessment input data, and fact sheet data tables</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Birdwell</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schenk</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.5066/P9YS1X7P</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5066/P9YS1X7P"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">U.S. Geological Survey data release</title>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Birdwell, J.E., and Schenk, C.J., 2024, USGS Gulf Coast Petroleum Systems Project-Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation conventional resources, assessment unit boundaries, assessment input data, and fact sheet data tables: U.S. Geological Survey data release, available at https://doi.org/10.5066/P9YS1X7P.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b2">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Smackover and Lower Buckner Formations South Texas-Depositional systems on a Jurassic carbonate ramp: University of Texas at Austin</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Budd</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Loucks</surname></persname>
</author>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">Bureau of Economic Geology Report of Investigations</title>
<imprint>
<biblscope unit="volume">112</biblscope>
<biblscope unit="page">38</biblscope>
<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Budd, D.A., and Loucks, R.G., 1981, Smackover and Lower Buckner Formations South Texas-Depositional systems on a Jurassic carbonate ramp: University of Texas at Austin, Bureau of Economic Geology Report of Investigations No. 112, 38 p.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b3">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">geologic assessment of undiscovered conventional oil and gas resources in the Upper Cretaceous Navarro and Taylor Groups</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Condon</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dyman</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.3133/ds69H2</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3133/ds69H2"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS</title>
<imprint>
<biblscope unit="page">42</biblscope>
<date type="published" when="2003-02-04">2006. 2003. February 4, 2021</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note>Western Gulf Province, Texas</note>
<note type="raw_reference">Condon, S.M., and Dyman, T.S., 2006, 2003 geologic assessment of undiscovered conventional oil and gas resources in the Upper Cretaceous Navarro and Taylor Groups, Western Gulf Province, Texas: U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS-69-H, chap. 2, 42 p., accessed February 4, 2021, at https://doi.org/10.3133/ds69H2.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b4">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Meteoric versus burial control on porosity evolution of the Smackover Formation</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Heydari</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.1306/07070302009</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1306/07070302009"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin</title>
<imprint>
<biblscope unit="volume">87</biblscope>
<biblscope from="1779" to="1797" unit="page"></biblscope>
<date type="published" when="2003-02-04">2003. February 4, 2021</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Heydari, E., 2003, Meteoric versus burial control on porosity evolution of the Smackover Formation: American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin, v. 87, p. 1779-1797, accessed February 4, 2021, at https://doi.org/10.1306/07070302009.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b5">
<analytic>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Heydari</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baria</surname></persname>
</author>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="m">Sequence stratigraphy of the Smackover Formation in the north-central U.S. Gulf Coast</title>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 90056</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Heydari, E., and Baria, L.R., 2006, Sequence stratigraphy of the Smackover Formation in the north-central U.S. Gulf Coast: AAPG Search and Discovery Article 90056.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b6">
<monogr>
<title level="m" type="main">Enerdeq US well history and production database</title>
<ptr target="https://www.ihsmarkit.com"></ptr>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2021-06-04">2021. June 4, 2021</date>
<publisher>IHS Markit</publisher>
<pubplace>Englewood, Colo; Inverness Way East, Englewood, CO 80112</pubplace>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">IHS Markit, 2021, Enerdeq US well history and production database: Englewood, Colo., IHS Markit, accessed June 4, 2021, at https://www.ihsmarkit.com. [Available from IHS Markit, 15 Inverness Way East, Englewood, CO 80112.]</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b7">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Upper Jurassic transgressive-regressive sequences, Mississippi Interior Salt Basin area</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mancini</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Obid</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Puckett</surname></persname>
</author>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">Gulf Coast Association of Geological Societies Transactions</title>
<imprint>
<biblscope unit="volume">54</biblscope>
<biblscope from="415" to="424" unit="page"></biblscope>
<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Mancini, E.A., Obid, J.A., and Puckett, T.M., 2004, Upper Jurassic transgressive-regressive sequences, Mississippi Interior Salt Basin area: Gulf Coast Association of Geological Societies Transactions, v. 54, p. 415-424.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b8">
<monogr>
<title level="m" type="main">The significant oil and gas fields of the United States database [data current as of December 2018</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">Nehring</forename><surname>Associates</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">Inc</forename></persname>
</author>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
<publisher>Colorado Springs, Colo., Nehring Associates Inc</publisher>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note>database</note>
<note type="raw_reference">Nehring Associates Inc., 2018, The significant oil and gas fields of the United States database [data current as of December 2018]: Colorado Springs, Colo., Nehring Associates Inc., database.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b9">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Triassic-Jurassic</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salvador</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.1130/DNAG-GNA-J.389</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1130/DNAG-GNA-J.389"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="m">The Gulf of Mexico Basin</title>
<editor>
<persname><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salvador</surname></persname>
</editor>
<meeting><address><addrline>Boulder, Colo</addrline></address></meeting>
<imprint>
<publisher>The Geology of North America</publisher>
<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
<biblscope from="131" to="180" unit="page"></biblscope>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Salvador, A., 1991, Triassic-Jurassic, in Salvador, A., ed., The Gulf of Mexico Basin: Boulder, Colo., Geological Society of America, The Geology of North America, v. J, p. 131-180. [Also available at https://doi.org/10.1130/DNAG-GNA-J.389.]</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b10">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Migration of crude oil from the Smackover source rock to Jurassic and Cretaceous reservoirs of the northern Gulf rim</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sassen</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0146-6380(89)90018-1</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0146-6380(89)90018-1"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="j">Organic Geochemistry</title>
<imprint>
<biblscope unit="volume">14</biblscope>
<biblscope unit="issue">1</biblscope>
<biblscope from="51" to="60" unit="page"></biblscope>
<date type="published" when="1989-02-04">1989. February 4, 2021</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Sassen, R., 1989, Migration of crude oil from the Smackover source rock to Jurassic and Cretaceous reservoirs of the northern Gulf rim: Organic Geochemistry, v. 14, no. 1, p. 51-60, accessed February 4, 2021, at https://doi.org/10.1016/0146-6380(89)90018-1.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b11">
<analytic>
<title level="a" type="main">Reservoir characteristics of nearshore and shelf sandstones in the Jurassic Smackover Formation, Thomasville field, Mississippi</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shew</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Garner</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4613-8988-0_19</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4613-8988-0_19"></ptr>
</analytic>
<monogr>
<title level="m">Sandstone petroleum reservoirs</title>
<editor>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barwis</surname></persname>
</editor>
<editor>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persname>
</editor>
<editor>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R J</forename><surname>Studdick</surname></persname>
</editor>
<meeting><address><addrline>New York</addrline></address></meeting>
<imprint>
<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
<date type="published" when="1990-02-04">1990. February 4, 2021</date>
<biblscope from="437" to="464" unit="page"></biblscope>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Shew, R.D., and Garner, M.M., 1990, Reservoir characteristics of nearshore and shelf sandstones in the Jurassic Smackover Formation, Thomasville field, Mississippi, in Barwis, J.H., McPherson, J.G., and Studdick, J.R.J., eds., Sandstone petroleum reservoirs: New York, Springer-Verlag, p. 437-464, accessed February 4, 2021, at https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4613-8988-0_19.</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b12">
<monogr>
<title level="m" type="main">The Gulf of Mexico Sedimentary Basin-Depositional evolution and petroleum applications</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Snedden</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Galloway</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.1017/9781108292795</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/9781108292795"></ptr>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
<biblscope unit="page">326</biblscope>
<pubplace>Cambridge, U.K.</pubplace>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Snedden, J.W., and Galloway, W.E., 2019, The Gulf of Mexico Sedimentary Basin-Depositional evolution and petroleum applications: Cambridge, U.K., Cambridge University Press, 326 p. [Also available at https://doi.org/10.1017/9781108292795.]</note>
</biblstruct>
<biblstruct xml:id="b13">
<monogr>
<title level="m" type="main">Assessment of continuous oil and gas resources in the Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation of the onshore U.S. Gulf Coast</title>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Whidden</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Birdwell</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kinney</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Paxton</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Pitman</surname></persname>
</author>
<author>
<persname><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schenk</surname></persname>
</author>
<idno type="DOI">10.3133/fs20233021</idno>
<idno>2023-3021</idno>
<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3133/fs20233021"></ptr>
<imprint>
<date type="published" when="2022-09">2023. 2022. September 2023</date>
<publisher>U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet</publisher>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<note type="raw_reference">Whidden, K.W., Birdwell, J.E., Gardner, R.D., Kinney, S.A., Paxton, S.T., Pitman, J.K., Schenk, C.J., 2023, Assessment of continuous oil and gas resources in the Upper Jurassic Smackover Formation of the onshore U.S. Gulf Coast, 2022: U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet 2023-3021, accessed September 2023 at https://doi.org/10.3133/fs20233021.</note>
</biblstruct>
</listbibl>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</tei>
</body></html>